e
e e
I will
call 6:30 I'll call this meeting order
and let's start with
pledge I pledge aliance to the flag of
the United States of America and to the
Republic for which it stands one nation
under God indivisible with liy and
justice
thank you
everyone if we can I know our clerk
letter is on Zoom um if you would like
to do roll call for
us thank you Madame mayor mayor Smith
here mayor protm Valentine
here trusty shelter
here trusty Schwarz
trusty check here oh
Che trusty Hunter
here trusty heck
here you have a quorum thank you did
truste Schwarz join oh okay good oh very
good now I see her great um the next
part of the agenda is the approval of
the agenda and I I have two requests of
the trustees about modifying the agenda
and the first is that we have been asked
by the two
entities that are Legacy events if we
would remove action item number three
consideration of creating a Legacy Event
designation if we would remove it from
this agenda agenda and continue it to
another meeting so that's one change I
wanted to bring up to you all and um
secondly we have an executive session
scheduled for the end of the agenda and
we have uh one trustee that cannot stay
past 9:30 and another that may not be
able to
participate for the entire meeting
therefore I'd like to ask you all to
move the executive session up to after
action item number
two um yeah that would work action item
number two so we will have action item
number one the S strr Rentals we'll go
ahead and do action item number two
which I don't we take much time and then
and then the executive session and then
when we get back continue where we are
but I want to say that I may in the
middle of the meeting ask I mean when we
get back in the session depending on
timing I may ask that we also that we um
change the agenda at that time but we'll
see how time from minut so if that makes
any sense and somebody would be willing
to distill what I just said into a
motion that would be wonderful I would
like to make make a motion that we move
the executive first of all that we move
the action
item
of the uh Legacy events to another
meeting I think that should be own
motion let's that all in favor of that
modification to the agenda I
I any
opposed okay that motion pass pass es
thank you then I'd like to move the
executive session until a to after
action item number
two we hear a second
second any uh discussion about that
potential
change okay hearing none all in favor I
I all right any
oppose not so with that
can we I believe we now need a specific
motion to approve the agenda if that's
correct okay can we have a third
motion I'd like to make a motion to
approve the agenda as
amended a second then right all in favor
hi
hi thank you
everyone so we will move on to
announcements and I am going to turn
that over to um CL better
if you're
prepared if not I can do
it no I've got it thank you Madame mayor
sure um so as you see we're still
seeking um applications and letters of
interest for our opening on the Zoning
Board of adjustment um which is why it's
on here again and um we actually have uh
three terms on the tree board coming up
for reappointment
so um we're seeking uh applications and
letters of interest for that and if we
can have any applications and letters of
interest for either vacancy by December
4th so it can go on our first meeting in
December which is typically our last of
the year it would be nice to go into the
new year with everybody knowing they're
going on to
committees um thank you can we add that
if anyone in the public has questions
they can contact you for more
information absolutely I'm more than
happy to um answer any questions that
somebody might have okay thank you any
other announcements from the trustees
anybody
online hearing none we'll move on to the
part of the agenda where anyone in the
public whether in the building with us
here or on Zoom if you have any comment
you would like to make you have three
minutes to speak on any item that is not
on our agenda tonight so with that um
would anyone in the room like to come up
and speak on any topic not on the
agenda okay seeing none anyone on
Zoom see any hands but I might not see
them okay no hands raised all right
thank you um we'll then move on to the
consent
agenda which consists of two meeting
minutes the first for our October 22nd
regular meeting and the second for our
November 12th regular meeting and we
also have dispersements on the consent
agenda are there any um comments from
anyone any trustees on any of the
content for the consent
agenda hearing none nobody on
Zoom okay with that um can we have a
motion to approve the consent agenda I
make a motion to approve the consent
agenda I'll second that okay all in
favor I I all right thank you that
motion passes and we are to staff
reports with the departmental scorecard
if anyone is following on their agenda
packet the scorecard is starting on page
28 um okay so departmental score card
has been updated um we just keep
updating this uh I don't think it's been
posted to the website in some time I'm
going to ask that it does posted after
this one um so that it's that that it's
available for public
consumption
um every department has
updated um the one thing that you are G
to uh which which is on here that you
will see soon is a new sign com up at
app Valley Park um and a sign
box what's the new sign um it is uh
about
uh the jumbo Mountain
Trail and that's a sign that was given
to us
by yes
yeah did anyone have any questions for
our administrator on the
scorecard seeing none we'll turn it over
to police chief ler for his report
okay the department like to thank K
Parks and Wildlife us for service and
the Delta County Sheriff's Department
for joining one of our officers up the
park during a trumpet treat for
Halloween it was really great to see all
those agencies kind of working together
in one
spot members of Department have
completed C first aid training and
certification that's an annual training
for us we do that every year this year
the train was provided by Blake ker
who's also the fire chief like to thank
him for his time and support after very
helpful to have somebody come here and
do
that also the department has changed
vendors for PD stickers stickers are
used means of commity OB are frequently
given out to Local Schools as well as
events throughout the year I've placed
some of the stickers at the door for the
public to see the new vendor is grit and
Grace it's a local company which is
owned by a PD officer's wife coats are
attached for comparison purposes
the new purchasing policy was followed
and the Town Administrator was consulted
during the purchasing process and
ultimately the change in vendors
resulted in approximately 39% savings on
sticker
purchases couple things with without one
was
that by switching vendors she was able
to reduce the total number of stickers
we had to buy at a time some places
wanted 500 or500 of a single type of
sticker she's able to do much smaller
Commodities um she also designed those
for recharge no tax no shipping um I'm
being told she makes about two cents
profit per sticker so that was part of
the reason we switched
so and you also notice the quotes that
are attached show to the other
cost so the cost savings was pretty
beneficial for us
but in the name of transparency we
wanted to point out she has married one
of our Patrol officers but they did not
come to us we went to them she's part of
a an organization called called
operation rehydration where they provide
drinks to First Responders law
enforcement give
and when she brought some drinks up to
the
department we were talking to her about
some other things she does and she
mentioned that she does stick and things
like that so we actually approach them
about try to reduce
our the last thing I'll add
is the Department's working with the
staff at County gate to recognize
students who exhibit soaring Behavior
the department purchases youth bicycle
helmet to a reward for those students
and the helmets will be given out
quarterly until the end of the 23 24
school
year so the way this works is that our
school resource officers up County K
Monday through Friday very any time stop
a day depending on the call we have in
town the soaring Behavior
characteristics of school is looking for
are safety orderly achievement respect
individuality neighborly and growth and
out of those characteristics our school
resource officer looks at safety respect
and neighbor and if he identifies a
student at the school who exibiting
those characteristics he give them a
sewing ticket and then what it is we put
their name on a ticket and it goes into
a drawing and then it's broken down into
distinct age groups so the kindergarten
through second grade is one age group
third through fourth is one and fifth
through eth is the other all the names
get put into a drawing they draw one
name from each age group each quarter
and the winner gets a bicycle helmet
that we purchase from a local vendor SK
bites we purchased those helmets nearly
40% off retail price and we purchased
enough to get us through the entire
schol thank you any questions
forage trusty Schwarz go ahead trusty
Schwarz yeah I just want to say thank
you Chief Lamer for explaining these
last two items um mayor Smith and I when
we were reviewing dispersements we
thought we we would ask for some
additional clarifications and we just
really appreciate you explaining this
again in the matter of transparency so
thank
you and I just want to ask are you
planning to do um did you say are you
going to do soaring again in 25 yeah so
the soring program was actually through
the school they developed that we would
like to be a part of that whether the
bicyc continue we kind of evaluate that
at the end of this year this school year
which would be in May um the helmet seem
like a really good fit partly because
we're watching these kids rides bikes
every day um given recent events we've
had in town the helmet like a really
good idea and so far it's been welled so
we like that feedback but we'll evaluate
this program like we do all of them
sometimes spr
probably thank you any other anybody
else questions yes I would just say I
think that's a pretty nice premium uh to
give the kids
for a token of and make them you know a
little more safe while we're at it
giving them something to get used to
Mar I they seem to like them and the
folks over us here were extremely
helpful and helping us pick out
sizes others that seem to be popular so
thank you to them as
well thank you appreciate the updated
information well on that note um why
don't we go ahead and start on action
item number one which is a continuation
of the meeting regarding uh proposed
ordinance regulating short-term
rentals and we will definitely be taking
public comment there'll be a three
minute limit on everyone's comment and
we'll um of course everybody in the room
and then I'll be try to be um
super uh V Vigilant about seeing people
on Zoom because I know it's a really
nasty night out so there may be more
people on Zoom that I can certainly see
um so with that I'd like to turn it over
to administrator wi to just maybe pick
up where we left off two weeks ago and
some information comments you received
and information you found as you see
sure so um what's in front of you and
what was provided for the public is um
some written comments that we've
received um from both for and against
regulations for from wins um and then
also um some research that that I did
based on um some comments that we
received as well um or it was uh five
citations that were provided um to look
into and uh I I did some more a deep
dive into them um the one thing that did
go out after our last meeting was a
survey and I wanted to share the results
of that survey uh with
you can ohy
okay um it was a it was a
pretty um short survey um
in which we received 60 responses but
not everyone chose to answer each
question um first question was we want
to know your relationship to town um 35
people said they live within Town limits
um 13 said they live out of town limits
but have a ping
address um two had said that they own
property in town but do not live in
ponia uh own property in town and
currently rent as a long-term rental
there was one one property in town
currently rent a short-term rental there
were two plan to rent property that they
own in town as a short-term rental and
that was one own property in town and
live in town 15 plan to or currently
rent a bedroom in my primary residence
short of rental of
three um you can see the breakdown of
all of those responses there let me see
if I
can let zoom in a little
bit um another question was did
participate the um the 2023 housing
needs assessment action plan process um
19 responses said no a yes and 40 said
no so that was a very large Outreach
process that took uh about six seven
months that was Urban rule Continuum who
completed that
process number three uh what do you
think of the currently proposed cap of
40 on short-term rental licenses uh the
currently proposed cap is based on a
recently completed study of active and
booked short-term rentals operating
within town limit showing 38 short-term
rentals currently being active
consideration for the currently proposed
C Authority is due to regulations
requiring that individual bedrooms also
require separate
licensure so digging into this
information there were 14 that said just
right 31 that said too many nine that
said too few um breaking down into the
too many um there were quite a few that
said
um that they would like to see anywhere
from 25 to 30 um a lot of them had also
said 20 so let
just and that is coupled with question
four is what do you think an appropriate
cap on short teral licenses ought be
keep in mind that housing that the
housing needs assessment discuss caps of
20 to 30 but no definitive decision was
made during the public Outreach sessions
please see the image of the consults
report from the 59 2024 meeting that
showed in uh an image of that report I
mean some people
took this and you maybe gave factious
answers you know like
81428 that's our ZIP code um 10 was was
another answer um but we did get some
pretty good data that was um that was
available that I think I sent to you
guys as a breakdown but it was quite a
few
pages um there was some people that
discussed regulation during this during
this um during this question like
instead of a cap limit all strs to owner
occupied dwelling units in residential
zones n non-owner occupied dwelling
units used for the purpose of overnight
lodging should be considered hotels
require commercial zoning fees taxes
regulations here's one of them that said
twoo many and the response was
30 so here's another one that says I
think that whole home rentals ought to
be by the year and not more than 25 no
more than 25 of them everever home
rentals ought to be by the year so again
that's one that said too many said 25 no
limit which I would never I can't
recommend No Limit
that's just not reasonable 20 could be
adjusted upwards if ST owners can
demonstrate demand exceeds Supply 40 at
least 50 and then more policy discussion
20 uh consider the impacts of having no
additional housing resources before
capping SP
hours max of 25 total I can see 30 being
an okay medium in general a CA
regulation needs to take place so we're
going to strip on this issue 50
according is good 100 um U for kin not
public um there's a conflation of adus
and short-term rentals we're tackling
short-term rentals right now not
accessory drawing units that's going to
come at a later time uh
2020 statistically Pro that this new
proposed r ation will make the community
better somehow or somehow better zero 10
40 seems to be just right don't want the
count town to get sued I believe the cap
for MB rentals should be no more than 20
including adus single rooms and entire
homes um there are way more than 40 now
I'm guessing at least twice that
currently 15 to 20 I think that
regulation of what is allowed is much
more important than the cap number the
majority of the or proposed ordinance
does do regul does have
regulations um I don't believe there
should be a cap again I can't uh
recommend something that doesn't have a
cap that's not reasonable 30 an
unintended consequence of the above may
be higher rents property values in the
above
plan not sure of an exact number but
there should be not so many places
sitting empty when there are people who
are in need 20 Max um let people be free
20 um 40 to 20 20 with a re visit outs
every 3 years 20 to 30 there are plenty
outside of 10 limits too Str strr should
be treated like commercial properties
because that is exactly what they are
tax them as commercial properties charge
them commercial utility rates and that's
something that this proposed ordinance
didn't consider was changing um that to
commercial um other communities like bre
R which I'll go into detail later um
does have an occupational business
license and makes everyone regardless of
if it's primary residence single bedroom
or studio um also get an occupational
business license something we don't have
in
town funny strs of prioritization given
to local second home local second
homeowners if
possible I'll allow you to make that
decision I trust the people in charge
here will might be a little aous 25 full
rental units and City Limits up to 30th
including rooms that and host rentals 40
I think it should be a percentage of
housing versus a specific number I'll go
into a little more detail about Summit
County and Breen Ridge um where there
are percentages and we're pretty close
if not less than their
percentages St Scout of saying what
people can do with their property that
seemed to be a theme that I saw in other
responses as well 25 50 20 40 20 40 20
um and that was it for
those what specific regulations or
changes to proposed regulation would you
like to see on short-term r
um there were some pretty good um things
that came out of here but they were
already in the proposed ordinance um
this one was was saying that um C1 Zone
should have Str Str use by right part to
have licenses but the number of licenses
in C1 Zone should not be restricted um
that that's kind of that's kind of tough
to do I think there should still be a
cap on the number of available licenses
I would recommend that um especially
when you go further down and we have
spot Zoning for commercial C1 um amongst
residential I think that doing this
would uh make it difficult to kind of
enforce uh if a dwelling unit is Ed for
oranic lodging less than 30 days it
should be treated as a hotel um people
who live in their home and rent a home
room within the same building should not
be allowed to do so without regulation
and we're essentially regulating this to
say what you can and can't do
see they pay business tax in town and
have County license so the proposed
ordinance also has a provision should a
referendum be made that puts a local tax
on short-term rentals you know that
that's what it would take is it would
take a referendum vote um to implement a
new tax in town especially Insurance
rental um it's there in case we decide
to do it but that's that would take time
right I think it's more important to get
this regulated than under
control no pets I mean that sounds
like I don't know that's not something
we're going to
regulate that's up to the individual
homeowner you should broaden the types
of Str Str allowed throughout town a mix
of lodging op options support local
economy license should be required for
Str Str an entire house attached Adu and
and attached ad the license for a
bedroom in a house be required and cost
less and this is exactly what the
proposed ordinance does
right all Str strs need do up be up to
some standard codes listed in your draft
there's a provision for that as it
relates to like fire safety
erress short-term rentals are the number
one threat to ponia or communities like
ponan should be treated as such no
additional short-term Ral should be
permitted in pionia and support the
treatment of rentals of single rooms and
occupied homes differently with full
home or Adu rentals I support the
requirements of Str strs to be inspected
for
$500 uh a year Town fee to be applied to
all Str strs and for locals to be
prioritized for permit before non locals
and so the proposed ordinance actually
does prioritize local homeowners renting
out a single bedroom in their primary
residence that licensing fee is
less cap at 100 within City Limits I
wouldn't I wouldn't recommend that at
all um but
uh but require a percentage fee of Sr
Revenue to return to the town Breen
Ridge does that um this grows revenue
for the town in respect to the growth of
the SR industry and doesn't cap revenue
for Town
$500 a tax or fee similar to that placed
on to that placed on motels that would
be a referendum vote to do
tax a special licensed operator
short-term rental with fees or taxes
which benefit the town and that's what
this is we licensing
regulating um where I grew up short
teral are tax 40% to the county and the
fee to obtain a license is Hefty I was
surprised when I moved here to hear zero
regulations were in place zero benefits
to the local population I know many
short-term rental owners do not live in
town or even in state um I don't know
how that that statement I can't verify
that
statement I do know that I do have you
know there's there are properties on
Third Street that it is a second home
they don't live in town then we also
have on Second Street or Third Street
that's operating ating and it's their
primary residence running on a single
bedroom I know that from my own
experience um adequate parking upkeep of
rental property that's contemplated in
the proposed ordinance um I personally
would like to see stiffer fin violations
we did have to reduce it from a th000 to
300 that was a recommendation of the
Town attorney because of some criminal
code U where we you know if the fine is
over a certain amount we would have to
provide attorneys and um for the defense
and everything because of becomes a
criminal fine where's $300 per
occurrence per day is
not um
none would like a lower number than 40
for Str strr should have extra tap um we
have a water tap moratorium so I don't
know how that would work with trying to
get regulations in place
now let's see regulations to discourage
whole house sdrs in favor of single room
or ad rentals again we have an incentive
to lower fee
um need to be licensed tax at a higher
tax
rate over that one none I'd like to see
no short-term rentals in town
limits limit to hotels hosts with
business license we don't have a
business license love to get one in
place but that was a conversation a few
years ago that fell on its
Spas I'd like to see specific regulation
short-term medals that prioritize
fairness Community stability and
Equitable opportunities these include
owner occupied requirement short-term
rental should be operated all by
homeowners reside in the property are on
the same lot residency requirement
homeowners must live in Pon to ensure
they are active members of the community
and not anente landlords one rental per
person a single Homer should be allowed
to operate only one short-term rental
property to prevent monopolization and
encourage Fair distribution of
opportunities annual Lottery system to
introduce a lottery system to allocate
Str permits this isn't permits this is
licensing there's a big there's a
difference
between ensuring new people have a
chance to participate each year this a
license can be revoked for failure to
follow through ensuring new people have
a chance to participate each year this
promotes inclusivity and prevents of
Monopoly by a few individuals no
grandfathering avoid grandfathering
existing short-term metal operators
solely based on prior participation all
Africans should be subject to the same
regulations to ensure Equity low cap
give licenses with terms that expire
that it's not like one landlord to
monopolize all the licenses this
proposed ordinance has a cap and is requ
annual renewal U specific lodging taxes
the restrictions on in town residents
who choose to operate Str as a way to
supplement expenses to live here so
that's something completely different
than what we've seen on some of these
CS there's that it's not limited to
zoning restrictions like R1 but Case by
case
bases um I'd like to see some of these
people giving give back some people who
in fact one this community a reasonable
place to rent lodging taxes um again
I've explained that one live Live and
Let Live um they need to be licensed and
if the yes is the whole house R you they
need to pay commercial taxes such as
loding taxes it's something we' been
over already having insight into
short-term regulations I would
definitely include an inspection that
the rental need fire safety Health
standards and propos the bonus on the
owner to pay and provide the city with a
current inspection report that will help
keep the city held harmless in cases of
negligence or mal feasance also consider
look looking at other sections of your
codes that just fire can require
sprinkler systems or hydrants for each
room
rented uh I would also suggest including
a registration and renewal process or a
deadline dates to register the SR I
agree with the Consultants that fees
should be collected at amounts based on
the type of Str Str number one priority
is to have clear definitions to close
loopholes require business licenses and
registration with state of requir um a
lot of the proposed ordinance already
has some of this in here but there are
some things that really really
restrictive like f um sprinkler systems
that I think would be really really uh
hard for somebody to put into
place and then again require business
licenses you don't have that um license
fee of 5,000 to 10,000 um that's one way
to stop any licenses density limits stay
limits yearly use limits nuisance
ordinance license loss lodging tax local
manager commercial property tax rate I
think only 25ish Str Str should be
allowed in town because they take
housing to locals I think just running
out a room in your house shortterm is
better because it doesn't take away
housing person $110,000 annual licensing
mandatory owner or manager living within
15 miles Town taxed heavily see above
second homes used as
adrs maybe Str strs should be zoned as
commercial tax for such would like to
see free food vouchers
um I as well struggle with out estate
property owners my property just rent
out I believe I I have lived or plans to
live in area for an allowed amount of
time complete ADA compliance and
accommodation make each property Avail
available to abilities disciplinary
actions for un licensed still operating
and licensed out of uh out of any
count i' like to see no cap on secondary
exiler units and a percentage cap on
Standalone units tax them as motels
hotels are tax quit wasting money on
Consulting um if you are that in F then
you shouldn't be in your position um
ensuring adequate parking off Street for
additional traffic giving neighbors
neighboring properties an opportunity to
get notified and state their views on a
business such as this in their vicinity
making sure that neighbors are both
notified and have an opportunity to
State whether they support or
acquisition to a business in their
neighborhood higher tax or fees for
shortterm funds go to help establish
long-term housing permanent residents of
ponia I like proposed legislation can't
turn long long term rental and shortterm
Rental taxes should be assessed and
collected by the town business licenses
should be required none right now I
would like to see a cap of 20 on short
to rentals as well as additional tax or
fee on homes are not primary
residents the rest of the rest of the
responses are names and email addresses
that I don't want to
present think I we haven't had any
public comment so anything else you
wanted to discuss before um I ask the
trustees if they have some comments or
questions and then public com sure um I
I mean I did so um we did receive some
comments um I should go into the
citations um so we did receive some
comments that they were available for
the public that included um five web
links to different articles about U
different communities what they what
what l that have been presented to them
um I actually went in and found the
complaint for one of them that was
talked about Summit County that's where
Breen rides U and that case number um
went before the US District Court in
Colorado and I took this analysis um
directly from reading the complaint
evidence submitted to the court the
final determination of the court to
dismiss the complaint of which the
county prevailed um that they they were
able to dismiss the complaint that was
brought on by short for rental owners um
for regulating
um some counties a little bit different
right they're a county they're not a
statutory Town we're not a home rule or
Charter Community we have to follow
State statutes um
but an Sumit county has operated with
some form of vacation rental since like
the 80s mean it's been a very historic
thing um they didn't they didn't uh
start reg so um they didn't start
regulating that until 2018 but they
incrementally have
added restrictions since 2018 and they
started the conversation in 2017 when
their affordable housing Workforce
housing was dwindling and prices were
going through the roof um they began
hosting their Community forums to help
form a regulatory ordinance in 2018 the
first short-term regulation Summit
County was passed and the planning staff
operated under them until
2021 that regul regulatory ordinance
imposed occupancy limits required
Property Owners to buas plans for
parking and trash trash disposal at the
property during um during s strr stays
mandated identification of a responsible
agent for the property that we call a
local contact person um should Str Str
guest or the county require a readily uh
accessible point of contact um fire
right if there's a fire in the property
who do you get a hold of um so that like
black kills energy can show off gas F
it's you know gas service um so that
bmea can show off electric service
where's where's those panel I mean
that's important
stuff um mandated the uh let's see made
permits non-transferable so this is
permitting it wasn't licensing at this
point it permitting made them
non-transferable requiring a new owner
to apply for an strr permit upon the
transfer of title meaning you no longer
say that this is operating as an Str and
selling the property somebody wants to
buy that property and make it as an
Str so all of these restrictions that
were put in in 2017 are contemplated
with the proposed ordinance some
County's 2018 ordinance did did not
impose a cap on the number of available
permits and had no booking limits and
again this is only for unincorporated
areas of Summit County the only proposed
that ordinance has a cap on licenses and
doesn't impose booking on in 2020
Governor po authorized HB
201093 authorizing Boards of County
Commissioners to license and regulate
sdrs and so that's why all of a sudden
there was this jump to regulate
shortterm rentals and make it a
licensure program
Summit County directed planning staff to
develop a plan to transition for
permitting the licensing in May 2021
ordinance 20 was up for its first read
which regulated Str strs Required
licensing of St permitting June 21st the
ordinance was adopted September 30th uh
was the of 21 was the deadline for strr
owners to convert from a permit to a
license on September 14th a 90day
moratorium on new Str licenses was
approved and enacted on September 18th
but renewals and conversions were
unaffected while Finance staff developed
additional
regulations in September 2021 ordinance
20-b was enacted that created overlay
zones and updated the County zoning
ordinance so now they have overlay zones
we don't have overlay zones and you know
an overlay zone is kind of like a
special zoning um District over that
that goes over other districts and in
this case they created two um zoning
districts um when I they called it a
neighborhood overlay Zone and a
residential overlay
zone They proposed three licenses type
one strr is the property owners's
primary residence we have something
similar to that proposed ordinance type
two neighborhood overlay Zone could
apply for type two license but the board
of County Commissioners cap the total
nights per year which rented to 135
nights per year type three license these
licenses have no limits on the number of
nights and property could serve as an
Str but property have to first be first
uh be approved through the conditional
use permit we call it a special use
review too the proposed ordinance has
two types of licensure one for running
out single bedrooms within a primary
residence that must also go through a
special use review and receive a
favorable outcome to get a license this
favors local homeowners because the
licensing fee is far less than a regular
home home short-term rental pay owner
proposed ordinance also requires a
favorable uh finding in a special use
review for all liur in both R1 and one
zoning
districts the ordinance also imposed
occupancy limits to two guests per
bedroom plus two additional guests the
proposed ordinance also has this kind of
oy May of 2022 a second moratorium was
active this spent for nine months again
to give planning staff more time to
propose additional regulations on Str
strs in 2022 The Summit County voters
passed a 2% Str lodging cach on all Str
strs booking limitations within the
neighborhood overl so so they call that
NZ
limited the licenses a Nas of type one
and type two no type three were
allowed add a definitions for a
qualified occupant stipulated that they
must live in the home for type of
license stipulates that an out ofate
residents can't a resident can't be
considered a qualified occupant Pia's
proposed ordinance gives gives certain
privileges for owner occupied sprr such
as a lower license fee type two licenses
are cap again these are unincorporated
areas of County um lower Basin uh which
is 15% of properties Snake River Basin
5% of properties 10 Mile Basin 6% of
properties and upper blue Basin 18% of
properties the owners proposed license
Camp is 40 of the 755 properties
identifi the housing needs assessment
that was found on page 28 or about 5% of
of all properties
to each cap licenses in some counter is
lower than number of actual Str licenses
in each Basin the county plans to lose L
them through attrition but is allowing
those Property Owners to operate until
they either need to renew or sell the
property in 2023 the border of County
Commissioners updated spr regulations
limiting rentals with 35 bookings a year
for non-rest owns in neighborhood Zone
in the neighborhood zones for that
neighborhood overlay zones the final
decision of the court so this was a
lawsuit that was dismissed County
Commissioners W
um said this this court is aware of the
significant consequences of the
ordinance in this order for property
owners residents and visitors to Su
County and perhaps the similar
communities across Colorado plaintiffs
in this civil action undoubtedly
participate participated in the
political and legislative process to the
fullest extent allowable by attending
meetings objecting the proposed language
in the ordinance and ultimately
litigating the issue before this court
their grievances concerns the potential
Financial repercussions of the ordinance
are valid it is important to clearly
denote the role of this court which does
not include second guessing the
legislative process or creating policy
rather this Court must determine the
constitutionality and legality of the
ordinance nothing more and nothing less
as the US Supreme Court has previously
noted of the municipal Council deemed
any of the reasons which have been
suggested or any other substantial
reason a sufficient reason for adopting
the ordinance in question is not the
province of the courts to take issue
with the council we have nothing to do
with the question of the wisdom and good
policy of Municipal ordinances if
they're not satisfying to a majority of
citizens the recourse is to the ballot
not the courts defendant's motion
dismiss that's the bo County
Commissioners had been granted
65224 other things to knowe Summit
County is not a statutory
town uh Summit County's explanation in
restrictions to pay's proposed ordinance
um which this case court case supported
sum County took an approach to
regulation over five years it's actually
six started in 2018 and allowed for
significant public feedback similar to
what payon has done and is doing Summit
County restricted the number of licenses
per Basin but only for new licenses and
are allowing existing strs to operate
under a license of the cap plans to
reduce them through
attrition um I did give some explanation
for licensing caps um and and in a
response to a uh comments that we
received from a resident um and I went
over this in pretty good detail the last
time of how we got to 40 Caps or that 40
license caps um we did a we did a
demonstration with a short-term rental
regulatory like program software uh we
found 38 this was in June and July 38
active short-term rentals within ponia
Town limits and so we were able to drill
down to look at what is the outline of
payon town limits um there was one on
Price Road but Price Road isn't in town
limits so it can't be considered as
something that needs to be licensed um
there were 38
operating and that didn't take into
account
um single single single bedrooms in
shortterm that's why that 40 cap was
proposed um I did go over like um some
of the other communities that on the
Western Slope that have license caps um
carbon Dale has no C but they only allow
Str strs in one zone and they don't
issue any more licenses outside of that
historic commercial
Zone Durango has a cap of um based on
they have different caps based on
different zoning
uh let's see Ridgeway has 50 available
Str licenses but but does not consider
the rental of the single bedroom of a
primary owner occupied residen is
counting towards that maximum number of
cabs so anybody in R1 could rent out a
bedroom get a license but it doesn't
count towards
C in our case we would in Pia's proposed
ordinance they would have to go through
a special use forev in order to even get
be considered for license um as for
safety regulations nearly every
Community with short-term RS has
requirements that a working fire should
be on site working carbon monoxide
detector working smoke alarms property
address and contact and emergency
contact info posted on site information
folder with owner's info agent trash and
recycling info is available and there's
an exterior erass SCH at least 6 36 Ines
wide another item contemplated is a
preference for only allowing locals to
have Str strr licenses um and the memo
from Urban rule Continuum says there
remains desire to only allow local have
S licenses but it's unclear whether this
would be legal without creating a te
system where non-locals are also allowed
to have Li STS um which doesn't achieve
what was being heard during the
meetings to check with our legal counsel
Boulder established um Boulder
established rental license requirement
of the book since 96 and has regulated
short-term rental since 2015 Mak it
making it easier to restrict who can and
can R to
show let's
see there's already a preference so our
proposed ordinance you've heard was
already kind of there's already a
preference for local homeowners um for
short-term rentals get a reduced rate
um let's
see Breen Ridge so Breen Ridge has
short-term rental regulations and this
was um taken from actually researching
their ordinance and their short-term
regulations web page they've been Reg
short-term rentals in depth since 2021
the chart also the chart below also
shows that they've grandfathered in
existing short-term rentals and plan to
lose them by attrition Theon proposed
ordinance with a cap of 40 licenses also
grandfathers in existing strs but
regulates them and doesn't allow for new
Str strs to come to town title four
chapter six bre R code regulates
shortterm rentals um it's very similar
to the proposed ordinance or the
proposed code for ponia but their fees
are significant ly higher than than our
proposed fees theirs are $400 per
bedroom or studio and $765 per bedroom
or studio in an accommodation unit they
call an accommodation they call a
short-term rental house an accommodation
unit um this also doesn't they also have
to get a a business occupation license
or a business license so that's an
additional fee for anyone
to uh let's see
they so their their cap on on Str
numbers um they allow a 100% in their
Resort Zone um to be licensed as Str
strs 92% their Zone one to be Str strs
51% in zone two and then their largest
residential Zone zone three 10% um which
means that 52% of their properties can
be licensed as an Str the cap allows for
4,16
licenses U but they have an existing
4336 again they plan to lose them by
attrition
um the proposed cap in in this ordinance
is 40 it is
5.3% of our proposed or of of the
properties time and um to show to show
my citations this is the complaint and
evidence 108 pages um that went to the
US District Court in Denver um of which
some County want a a motion to dismiss
and then this is the
actual uh order giving a
motion are there questions for the
administrator from the
trustees anybody on
Zoom yeah I have just uh a a question
and then I'm so anxious to hear public
comment and that is can you tell us can
you just summarize what taxes are
currently being paid by short short-term
rentals is it just sales
tax no so they also have to pay a
lodging tax but it's it's County
specific and state specific there's no
local uh lodging tax levied on that
would take a referendum
vote got it so right now the only thing
um short-term rental folks pay our
County and state tax and no no sales tax
because it's not really a sale I believe
they have a sales tax as well I'm sure
you're going to hear from short-term
rental owners tonight who can tell you
how much taxes they are
paid okay
thanks M
Lucy not at this time thank you mayor
thank you um so with that having heard
the introduction uh this will be a time
to take public comment so uh if you
raise your hand I will call when you
come on up to the podium and I believe
we have a signin sheet but but publicly
just give us your name and whether you
live in town or out of town but if you
put your address on the signup for our
records so um I'm sure there's some
people that want to come up and speak so
give me a hand all right raise a hand
for everybody wants to come up
thank
you have
people I'll get them
next uh Andy
Ford homeowner
here it's primary residents um so yeah I
have two points I'd like to make one is
um it seems like if it's your primary
residence that you're trying to
short-term rent here uh um it's kind of
a different situation if you if you live
here 200 days a year or more um and
you're you're wanting to short-term rent
your place just when you're away on
vacation or something like that be less
than 165 days that you're not here or
less uh it seems to be a different
situation um and it wouldn't be
replacing um long-term rentals because
if you're living in the property it's um
it's not not on the market right so uh
it seems to be a different situation um
so I don't really understand um and
limiting um someone who's trying to rent
their their primary license when they're
when they're
weigh um the second point I I had was
the 36 in minimum uh door
opening um not really sure what we're
trying to regulate there unless um
that's an ADA
standard um but if a house is not ADA
Compliant for example it has steps that
lead up to the house and then the door
has this wide opening doesn't really
make sense so
for requiring all of the short-term
rentals to be completely ID compliant
that's one thing but just picking the
door opening to be 36 in wide seems
uh to be unnecessary
thank you anyone else Miss
Watson Suzanne
Watson hey this shortterm rental um
ordinance you will be changing the land
use
code um we have laws this tment you're
not following and that is in chapter 16
article
14 um There are rules about changing the
land use code um the town May from time
to time amend any regulation or with in
such District or any other provision of
this chapter they're talking chapter 16
um 16420 says amendments to this chapter
shall be considered by the Board of
Trustees only when the the following
requirements have been observed one um
request for Amendment may only be
presented by they're talking about legal
title owners but I'm going to shorten it
to by the Planning Commission or the
Board of Trustees and two each Amendment
shall be submitted to the Planning
Commission for its
recommendations such such action by the
Planning Commission shall be filed in
report to the Board of
Trustees and then finally
16430 Board of Trustees public hearing
prior to the final adoption of any
amendment to this chapter the Board of
Trustees shall hold a public hearing
thereon notice shall be given as
provided in 16-1 16-10 of this chapter
and that's um advertising it in the
paper of notice um at least 15 days in
advance of the hearing none of this has
happened and I am the chair of the
planning Comm commission and I will
swear to you that we have not submitted
a written report to the Board of
Trustees um that being said in um
chapter 16 of our code we have um
renting of rooms is a use that's
permitted by right it's already
permitted renting of rooms and for
and drills down on um single unit
dwellings and it talks about how many
people you can rent rooms too it talks
about parking
regulations your ordinance is
contradicting the regulations that we
already have for people wanting to rent
a room in their own house I don't see
where you come off thinking that you can
mandate the length of time people live
with other people in their own homes
there seems to be something that's a
little bit of an overreach there um I
can see if you'd like to make it maybe a
business use home occupations are per
as well but renting of rooms is a a use
that's permitted by right in our town
code and as far as your
survey I'm signed up with text myg and
and you didn't even let people know
through text myg that there was a survey
out so maybe it was a good
representation with the number of people
you got but it it really was only geared
at a CT unlimited audience time up thank
you okay but I do want to let you know
you're breaking time's up 's up thank
you I'm I see a hand up on
Zoom if that person would like to make a
comment I'm sorry sand Phillips was
first I Sandy Philips Sandra Phillips is
whose hand is
up yes please um give us your comment
Sandy is that right yes yeah can you
hear me yes um I'm Sandy Graves now um
I'm on Third Street um I just wanted to
come out open uh representing homeowners
and hosts um and I really understand the
need for regulation so thank you for
going through all the hard work to do
what you're doing um I really appreciate
it um my story is that I've been living
and working part-time in ponia for 20
years um six years ago I finally
purchased a home and I work in ponia one
week out of every given month by average
and when I'm not there for the remainder
of the month I've been renting my home
out through
Airbnb um I want to make the defin I
mean so as in ponia we're a small town
we don't have a big tourist pull you
know we're not like Summit County um I
don't think anybody's getting rich
renting their house out it's really a
five to six month rental period during
the summer there are very few people who
are looking to rent a short-term rental
in
ponia um during the winter
um let's see where are my notes
um so it's it's not a job and it's not
it's not something where people are
clamoring to go and make a bunch of
money by having a short-term rental that
they're renting out full-time in ponia
but it helps to be able to own a home if
you can do this and I think I would say
most people are in this situation
because it feasibly doesn't really make
sense because there's not that many
rental nights available in Pia um in
while we are renting out um our homes or
our room in a home for a certain period
of time um you know we're giving jobs to
local people for yard work cleaning you
know the plumbers we do all the things
we um
so we're doing that we're also working
really hard to
be um Airbnb hosts we have a lot of
responsibility to Airbnb and I think the
vob people do as well um to keep our
ratings up we have to keep the place
really nice um it really you know we
work hard to do this and we don't make a
lot of money I pay you know $1,000 in
property taxes a year and this year I'll
pay more than $2,000 500 in short-term
rental
taxes um so I'm paying you know just in
taxes over
$3,500 um this year um most of my guests
are people who are visiting friends and
family people who are you know coming
home for the holidays and you know so
happy to be in a home that feels like
where they grew up because it's next
door to where they grew up um I rent to
um people who are here to work um people
here for the solar Institute graes your
three minutes are up sorry thank you
okay thank you so much for your time
sure thank you and um I can't talk
there's another hand up but I would like
to ask if someone in the audience would
like to come up and speak
yes and then I'll do that hand up at
Zoom if I am still seeing a hand is that
right okay thank you sorry Hi um thank
than for that help to review um and for
having us here give us your
name my name is Delan Rudy and I live in
town thank you um I H feel incredibly
fortunate to be able to own a home in
Pia it feels like something that wasn't
like I think for many people my age
didn't feel like a possibility ever and
you know things kind of fall in line to
to create this kind of opportunity and I
want um this community to be able to
grow um in folks who live here and are
contributing to the community um I I
want to just give a couple different
examples um of similar towns towns of
the similar size that have had different
experiences so um the the town of Manus
in in some of the um prep material um
their their regulations were discussed
um it's a town of 1300 similar size to
obtain a short-term rental business
license make is um if it's in a
residential um Zone
area the owner has to live on site um
and if it's in a commercial area the
owner must live in the area code um and
and make his continues to be thriving
Community people who can afford to live
there um as a kind of contrast uh my
fiance who wasn't able to be here
tonight grew up in Gardner Montana um
and uh when he was growing up there the
population was about 1300 people so
again a similar size um there's no
zoning and no restrictions there um and
they've seen the population uh plummet
to only about 700 folks um uh and has
just completely gutted the community as
they know it um they're down about half
in school enrollment as well um prefork
another community in Montana learned
from Gardener um and they banned
unoccupied short-term rentals uh
allowing owner occupied um short-term
rentals and uh they have maintained a
steady um full full-time population
about 1900 people so again a similar
size and I would say three fors is a
very similar town to PA a little bit
less um a little bit less the tourist
influence than St Gardener um again also
um the speculative buying of homes for
short-term rental income um contributes
to skyrocketing home prices which pushes
families out of the community um and I
just would really love to see this
community be able to support um folks
who are living working and raising their
their children here
um uh yeah and I just think of those
those 40 currently permitted homes um
and it's 40 40 families that are not
able to to live here and contribute year
round to the community so thank you so
much for your time thank
you me Mr Megan Megan I see your hand is
up if you would like to have your
opportunity to speak please go ahead yes
hi thank you my name is Megan Lawson um
and I just really wanted to Echo
uh Sandra's sy's comments um I also have
a short-term rental over on Colorado AV
um and I agree with like thank you I I
do think that there should be limits on
them I think there should be licenses
and so I support everything all the work
that you all have been doing I do think
the 40 limit is good um because the the
town will not be involved with picking
favorites um I was really concerned with
initial very low numbers and I was
wondering what those criteria would be
to decide who gets one and who doesn't
um I do I would appreciate a
consideration of a percentage of the
housing stock um as um we heard that
it's at five 40 units represents 5% of
the housing stock but I'm concerned if
the town grows will that cap at 40 seem
um too low to support of that summertime
tourism economy um and then my my final
um and maybe bigger question that I have
uh because I am an R1 and would
require uh special use permit I'm just
curious as to what the process would be
um because as Sandy mentioned you know
we have our co-hosts we have our
cleaners we have the folks um who are
already planning on um you know their
work for the coming year we have
reservations and um it would be great to
have
[Music]
some uh minimizing
uncertainty um you know once we make
those uh submit our application
um can we continue to take
reservations um will we be in violation
if we take them because we have
reservations we would have to cancel um
if that's not the case if I can't um
know with some amount of certainty if we
follow all the rules um and go through
this if we'll be able to um I'm not sure
how long this all will take you know if
there's all of a sudden a slew of uh
folks who need to go through the special
use um review process kind of how much
time that will take um that's my bigger
uh bigger question I have uh have for
everybody thank
you thank you very much um all right
anyone in the audience who would like to
come forward
yes uh Pete McCarthy I live here in
town I just want to Center this
conversation a little bit because I hear
people are talking about their concerns
about the number of permits and things
like that imagine the concern and the
anxiety that the renters the long-term
renters in this town have had to live
under for the last 10 years while this
board has done nothing to protect them
and they're just talking about possibly
having it reduced to 40 or 20 or
something could you please speak this
way so we can be sure that you are heard
did you not hear me I can hear you fine
but we this is for recording purposes so
would you please face me and uh speak to
me is is that a requirement yes it
Robert
R thank you thank you for letting me
know I okay okay um so imagine the the
the anxiety that the long-term renters
have been going through for the last 10
years and now we're worried about
lawsuits that have all been dismissed
precedent with the town of makus being
able to do these things we we can do
better than what this is uh we had I sat
in many of these things I heard from
long-term renters we heard from
landlords and as the shortterm I thought
one of the most amazing things was all
the short-term rental landlords came up
and they said we could make just as much
if we if we did long-term rentals but we
chose to do shortterm because I don't
know it's neat it's nice we it's
fun we have those are 40 you said that's
just 5% of the community 5% of the
community it's not just 5% because we
know that there's short-term rentals all
around this whole valley so there's
probably a 100 in this whole valley
that's 100 communities that's 100
households that are no longer here that
my daughter T will have playdates with
that this is what we've done and now
we're balancing the conversation and
taking it all the way to for that is not
a balance we need to do we need to have
relief for the long-term renters in this
town we need to find balance for them
not for the people that have been
profiting at their expense thank you
thank
you I don't see any more hands on Zoom
is that correct correct okay anyone else
in the audience yes please come up
my name is David Mary in town I've lived
here for over 30 years um I think your
cap of 40 is probably
reasonable uh I think the proposed
ordinance is probably restrictive enough
that I would be surprised if you even
reach that cap one thing I want to point
out is uh section
6-54 parent H2 local contact person
requires this person the owner or the
local contact person to be available
24/7 be able to respond and and be able
to respond physically within 60 minutes
if you read that literally a local
contact person probably can't leave town
they can't even go to Grand Junction
because they probably can't get back in
60 minutes that seems to be a little bit
Overkill I don't know that there have
been problems I'm not aware of any in
this town with a short-term rental where
somebody needed to respond physically in
60 minutes so I would suggest that you
at least look at that section and make
that a little more reasonable thank you
I also agree with the comments by Sandy
and Megan about the benefits of the
short-term the Comm thank you anyone
else in the audience I'm sorry you only
have one opportunity anyone
else well with that um and no one on
Zoom than um so one thing I would like
to do is ask our attorney if you could
please please address the comment made
about chapter 16 article 14 that would
be very
helpful hey Bor you guys hear me all
right
yes um I mean I listen to a lot of
comments we're talking about the comment
regarding
the amendment procedure
correct so as I let me let me pull it
the
so we're talking about we're talking
about chapter 16 article 14 Amendment
procedures to the
zoning I I believe what the comment was
was something to the effect that any
amendment has to be
presented uh looking
at
16420 procedures
16420 uh sub paragraph 2 each Amendment
shall be submitted did to the Planning
Commission for its
recommendation I think we're kind of
mixing apples and oranges here the the
shortterm
rental regulation is
a legislative event um it doesn't
trigger any rezoning any anytime a Board
of Trustees passes a
law um that has some sort of effect on
the
the zoning chapter doesn't trigger a
review by the the Planning Commission
this this particular section is talking
about amendments and if you read the
first paragraph it's talking about
amendments that are presented by legal
title owners or real property within an
area proposed for a change and so the
zoning issues are mostly quasi judicial
if and when they are only affect one or
small group of property owners
when the Board of Trustees takes action
that
affects an entire group of people or the
entire jurisdiction the Supreme Court's
well settled and I'm talking about
Colorado Supreme Court has uh made it
clear and I need to find that case law
again but it's made it clear that broad
legislative decisions such as the
short-term rental ordinance that we're
looking at here is uh legis in nature
not quasi judicial so it doesn't trigger
those quasi judicial
resoning uh procedures for as an example
there's been multiple counties and
multiple towns that have
completely reshaped their land use
development code or land use code and by
reshape I mean changed redefined every
Zone within
Town
re um remapped every Zone within town
and and
accordingly like re written every law
term and condition and use that
affiliates with that zone but because of
the broad nature of the law and the way
that it was written it was not
considered a quasa Judicial function it
was considered legislative in nature so
I
think the uh chairperson for the
Planning Commission that spoke is
regarding this
is would be correct if this was an
amendment that is trying to change like
a particular piece of property within
the town or rezone a a block or a couple
properties that were affected but as in
so far that the short-term
rental
ordinance affects everybody within the
jurisdiction of the town
because
um it's as a legislative function it it
is affects the entire jurisdiction I
don't I don't see that this amendment or
that section has anything to do with
passing
this this particular ordinance there's
going to
be there's been previous ordinances and
there's going to be more ordinances to
come that have you know an ancillary
effect on
zoning but there's a big difference
between asking for rezoning for
particular property and the Board of
Trustees taking legislative action that
has an effect um or creates another use
or an infast or infrastructure or
Foundation um for regulation uh those
are you know very separate
topics so I don't I I guess
I I don't I hope that answers the
particulars of your
question
um so you need any clarification please
let me know no I think that's helpful
it's not helpful excuse me I'm sorry you
may not speak out of the audience um
we're going to continue with if the
trustees would like to start asking
questions of the
administrator discussion amongst
yourselves and um the trustees on Zoom
please don't let me forget
you so would anybody like to ask
questions or Rec comments yes I've got a
comment on the local um representative
local contact person um I suggest that
we change the
um language to instead of a person
designated by the owner or a owners or a
owner representative agent or
representative shall be available 24
hours a day which means that there is
somebody on call at all
times and that eliminates the problem of
somebody wants to go to Grand
Junction can I so I think you were
looking at the definition under
definition and solve that so under local
management required it it allows
somebody to go to Grand Junction um
under H2 where it says
um respond within within 60 Minutes in
person as necessary to emergencies it
will any municipal code violations in or
complaints regarding the condition
operation occupancy or conduct of the
occupants of the shortterm rental to
take remedial action resolve such
violations and or complaints that's
saying if if it's not rented they don't
they don't have to be here right so as
long as if somebody has rented it then
that person needs to be available to
respond within within an
hour page that you just reading um page1
thank you H
H1 P two P two correct replacing the
word the the
local solve that problem a local contact
person I see what you're saying oh so
changing it to
yes that'll solve all the problem and I
did uh trustees online did you hear that
uh
potential proposed change
under okay thank you thank you and I'm
thinking like you know if there was an
issue like do they have to respond in
person or is it just that they're
available by by the F by a phone call
and then they could call the plumber or
whomever like that just seem it seems
like a big deal to have someone be able
to be there within 60 minutes if we were
able to if they were able to to resolve
it with a phone
call
um yes the way the way I read that is
they have to respond within 60 Minutes
it doesn't say in person here in section
two they have
to oh in person as necessary that's true
[Music]
so if they have made contact with this
person because they were available
that's when they make arrangements to
resolve whatever the pler problem that
was and that's where the in person has
necessary yeah so I mean this is this is
in case there's a Rowdy party right so
um Ry party gets out of hand police are
called there there needs to be somebody
who's responsible for that that short
ter rental that can come come and take
care of
it
presume just a thought would it be
better to make it that in h local
management required short-term rentals
must at all times have a designated
local contact person in parentheses s
persons
whose contact information is on file so
it's not necessarily a single person who
is uh made responsible for that kind of
response that might help
and with that um have any issues with I
the local contact person must comply
with revisions of this code at 169 69-10
D3 I don't know what that says you have
to go backwards right you have to go
forwards forwards you know what page
69-10 D3 is
on paper copy comes in hand um that's 58
thank you
proximity okay you want to look at if
you would would you read that out loud
proximity of owner or owner's agent all
short for metal owners or owner's agent
must reside or conduct business within
15 miles of the short-term rental the
owner owner's agent name and contact
information shall be provided to the
town all short-term rentals must comply
with section
6548 of this code so it's circular um
there have been edits to code made in
the past where it referenced different
pieces but then didn't go back and make
a a a reference back to another section
of the code so something got changed and
then it didn't get changed throughout
the code and so that's why this is
written just good
[Music]
policy so I would just ask the trustees
with with this um section three in
mind um does it look as though there
would be any problem if earlier in the
code it was made plural and that person
had a little bit more um
flexibility like you were suggesting
trusty
Selter maybe that's a a good suggestion
for
flexibility just the cter I believe
that's a very good suggestion that it
should work
and administrate oh I see a hand is up
it'sust okay trusty Hunter please go
ahead and speak um a couple things thank
you mayor um could you repeat that last
item you were just discussing I didn't
catch that was that the reference to the
local management
required and then we were referencing
back to se forward section
16910 which was uh more prescriptive on
the local
agent is that the part you missed well
just just the latest where trustee
stelter just said he thought that would
be a good change I didn't catch exactly
what change we were recommending or
discussing could we have a summary by
administrator when if you're profitable
yes so there's um two changes to um the
ordinance that are being considered um
six uh it's first one is 6540 H1 and 2
change D to a so a local contact person
instead of the local contact person and
they change to um section 654 H um Lo
instead of saying local contact person
saying local contact persons with an s
in
parenthesis got it thank you for that
clarification and I had my hand up
earlier because I just wanted to say
thank you to staff um I know this is not
an easy issue to tackle and we've got a
lot of community
members um with with
varying views on this and I I think that
the ordinance is well thought out and it
takes into account um the needs and
concerns of of all the different
residents and viewpoints so thank
you um any other trustees have
suggestions or sections of the proposal
students that like to discuss in
detail and I see trusty
Schwarz sure um let's see I have a
couple things that I would like to
discuss uh there's there's two main ones
one is with the timing um
and obviously the January 1 that seems
very unreasonable um just given staff
time and the amount of time that's
necess Neary so I think we should have a
discussion about what would make sense
because again we do need to
like tourists are already making plans
to come to ponia they're already running
out their places Etc so I do want to
look at timing um so that's one issue
that I would like to discuss the second
issue that I would like to discuss is
the number I really I remember when we
were having um the public um meetings uh
with rural continu
about the number and whether or not we
should regulate people who are Renning
out their their rooms
Etc and I I think it is really good that
we have there be a license attached to
people renting out their rooms um and I
get that that's what's has increased the
number to
40 there is still part of me that thinks
should we start with a little bit lower
number perhaps 30 and then we can always
increase it
um versus if we start at 40 then it
would make us it's a little bit harder
to decrease it as needed so I tend to
take a little bit more conservative
approach and say let's start with 30
which would include people running out a
room in their home and then we can grow
it as necessary um it's just easier to
to grow than to decrease that number so
those are those are my two my two
points um would everybody be comfortable
talking about the first uh issue that
trusty schs brought up in terms of
timing since we know January 1 sure
isn't going to
work um there's some thoughts on that
yeah 90 days I think give it 90 days
before it's
implemented after adoption and or so
somewhere around around there if you
could explain the time frame from our
vote to what has to take place yeah so
um any anybody that's currently
operating should this pass anybody
that's you know the first there's that
30-day period before it the ordinance
becomes enacted right so if it passes
tonight the earliest it could be enacted
is December 26th day after Christmas um
and then there would have to be a time
frame for people to present oh Sam's
raising her hand so she's got something
to say about that you want go ahead just
clerk
veter I'm sorry I just since you guys
are talking about timing I just want to
make sure you have it right so it would
be 30 it would be enacted 30 days after
it's first published in the paper we do
have a weekly weekly paper and that that
can change your stuff up to a week so I
just wanted you guys to be aware of that
could you explain so if it were approved
tonight how soon would the first
publication be
published today is Tuesday if I had it
in by Friday it would publish next
Thursday
okay and then the clock the 30 days
start January 5th so it would have okay
thank you thank you for that
clarification um which then if you're
operating in a R1 or an E1 for special
use review and that you know that's that
has to go through the Planning
Commission has to be either
recommended U approval or denial and
then it goes to the Board of Trustees
for final approval um so that's a
minimum you know 30 30 to 45 days there
um I would assume that February would be
really really busy um and it would make
sense that uh that license be in place
or need to be in place by sometime in
March and that's if everything happened
today right if if we push this to
December 12th you know then it then it
goes a little bit further and if you
know so those are some considerations as
well
is um I just thought that no matter what
date we pick people are going to have
reservations at this point um we can't
fix that so let's just go ahead and set
a date and go and we'll start from there
it's going to it's going to bite
somebody somehow and better to do it now
first in the process then wait until
June or July when we're really in
trouble so the longer we delay the more
reservations are coming in and the more
problems we're going to have that's my
thought you're
here was that trusty heck yeah trusty
heck go ahead oh I oh yeah I was just
mumbling U I was
with and I think yeah just do it get it
over with we're kind of kicking the can
and we really don't have a direction
that we're headed but so the 40 seems
like the number that uh it doesn't
affect anybody on the short term so I'd
kind of go along with it I think I think
that's the way to do it and just get it
done thank you um I just wanted to ask
the administrator when so you'll need to
be creating the administrative side of
this
application um be ready staff-wise so
how do you feel staff-wise to be ready
when our uh calendar date goes into
effect yes so when when considering this
ordinance I looked at what other
communities had done and what they wish
they had done um a lot of the
application process was defined by the
finance director and other communities
and not codified we've this proposal
codifies that application process and
also provides a waiting list if there is
more and um you know if there are more
license have that come in it also
contemplates what happens if somebody is
in an R1 or E1 District they've
submitted an application now they have
to do a special use review they this
code contemplates that it will encumber
that license until they either receive a
favorable decision from you know for
that special use review or a denial you
know or an unfavorable um and then it
either makes that license active or that
that license goes back into the kitty so
it's it's contemplated
that on the on the front end rather than
trying to scramble administratively down
the road um you know when we when I was
uh putting this together doing the
research we also held department head
meetings where I learned about
enforcement activities what it would
take that's why some some of the things
were put in about enforcement um and so
you know that that's why that's there as
far as making an application um it it
should be relatively easy
um especially with our new modules with
Cassel um I see a hand I just want to
clarify public comment right yes
so yeah I'm sorry we're not taking any
public comment at this
point um
so follow up to administrator win there
from any
trustees I have a question but I don't
want to
so go ahead um so if whatever the date
is that gets implemented you know gets
embedded in the ordinance are you going
to be open to people contacting you and
saying I want to be on the list for an
application before that date begins
so what if this if this passes um they
will be G they would be given an
application to fill out after it's
finally adopted so after for that
publication date I don't want to
take threee applications it's
applications and so um that gives plenty
of notice there's plenty of time for
people that have that property to know
that they're going to have to get an
application in um and when they are
available after this notice period they
would take it at that time and then it
would be first
comfor it looks like trusty Hunter has
her hand out yes I'm ready to to make a
motion if there's no further discussion
but I don't want to jump the gun if
there's more you would like to discuss I
think there's more discussion and I also
see a hand above but I can't tell whose
hand it is it's public it was it's
somebody from public okay but I see I I
think you got a pretty visceral reaction
here in the room that I don't know that
a motion that we're ready for motion yet
is that okay I have some things that
need to be clarified yeah so let's hold
off on that trusty Hunter and if I might
ask I see trusty schwarz's hand is up
trusty Schwarz if you want to go ahead
and speak I you know I um I do not feel
ready for a motion yet but mayor Smith
you did you have a comment because I've
already spoken once so I want to make
sure we can go around the room no I I
was done with mine oh okay great um so I
do want us to have some discussion about
the numbers um again I'm like the timing
thank you for answering that I think
that's just an administrative thing and
I agree that we want to be we have to
pull the Band-Aid off at some point and
we need to be reasonable both for staff
and people who are existing short-term
rental folks um so I just ask that we be
reasonable and we give ourselves time to
to implement this um I do I do want to
have some discussion on the idea of
lowering it from 40 down to 30 and with
that 30 being um including people who
are renting out their rooms again it's
going to be so much easier for us to go
up but I'd rather us this is new for us
as a community to be regulating them and
I'd rather us start with 30 and then we
can build up we can come back to the
council if we need to increase
it and it would be more in line if we
look at the the survey that was done if
we look at um the recommendations from
our housing report um it would be more
in line with those those two
things thank you I was going to ask
administrator when if everybody could
hold the thought on the numbers for a
second it sounded like administrator wi
had a few other things that we need to
think about and then we can start that
discussion right um so what's in the
packets it's just a carryover from the
last meeting
and it didn't include the changes that
our town attorney had requested for
penalties and so um one of the one of
the big changes is 6580
penalties needs to be um
$300 not $1,000 because of that criminal
element to it um so 6580 would need to
be revised um that's on page 55 of the
packet yeah um would need to be revised
to in the amount of
$300 per day day get rid of with $150
just $300 per occurrence per
day is that the only place where there
that
amount I I believe it's also in h
section
six
6560 sorry section six of the ordinance
so towards the end of the
ordinance oh yes so section six is
um is what was uh requested by
CL oh is the pream um no no it would
have been on it would have been on page
58 let's
see uh trusty Hunter must be looking at
the the new the new ordinance the the
one that was revised
um uh yep yep
yep and then um so that's that's easy to
to revise to change those things to say
$3 $300 per recurrence per day um it
change at 6580 and within section six
and then um the next one is the the time
so
658a no I'm sorry 6530
C got a page number for us uh
49 I know that's the license number it's
um
658 change to
33025 which it says January 1st of
2025 I'm G have to do can you are you in
the packet or you in the I'm in the
packet is that section that's section
6530b
6530b what page in the packet Lu I'm
looking at the paper copy 48 thank you
okay which is starts
with yeah and so in order to operate
honor after January 1 it would be I
would propose onor after March 30th of
2025 all current B insur rentals must be
licensed and then
um actually so that should say April 1st
2025 all current pay insurance ter
rentals must be like license no later
than March 30th
225 and you feel confident in being able
to be ready for that uh and it would be
incumbent
upon um those those people seeking a
license to get an application as soon as
they
can so we can't the ordinance can't go
into effect until January 5th correct so
and you will be working on an
application between now and then I
already have one already so after the
5th people could start submitting an
application after January 5th after
January 5th okay I want people to
understand that that there is now a
window beginning January
5th through March
30th and to to be having a special
review requires a Planning Commission
and the
trustees and it has to be a public
hearing correct so there's at least 30
plus 15 days associated with that so
that could be 45 days
so people will not be licensed by March
30th if they have to go through the
special review that's that's my point is
that an issue they could be right so if
if they take that application January
5th they would also get a special use
review application and we want them to
send them in as soon as possible and it
would be incumbent on that applicant to
get both of them in um and that's only
for those short-term rental licenses
within R1 and E1 at this at this time if
they're in C1 C2 or R2 and R3 they
wouldn't require special use review as
it's
written and then i1 and I2 are not and
other resource districts are not allowed
and that brings up a point um for
somebody to have a single seat Beauty
single seat beauty shop in their home
they have to have a special review and
these impact the neighbors equally as
much if not more so I think that a
special review should be uh required for
any neighborhood business such as
short-term rental are you referring to
Beyond R1 yes R2 and R3 as well that
would change this
considerable I mean it would change the
text it would change text um but it
would be uh in just a few sections
so so that okay if I
can so if that's the case there are
going to be an awful lot of special
reviews going on simultaneously there
will be yes and are we really equipped
to do
that up upon your Planning
Commission I'm on the Planning
Commission
[Music]
and I I'm sorry but I don't think that's
practical to start out with to be asking
almost everyone who currently has
a an Str Str is going to be in one two
or three maybe a few c1s rooms no no yes
there's one instance of rooms in the C1
and there's a there is somebody who's
chomping at the bit to get one and see
one as right but do you really think
that's practical to get done by March
30th um I'm not against it I just think
we need to think about what our
capabilities
are because that's a lot of public
noticing each one has its own public
notice its own notification to everyone
within what 200 feet 500 yeah I
mean if that's the case I think you have
to let this go further out that we can't
I I honestly I can't see being able to
do this money
in three
months well the longer gets put off
though the more gets into the rental
season in spring summer when you want to
be on the play Comm sorry sorry just
it's there's a practical issue here if
you were to make it's almost you would
have 38 licenses coming in I I say 35
licenses coming in with specialty was a
good chance
if if it were R1 R2 right that's my
point if it's R1 R2
and my point is the neighbors do have
the opportunity there to support or
oppose no I think it's I understand what
it is I don't think it's practical at
this point to have 35 public hearings
they license is held until they get it
when they apply for the license it's
held until it's denied or approved so if
it goes beyond that we don't have to
worry too much about
it it's not a lot of that doesn't make
me feel a whole lot better in
terms administrative thing here um I
don't know if you have staff to do 35
public hearings in three
months um so anyway I'm just throwing
that out there from a practicality
standpoint we don't move as fast as you
do oh yes I wanted to add cost factors
because certification has to be sent out
to the neighbors and each one's $10 each
certified letter yes which is paid by
the
applicant no we shouldn't it should be
it's the applicant P it it's covered in
the fee um barely it barely covers the
fees so it is anticipated that the fee
will pay for those certified letters cor
because it can be a lot yeah that's a
good point too okay well I'm just you
you've got my thoughts on
this so continue the
discussion
spoke you guys are out
that we adopt the wait wait wait no wait
one
second there's still there's still a
request to talk about
the okay yeah so
take and do you feel like this motion
can be done in one piece administrator
wi for do you're you're keeping track of
all the changes so it could be as
amended so I Curr we have five um there
would have been six if if there was more
support for um special use review for
our2 and R3 I don't have that one in
there would with that being brought up
would the trustees like to weigh in on
that including the three on Zoom R1 R2
and
R3 may I take that as a no I madam sorry
this is trustey Hunter I I just see that
is is
really difficult to
implement
okay I agree with trustee Hunter and if
we were going to go that route then the
route that I would suggest is that we
remove that we eliminate our one two and
three from short-term rentals if we were
going to propose doing Special use
reviews however I um that's not the
route we're going and I and I am
supportive of keeping them and R1 two
and three um
and wait where am I
uh yeah I would not want to have all
those special special use reviews um and
if we were going to go that route I
would say let's just eliminate those um
from this from this
discussion so just for clarification
you're saying that a Str Str could only
be in C1 or
C2 if we were going to require special
use reviews in in all in all the um all
the residential areas as trustee stelter
was saying then I would say let's just
eliminate them completely um but that's
not I'm not in favor of this
and I apologize I'm on the East Coast
right now and my brain is a little bit
slow here at 10:15 p.m. yeah okay I'd
like to know what a special uh use
review
entails I mean you
notifi publish it notify your neighbors
and they have to comment on it and then
it it goes through the Planning
Commission get voted on whether you
approve it or not yeah so we applicant
has given a chance to um talk about
their application for that special use
review um there's a staff report that's
provided the applicants uh then there's
public comment the applicants given a
rebuttal time staff has given a rebuttal
time and then the Planning Commission
deliberates makes a recommendation to
either approve or or deny that special
use review or make no recommendation to
the Board of Trustees or trustees and
holds public hearing does their thing
so you guys are going to
see you know my thoughts so
yes Rick has a good point
about including all the um players The
Neighbors in this and
uh well do you have a good
point about dragging it out I think more
people are going to hate us if we drag
it out until
June um and we can hold the sounds like
we could hold the uh uh licenses until
the process is
done which gives a lot of incentive
to get it
done so I'm in favor of having our cake
and eating it too here um let's review
the R1 R23 and let's shoot for March and
if some of them
tail off I'm guessing it's not going to
be as involved as we think it
is
um it's hard to say that's part of the
problem is we just don't know and I
think we should air on the side of get
it
done so it's my understanding if they uh
get their application in then it sort of
uh holds their place in line until they
get the special use
review and that could go beyond the uh
date that it's required for them to have
their uh license if their review isn't
done and they just are still waiting as
the way the ordinance is written right
now they would have to have that license
activated by April 1 so if they have
bookings and they haven't completed the
process have an active license right
they're going to have to cancel some
reservations right I see that as a real
hard to the people coming in person
let's give them a month could add
another 30 days to this for the staff to
get their uh the special reviews
accomplished and then have instead of uh
April
Mo no matter what we do there are going
to be hardships oh yeah well right now
it's March right now it's March 30th
well right March April
1 they have to have that license
before before April 1 so they have to
have everything done by by March 30th
just Sil I've got a suggestion that we
limit public comment to the people that
are specifically notified within the 500
foot radius per occurrence for the
judicial quasi judicial hearing and that
way there'll be much less
um influence with I'd ask the attorney
if that's legal that that almost sounds
like what we'd have to do is also change
an ordinance or special use use review
public hearings and it would be and yeah
we would have to check with to see if
that is legal because it's a public it's
a public hearing
that's do we put the question to
play there would be a lot more work
changing an ordinance to just tell you
right because it seems to me you cannot
limit public comment at a public hearing
to people that live within that we can
limit the amount of time they have to
speak but I don't think we can limit I
don't see how we do that doesn't seem
reasonable so is the so right now sounds
like there's two four and three online
that are saying let's get it going and
then I don't know where truste do we
need a motion well we haven't talked
numbers
yet well I meant a motion for this
specific issue um I is it a good idea to
break this up into multiple
motions um I it doesn't I don't I don't
know the answer to
that because it's all about the content
of the ordinance word smithing a bit so
I guess if you wanted to make a motion
on whether or not you um require special
use for R2 and R3 that can be a motion
that would be presented you vote on it
we'd know where to go we can move on
from there Sam has her hand up
yes oh sorry um I was actually gonna say
much the same as um stepan just said
that since you've got varying opinions
it seems on different issues that seem
important maybe you should do them by
East mosing because then it's not
muddied up by something else with it
thank you so I would like to propose a
motion that we include R2 and R3 in the
special reviews process for
licenses we have a second second okay
more
discussion hearing none C can we do a
roll call vote sure um all in favor
I um can you
hey Sam can you do a roll call vote
please yes oh sorry switch in between
screens um trusty
stelter
I trusty check
five trusty Valentine or mayor protim
Valentine
all trusty Hunter
nay trusty Schwarz
nay trusty heck
I the motion passes
the next oh sorry goad trusty Schwarz go
ahead well I'm wondering if the next
section that we could perhaps do the
same way that we just did this is to
talk about either timing or
numbers okay you go ahead what's your
preference yeah I'd like to just dive
into the numbers so um my uh again you
all know where I stand I think we should
lower it to
30 including the single the single
room and I'd be happy to make a motion
on that too let me just check if there's
any more discussion on numbers amongst
the
trustees okay I say go ahead and do your
oh sorry trustey check no I would just
give my opinion but I can give that my
vote okay so go ahead and make a motion
trusty Schwarz I make motion that the
total cap of short-term rentals be 30
including single
bedrooms second that I'll second that
motion
oh all right do we need a roll call can
we go ahead all in
favor
I opposed
nay Madam mayor can can we do a roll
call please sure trust or clerk
better thank you I just want to make
sure everything's clear for
everybody okay trusty stelter
I trusty cheze
hi trusty Valentine
hi trusty Hunter hi
trusty Schwarz
I trusty heck
nay the motion
carries okay thank you so now we are on
to the topic of
timing and let me just if I well maybe I
should let administrator win um you
right now it is March
30th on under section 6-5 D30 license
required subsection B in order to
operate on or after March 30th 2025 all
current short-term rentals must be
licensed no later than it says December
31 2024 so I don't quite understand the
relationship
there this is a
dra it was dra we had already
discussed well
but I don't know what the March 30th is
is it referring
to after March
30th so the license would have to be
applied
for in enough time process right we
don't have a second date I don't
think said April 1st and March 30th yes
so do to operate on or after April 1st
2025 all current pay on insur to rentals
must be licensed no later March 30th
2025 stter did you have your hand up um
I suggest that we change March 30th to
April 1st and that's applied for not
licensed not completed and that they be
completely licensed by May
1 so you're saying in order to operate
honor after April 1st all current payon
your short-term rentals must be licensed
no later than what did you just say they
must be licensed no later than April 1
or have their applications in and the
deadline for us would be May 30 May
first I I'm looking at how it's worded
can you trust can I I'm really confused
in order to operate on our
after April April 1st 1 all current
paying short-term rentals must be
licensed no later
than licensed or applied
for because that way we've got until May
1 to get all the public hearings
done so May 1 so in order to operate on
or after May 1st 2025 all current
short-term rentals must be licensed or
application made no later then April
April 1st
2025 everybody on Zoom catch
that yes thank you mayor I have a does
that seem realistic for the members of
the Planning Commission like it seems
that our comprehensive plan is a
priority and that that takes for I think
you all meet like once a month it seems
like a lot to also throw in all of these
special use reviews and even though I
appreciate the extension I'm still a
little bit nervous that this is not
enough
time um to go through the special use
reviews Selter as the Town Council often
meets in a work session um we when we
have bus business we have to get done
specifically the budget that kind of
thing we often meet more than twice a
month and I assume that we can probably
ask the Planning Commission to meet more
than once a month
and but I'll just add the trustees are
gonna have to meet more than once a
month twice a month as well I can just
guarantee it so anyway go ahead trusty
Schwarz oh that that was the that was
the extent of my comment just are we
being reasonable with our
timing and my opinion is
no what's
that it's my it's my standing trip to
the
Indianapolis more discussion on those
proposed dates oh just really quick
M just a quick
question as I understood it we have like
uh 38 people out there that
qualify what's the criteria for
eliminating the uh
excess you want to answer that it's not
anymore I don't know um so it's first
come first serve at 30
okay I just curious how we're going to
do
it um at least eight times
um okay so can can I go through the
changes that you've requested so far um
we now have six but one of them is more
like changes to eight different pieces
um the first change is 6540 H1 and and
two change V to
a um the second one is 6548 local
contact persons as in
parentheses the third is 6580 penalties
to $300 per occurrence per day and
section six um of the ordinance the
fourth is
6530b change to 51
2025 and add must be licensed or
application
made application
made by uh 41
2025 number five is adding special use
review to R2 and R3 which changes
section
6530d section 6550 B1 section 6550
b1i section 6550 E2 section 4 table
16-1 section 1691
C and then number six 6530 C change to
Str
licenses um there shall be 30 total
combined short-term rental and
single-bedroom short-term rental
licenses initially
available I would like us to do could we
do another poll or another vote on the
timing because it doesn't see I'm not
clear if we all in agreement with that
or we have a majority
agreement did you have a motion on the
Sam did you was there a motion made on
the timing I don't think there was no
there there has not been a motion made
on that one yet can you take us back to
that which rule it is
6530 and you have a page number yeah 48
thank you
so what was discussed was in order to
operate on or
after May 1st all current rynolds must
be licensed no later than April 25th is
that right no so in order to operate on
or after May 1st 2025 all current ponia
short-term rentals must be licensed or
application made no later than April 1st
2025 well April 1
25th
2025 I I have a question about all
current um and it also goes I'm sorry I
know we're talking about timeline but is
this like if we go to page um what page
is it
47 the top of it says the regulations
set forth herein will not infringe on
current operations of existing
short-term rentals but limit the
creation of additional short-term
rentals and provide permanent
regulations for new licenses and the
annual renewal of licenses in my mind
that that paragraph needs to be
struck
and when it comes to the
timing it say and it said uh all and get
rid of current so it's in order to
operate on or after April 1 blah blah
blah all pay on your short-term rentals
must be licensed no later than whatever
date that would be um so I just want to
clarify are we only saying that the
licenses are available for those who are
existing short-term
rentals because that's what that
language is
implying okay so it sounds like there's
two more changes that are being
requested um the first is to strike and
I'm sorry which paragraph number
two so strike the entire paragraph
number two on
whereas
correct
strike because we're not grandfathering
in like existing short-term rentals
we're basically putting an open
application that anybody first come
first serve whether you're an existing
short-term rental or not can apply for
trusty stelter then that leads to page
48 under license required 65
6530 section B it says in order to
operate on or after January 1st all
current short-term rentals must be
licensed to qualify for a license it
says that you have to provide proof of
ownership and then go down to two
subsection I
Pro the short-term rental was
operational on or before J December 31st
2024 so that means that it's a free-for
all so it's saying
that or it's
or you're right so I'm not the intent
wasn't to only limit this to people that
already have a Str Str was it because
people wanting to create an Str
Str have the opportunity to apply as
well
right yeah or proof that the applicant's
primary resonance is the same property
of the same proper
and so do those three
subparagraphs make it clear that
somebody can start fresh with an Str Str
you never had one
before um you could change let's go back
okay because we're striking paragraph
two um which you're saying it's first
come for serve so you strike paragraph
two section
6530b you would be striking 6530 B you
would be striking current so it says so
that it would be all p short to rentals
be
licensed um and then two provide either
um to I that would have to changed to
say Pro proof that the applicant for a
short-term rental is is the owner of the
property may ask a clarifying question
are we all on the same page that we are
not allowing existing short-term rental
people to be grandfathered into
this I you've made that my opinion is
you've made that clear when you reduce
the number of available licenses to
30 was that
y May yes clerk has oh go ahead clerk
matter
sorry hi sorry I have a clarifying
question too what what was the date in
May that we had to be by because we
might have a strategic issue there May
1 yeah
okay so what I'm seeing here is if
we Sorry if people have their
applications in by April 1 unless we're
going to get both the Planning
Commission and the Board of Trustees to
set special meetings for this and I'm
assuming that even with 30 licenses that
there's probably going to need to be
more than one meeting maybe unless
there's a really cool fast tracky thing
um they wouldn't be able to in front of
the Planning Commission if they went by
a regular meeting until May
5th and then wouldn't be able to get to
the Board of Trustees after that until
at least the 27th of
May
understand Sam gonna have to and the
outcome would
be
confused the outcome of that would be
that uh unless they're in a C1 or C2
everybody needs a special
review and you're saying they wouldn't
even have know if they were in or out
until after May
5th is that what you said
yes so if this were to go in effect
January 5th applications are submitted
uh or or are given for both the license
and for a special use review they could
be on
the what the
March that March Planning Commission
meeting and then the next the next
meeting of the Board of Trustees could
hear whether or not those license th
those special use reviews were approved
or dened that would be on March 11th
March 11th and then still within April
you've still got your 30 30-day period
you're still
fine Sam I'm not understanding where you
would say 5th would
be I guess I was just misunderstanding
because if somebody applies for
something and they use the deadline of
April 1 they're not going to be able to
get in front of the Planning Commission
until at least the
5th but that's that it's incumbent upon
the advocate to get in as soon as it's
available so you're just saying that
they need to push they need to do it
before April 1st somehow that's why I
was confused because I was like well
we're not going to be able to meet that
deadline just with notification thing
things I see what you're saying now okay
so January will be a flurry of
activity for submitting
applications
corre that that's the yeah okay that's
the logical outcome if it gets approved
tonight and publish
ASAP
okay so C trusty
Schwarz go back to your original what
was your original comment
um just this idea of of grandfathering
in and Town Administrator when I know
you said that there's there was like 38
existing short-term rentals but I think
that number changes all the time so
regardless of that that number it's like
okay if we agree that 30 is that number
um and it's going to really be open to
anybody in the community whether or not
they've had it before so I just want to
make sure we're all on the same page
about that because it does change the
intent of what Town Administrator when
had brought forth so you're striking
paragraph two that's the seven I'm
proposing that we strike paragraph two
well I think you had enough support So
striking paragraph two uh in the whereas
is
um and then eight um the eight and it is
6530b straight current and then 6532 I
changed changed
from uh to 6 by3 I proof that the
short-term rental was operational on
before December 31st 20 31st 2024
changing it to um proof that the
short-term rental applicant is the
property
in correct okay and then what let's just
okay and then let's read the rest of
them so we're and then at the applicants
primary residence is the same property
or on the same property as a short-term
rental and provide proof that all
applicable payon your sales tax was
paid
um do we strike that one as well no
please don't so okay that at least gives
me a baseline to look especially if it's
if sales taxes submitted quarterly by
Airbnb or verbo or bringfido.com U that
allows me to look it up and make sure
that that that has been
done okay and then number two I I really
or I really like that one it's like
proof that the applicant's primary
residence is the same property or on the
same property as the short-term
rental um that's that's for that lower
licensing fee
oh got it for the single bedroom correct
okay and it also it also is an or it's
also a provision that allows for an
expansion if adus are considered in a in
a in an upcoming Co
change noted
yes right now they're not allowed
so where do we need a motion on the time
frame we do not have that and do you
need a motion for the last two the
changes that just I heard no opposition
to seven and eight so I don't think so
um it would be nice to have
clarification on Section
6530b
um
correct as it as it is as it has been
proposed it is
uh 6530b in order to operate onor onor
after May 1st 2025 all current pay
strike hurt all pionia short-term
rentals must be licensed no later than
must be licensed or application made no
later than April 1st
2025 so I'll read that again in order to
operate on or after May 1st
2025 all peonia short-term rentals must
be licensed for application made no
later than April 1st
2025 I'd like to make a motion if I
may that that section that was just read
by administrator wi that in order to
operate after May 1st
all applicants are all B all short-term
rentals shall be licensed or applied for
by April 1st
2025 a
second and then can we do a roll call
vote
Sam yes just look better would you
please do a roll
call yeah oh
sorry um I'm sorry who seconded
that uh truste check thank you
all
right trusty stelter
I trusty Che
hi mayor proam Valentine
hi trusty Schwarz
nay trusty Hunter
I trusty heck
May the motion
passes any further discussion on this
ordinance okay I do have a question on
um where we're this is section this is
page
40 uh
49 um and then it's uh section
6.5.4 40 conditions of short-term rental
life licenses it feels like an
overstretch to say how what a maximum
occupancy equal to two persons per
bedroom plus an additional two persons
per
property
um do we really need to be regulating
that is my
question so yes um the short answer is
yes um there's fire code um this is this
is pretty standard in other short-term
rental regulations across to
State
okay and then we had a question by um a
member of the audience if you and I too
have the same question and I know that
it's about the erass store being 36
inches wide um could someone please
explain
that so uh 2018 International Residence
code and international business code
already stipulate that uh egress stores
must be 36 inches wide um so if you're
going to commercialize your property
receive a license from the town in order
to protect us by issuing that license 36
in would be necessary it's uh it's
something that needs to be done I
understand that there's some concern
about ADA um with steps um think of it
this way if somebody were to get up in a
wheelchair up your steps through that
door um and a fire breaks out they'
still got to be able to get out that
door or if a fire department
is called they're going to have to wheel
somebody out the door it has to be 36 in
wide um so if you're going to get a
license from the town you're getting you
know that's the town saying you're okay
to have this short-term rental you want
to be able to regulate that say you got
to have a 36 inch exterior aress okay
thank you for
that I have no further
questions do we need a motion to adopt
the entire ordinance absolutely as
Provisions are made okay um is there any
more comment on the over U content
specific content that anyone would like
to
discuss with that would somebody like to
I do have a o apolog um ahead
I is it impossibility to ask that we'd
be able to see the final version before
we vote on it there's no way I'm going
to have that done tonight oh I'm not
expecting it I'm thinking for next the
next
meeting I have to say that would mess up
the timing we'd have to change the time
frame because it wouldn't be able to be
seen until December
12th or no
10th is our next meeting December yeah
yeah it would be the Thursday after that
before it's published right so it would
it would mess up the time frame by
pushing it back a month yeah well yeah
yeah would you like me to go over the
changes again the request of
revisions I don't need that no i' I've
heard them
all somebody like to make a
motion I move to approve ordinance 2024
D5 regulating short-term rentals with
the following revisions
um numerous revisions that we've already
gone through
twice who got their
first that was trusty check who
seconded all in favor I
I POS
oh did we hear from trusty
heck yes yes you vote you voted I I yeah
okay thank you I just didn't hear your
voice all right I was in the middle of a
sneeze all right so
um I
had when we changed the agenda I had
action item number two let's I think we
go ahead and do this fast item number
two is because we would like to have
we're going to lose trusty Schwarz at
9:30 because she's on Easter time C
could I ask for a motion
to um move action item number two until
after the executive
session I make a motion to move action
item number two till after the executive
session I'll second on
favor I all right so we are uh moving to
the executive
session
and I need a
motion to go into executive session if
someone will make a motion to that
effect based on the content of the
agenda we go into executive session for
conference with Town attorneys for the
purpose of receiving legal advice on
specific weight questions under CRS
section 24-
6-42 for B specific ongoing
litigation I'll second that all in favor
I thank you all right so
now we will um move into another room
yes and our clerk
is clerk is going to do a breakout room
we have the C attorney online um are
presenting Us in this case and they sort
how so they're going to join us in this
breakout do we need another laptop in
there I've got I'm picking mine you're
good okay and we've also got a camera
support so okay thank you can I ask when
that ordinance the way you just
passed
e
e e
so trustees I know trusty Hunter has to
drop off as long as trusty heck stays on
we'll have a forum I know trusty sworts
is east coast and it's really late so
I'm sure she's going to drop off shortly
too but as long as trusty heck you stay
on we're going to have a forum and can
finish the business
you the time is now 9:29 p.m. and the
executive session has been concluded the
participants in the executive session
were administrator win trusty stelter
truste check truste protim Valentine
truste Schwarz truste Hunter truste
heck uh clay
bner
Walsh
Francisco
Frisco cersa and Corey
heiner for the record if any person who
participated in the executive session
believes that any substantial discussion
of any matters not included in the
motion to go into executive s session
occurred during the executive session or
the improper action occurred during the
executive session in violation the open
M's laws I would ask that you state your
concerns for the
record any concerns from
anyone okay hearing
none the next agenda item
is extend the meeting sorry extend the
meeting oh gosh can I have a motion to
extend the meeting I I want to make a
motion to extend the meeting for 4
minutes I'll second
motion all in favor
all okay hearing no oppose that motion
carries uh did you ask for oppose oh I
didn't anyone
opposed okay we are
continuing with action item number
two which is uh continued from our last
me meeting resolution
20245 adopting a mission statement and
value statement for the town of ponia
which is on page 184 of the agenda
packet and administrator wi if you will
yes so we this this started in October
this is part of our SWAT analysis that
Workshop that we had um a um you've seen
this mission statement and these value
statements before this is a resolution
formally adopting those Mission and
value statements so they can go into a
strategic plan for the upcoming budget
due on December 10th um so um they are
this is the resolution that adopts it um
all of the fund whereases and then
um what what is the actual exhibit
exhibit a is mission statement um Pion
is a Vibrant Community that values our
rues small on history and Heritage
centered on education Recreation social
and economic diversity the government
then ensures a quality of life for all
residents by striving to provide exemp
service safe healthy and transparent
manner while protecting our precious
natural resources the value statements
are all there resiliency family and
Community conservation Recreation
natural resource and economic
development and here is the visual that
was presented to you
before any discussion amongst the
trustees I should back up I don't know
if there's anyone from the public still
attending by Zoom is there any comment
from the public
see none anything for the
trustees so would someone like to make a
motion I move to approve resolution 20
24-15 adopting the mission statement and
value statements for the town of Bonia
with the following edits attachment a
attachment B and attachment C
second all in favor I I
posst okay thank you thank you and do we
still we have trusty Schwarz and trusty
heck
correct correct okay trusty Hunter did
send a message I I knew she I was just
making sure we are still holding up okay
so let me ask a question and it has to
do with the agenda agenda item number
four consideration of adoption of
ordinance enacting electronic
communication and device security
policy I have read it it's quite lengthy
um for the sake of time let me ask clerk
better does this need to be adopted or
considered
tonight
um as much as I would like it to be I
think it would be fine to move it to the
10th
um I think it it definitely needs to to
I'd like to have it done by the the last
meeting in December at least so we can
go into the new year with it in place
thanks um we got some big changes coming
next year and this is really important
that we have so all right well we have
one two and I was going to ask action
item seven could be continued but I'll
ask that when we get to it so if want to
three four five items on the
agenda
um I don't know I'm sort of asking so
let's go ahead and and go forth with
action item number four which is
adopting that ordinance um you know yes
electronic we discussed this last
night um we've not discussed to the
detail that this is you know we we
talked about um requirements for using
email that was voted on and this just
gets into much more detail of uh all the
electronic policy for everything for
security and everything I mean it's a
very thorough important policy and Madam
yes I sorry if I could just toss in
there you know and I would just assume
you guys wait till the 10th if you
haven't had a chance to review it
because one of the reasons we're
adopting it is because we
specifically um are asking you to hold
all your boards committees and
commissions to the same
standards that town staff is for
electronic communications and device
so so with that um do we have a motion
to continue this to the next
meeting the proper motion to table it
until December 10th meeting I make a
motion that we table this uh electronic
device policy until the next meeting
second I'll second that all in favor I
hey thank you um we do need to make a
decision on the RFP for blush brush
clearing for the hydrological study
contractor selection and trusty
win so the proposal did go out it was
received November 20th um all we had
three respondents they're in front of
you in one of the printed paperwork I'm
sorry I didn't get to the packet I took
Friday off
um and U they only submitted them to me
so um but we have three proposals they
are um the first one is from um Diamond
S Fencing their proposal was for they're
out of Scott City Kansas their proposal
was for $41,800 we didn't submit any of
the additional required paperwork with
it um and they are the highest the next
one the next one is from um Gunsite
Holdings LLC doing business as parol
land Works um they're from the salt and
um they did provide all of the
documentation that is necessary um to be
considered as part of this um um to be
considered for for the work um they did
provide references and their total cost
was $122,800
um the last proposal is um from hemlock
Consulting they are the lowest proposal
but they also have the most experience
um they're also board IFI Master
arborist um and they're doing um they do
where are they from I want to say
they're from Leadville so they're
they're also native to Colorado and
their their proposal cost is not that
first one it's going to be the second
one which is
11,763 they also have done work on
Forest Service lands and BLM land um of
which our uh proposed brush clearing is
on um if I were to say who is the most
responsive and respons the lowest post
responsive and responsible bidder it
would be himl Consulting and so that
would be my recommendation to move
forward
them and that that wording is really
important lowest most responsive and
responsible
bidder why was the two uh
price um that was if they could get it
done this year or if they wait till next
year and so we're going with the higher
price because there's no way they're
going to get it done there's a lot of
discuss
resp any discussion on
this and I don't think we have any
public for
input if someone would like to make a
motion I make a motion that we approve
the bid
for hemlock Consulting as the lowest and
most
responsive
responsible
bitter we have a second second all in
favor hi hi thank you this also gets us
under contract with our water smart
Grant so it was the necessary last step
so thank you great thank you very much
and the next item is one I can describe
um so it turns out uh at our Planning
Commission meeting the one before this
last one it was uh um whenever it was
two times ago um K Rose a strander was
in the audience and there was much
discussion of how can we make sure that
the final draft that we want public
input on how can we get the best
information out to the public to get
them in attendance and to have them um
ask make comments Etc and Calla Rose
said that she offered to use the last
$394
in the Phoenix Rising contract to help
with that Outreach the Planning
Commission thought that was a great idea
there was a lot of discussion about
things she could do help
commission and so but uh so the Planning
Commission is asking the trustees to
approve the remaining budget in the
Phoenix
Rising contract to be used to help work
on the the meeting that will be held for
this actually going to be a workshop for
the public to come to and it has to be
yet to be determined it will not happen
in 2024 we're looking at possibly having
that Workshop sometime in January
because yes can I boil it down really
simple so the the the the request is to
have to allow the Planning Commission to
use the remaining balance for Phoenix
Rising resources to do to the public
Outreach for the final draft of the
conference of plan and and it will be a
draft going to it will not be the
hearing
that she's doing this is the workshop so
the public will have opportunity to come
in and have a back and forth
discussion any
comments and would someone like to make
a motion on page 255 I make a motion to
approve the remaining funds in the
Phoenix Rising resources contract to be
used to provide assistance to the
Planning Commission with public Outreach
regarding a yet to be scheduled Workshop
to be held in consideration of all
changes made to the draft comprehensive
plan since June 21st draft was
published I'll second all in favor I I
thank you br and so action item number
seven um we'd like to um continue that
table it and continue it to a meeting in
January simply BEC or was it February
11th oh until February 11th when there
is more time for discussion of this new
approach oh I'm sorry the Citizens Watch
group you're right January I'm sorry oh
January um the first meeting in January
yes and where Stephan can uh explain
what what this is if folks are okay with
tabling and continuing a motion to that
effect would be wonderful I motion to
table this resolution until J January
January the first meeting first meeting
in
January second second all in favor
I now uh action mik approv a resolution
oping out of certain elected and
appointment positions from workers comp
this is a something we have to do every
year s so requires it so it's um
resolution 16 2024 requires that um we
that we do a resolution opting out of um
paying for workers compensation
for uncompensated board members and um
trust me yeah I
you I don't see the tree board on this
should they also be included in section
one uh we listed Board of Trustees Andor
B Planning Commission and the Zoning
Board of adjustments and appeals yes is
a tree board there also a codified
board 256 yes and so if you do approve
this resolution you would would say as
amended to include the tree
board any discussion may make a motion I
make a motion that we approve resolution
number
16-22 has
amended I
second by me I didn't all in favor hi hi
any
oppose okay all right last action item
number nine discussion on the capital
Improvement phase one project needs
assessment it begins on page
258 turn it over to you administrator wi
um we're almost done um so this is
capital Improvement phase one for the
water uh water Improvement plan we do
have a public meeting scheduled for
December 11th um that's when our
Engineers will be here we're planning to
invite the water companies as well
because this is specifically to talk
about not just those improvements like
the 2 million gallon water tanker lining
but most importantly the Western Loop
water main replacement project um
something that we're also you recently
approved an EF Grant to go out for a
million bucks for um it's going to be a
$7.2 million project that one alone um
it realigns the so it replaces and
realigns the existing pipe um out of the
majority of it being in private right of
ways into public right of ways um
following following the road system but
this is we we need um your approval to
have this meeting which is the last step
in applying for funding come January um
for that low interest drinking water
revolving
F oh Mike is coming back in sorry trusty
heck is
coming oh yes I just have one question
on page
278 um um on line number 32 it has
easement negotiations and of that it's
2399362316
[Music]
they I I will try my absolute level best
to get them to wave the fees but I doubt
I'll get I'll get that accomplish and so
I'll still have to do some application
fees um for that
so any other questions from the trustees
I just have a question about the total
project cost I know there's a 20%
contingency build in there given that
this quote was done a year ago do we
still think that this total project cost
is is accurate uh no so I don't know how
this part got in here I didn't I didn't
add it to the agenda packet um it's this
this specific one for um the 8 in steel
distribution line replacement is $7.2
million 7,200
th000 but that's this isn't the public
hearing the public this is the
discussion to have that public hearing
on December
11th and do you expect to have different
content yeah I don't know I I don't know
how this made it in so would all the
attachments be attached oh absolutely in
that actual agenda packet that for the
meeting okay because they're not in
y any other
discussion somebody like to make a
motion
to essentially approve the meeting yeah
yeah approve having a meeting on
December
11th I make a motion that we we approve
the meeting for December 11th for the uh
final meeting with
respect it it'll be for
um oh yeah phase one project meetings
assessment
I'll second
[Music]
that all in favor
hi
oppose I didn't hear Mike hi okay thank
you comp was off for mat so I
missed
was I just want to make sure we got
everybody in and um on that note that is
I have no report I don't know any trusty
report
so I we have completed our agenda and I
would like to adjourn this
meeting thank you all have a Happy
Thanksgiving guys than for everybody
hanging in there on the East
Coast good evening guys by good night
night