e
e e
now and it is now unmuted
so I got some kind of a text today about
emails that Pete sent some emails and I
don't have anything from him um to board
members about comments does
anybody did people get emails from Pete
that's why I was wondering um are we are
we going to start meeting um I'm just
asking before we start the
meeting just the one that step
said's comments so there's a so is that
I'm wondering if that's going to replace
him at the meeting tonight for piece
planning on coming oh we do have an
email from Pete so it says due to work
travel and weather related flight delays
are in I'll be unable to attend
tonight's meeting I respectfully request
the town staff print and include these
comments in tonight's packet for
discussion submit the following comments
for consideration
okay is there a way to get those
comments to I'm I'm not rushing you I'm
just yeah that's what I'm doing right
okay thank
it's
than
so I'm kind of waiting for
Pete that's you know his comments are
him and he obviously guess he's not on
it didn't sound like he could join
electronically either did he say
something about flight
the yeah but
I it's not an optimal way of attending
the meeting so
well sounds like Stephan's going to have
that test in a minute now assuming he
print yeah okay so I'll call the meeting
to
order um
so first let's have a roll
call Stan oh okay so he's standing in
that's fine we'll
wait I can take
roll it took me a minute to find unmute
sorry
chair
Watson
pres Vice chair
how commissioner Smith here commissioner
McCarthy commissioner Hunter here you
have a
quorum um next on the agenda is approval
of
agenda to approve the agenda
okay a
second okay so I'm just um gonna say I
don't want to stay here after 8:00 and
there's a lot on this agenda and I
wouldn't have put the items that I put
on the agenda had I known it was going
to be this long um so
um what I'd like to propose is
um um are there especially I I'm not
going to take very long on the first few
agenda items because some of that was
put there um what I thought um to
address some of Pete's concerns um
indeed I think we all probably have them
but it would be nice to be here
inclusive to talk about some of this um
but the master plan
items um there's just so much there this
is a lot to address in one night so um
I'm wondering if you guys want to pick
three of these or ones that you see as
the most pressing that you'd like to
start talking about I think they're
mostly the new elements that we've been
adding is um I think um what we really
need to startop start talking about to
begin with but um do any of you have a
preference Ln Lucy on
page I I would love to see us get
through A and B because they were on the
previous agenda and we didn't get to
them okay and those are proposing
additions to the plan so yeah and it was
new that would be great to get to those
I'm not sure
infrastructure I'm not quite sure what
is that constitutes okay um and the
housing
element we have Pete's comments on but
with him not being here he had
identified
yeah I would really like to see him here
for that too I
mean to try to include him in that so um
let's start off with if that's okay I'll
make a motion um or I don't know as a
chair I don't think they can dump things
off the agenda but if we could start
with those two and then see as time
permits if we want to add a little bit
um to to the end there do you mean
agenda item one and two maintain them or
would you like well I'm talking about
now the compan of plan oh
sorry yeah and um
yeah the setting agenda it was mostly it
would be nice if Pete were here it would
I would just like to kind of um that's
something that we talked about at the
last meeting and um I'm just clarifying
those things um civility I just want to
remind people that especially the Board
of Trustees you have a code of conduct
and um personal attacks are not
permitted um I know we hold that code of
conduct in high esteem recently ly so
I'd like us to all be cognizant of that
um you know no personal
attacks
[Music]
um agenda item two so I'm moving right
along and I skipped the minutes so let's
go and talk did we talk about the
minutes yet we haven't had a motion to
approve the minutes yet so I was just
talking about approving the agenda so
what we decided on was um on agenda item
four getting through what we can get
through starting with the healthy
environment and Zoning right is that
what you said that's what I would like
to see those are the newest types the
newest elements and they haven't had any
type of group discussion okay so um um
I'll make a motion to approve the agenda
as amended there with us um taking off
um agenda item one until the next
meeting when Pete can be here and um
agenda item four Sen how far we can get
into it starting with health and natural
environment and
Zoning um so do I have a second I'll
second all those in favor I I okay um
approval of
minutes do I have a motion make a motion
to approve the minutes second all those
in favor any
discussion changes no all those in favor
I okay actions and presentations I kind
of synopsized this um so we're going to
defer some of this till the next meeting
um procedures clarification setting the
agenda and I I preached a little bit
about civility so moving on to agenda
item two um procedure for Content
inclusion in
plan
um so that's not very fleshed out or
described but
um so we're we're creating these new
sections here and we obviously want to
we're talking about you know what we
agree on with them right but what's the
procedure for including them in the plan
and um some of that's kind of new um the
contractor this wasn't available in the
contractor was doing their presentations
and I'm also wondering about how we get
it to the public
um so that's kind of two topics there um
how are we how are we going to let the
public know that we're making these
changes and I kind of thought um or
additions let's say I thought it would
be interesting and I don't know if this
is possible at all but almost like a
Serial novel every week in The Shopper
for a while you know with maybe a new
section some of the brand new just to
get I you don't want to send it to Delta
and hodus but I don't know if there's
any way that just locally in in town it
can be distributed somehow like um you
know once we've decided to include in a
plan I don't know I don't know how that
process is going to work either about
that just inclusion I'm kind of jumping
ahead um Paige I would what I'd like to
suggest is that we uh go through the
pieces that you two have created and and
do a motion whether or not to include
them in and where and through that
motion have a new document that's
created um and again it could be a
strike and underline and clean
and and maybe have one more meeting to
go through the housing element with
Pete's things there I I just don't know
if the public is going to look at these
things in pieces I'm thinking the public
might appreciate having an entire
document with a cover sheet that
explains what was added so they can know
if they have been paying attention they
know which sections to go look at but I
just don't know if the public is going
to pay attention to the incremental
pieces over
time yeah um can I ask a question of
commissioner um Smith when you say new
document you just mean a new iteration
right yes and um I should let you know
that both contractors Urban Ro Continuum
and Phoenix Rising resources have been
contacted um to push out whatever draft
we call the final iteration to their
mailing list serves so all of the people
that we've engaged throughout the both
processes will have some of them may end
up with
duplicate emails um but sending that out
to everyone U for their
so that's already in the works it's been
available on our website and uh we've
had it on the agenda now a few times so
my concern though is and I'm looking at
for instance this comprehensive plan
extension approved um dated Tuesday 9917
2024 and that last sentence says grantee
will make all efforts in community
outreach to include underrepresented and
disproportionately impacted community
members
and to me the underrepresented and
disproportionately impacted community
members are all the people who don't
participate and haven't been getting
emails and haven't been on the list Serv
and haven't come to the um listening
sessions and there are people who
haven't and this plan is for them too
and I want people to be aware of what
we're doing um you know I had talked to
Tom Wills um last week and and he's he's
quite knowledgeable with Master plans
because he wrote hod kisses and he was
saying that it's probably too late for
us but you know a door knocking campaign
would have been good something to get to
the people that don't have access to the
internet um for whatever reason um how
are we going to do that I don't think
just sending it out by email is going to
cut it or making it available online
because we're not reaching under
represented and disproportionally
impacted community
members um okay let me just ask anybody
else no okay Pig well I think your idea
of putting something in the High Country
Shopper but but my point would be wait
till we have the draft that we want
people to look at but put an article in
the High Country Shopper telling people
where they can look at it electronically
or to call Town Hall if they want a
paper copy yeah would be one way a lot
of different people look in that put
binders in the library of print
copies I don't know if that's you know
again I'm don't know what staff okay
stepan so um you know this hasn't just
been a digital campaign um we've also
implemented new Outreach Technologies
like text by go for anybody that's
signed up for that we've also put this
on water bills for multiple months and
so those residents that could be
affected even those residents that are
outside of town limits that get a direct
bill from us would have gotten a notice
with the bill so so we have done all of
the Outreach that that we can do at this
point I I that's up to you guys to just
yeah I don't think the water bills
really it's it's like half of a sentence
you can put on there so and I haven't
actually noticed them myself but it's
not like we have newsletter that comes
with the water bill it's just a tiny
statement um but page where you wanted
to okay so anyway that's still you know
the process here since I mean there's a
lot of new stuff I think that um between
the housing the zoning
the Natural
Factors yes I ask a question so to to
Really nail this down what
disproportionately affective residents
would you like us to to make an Outreach
campaign for if if you remember the
housing needs assessment we have a
disproportion amount of our residents
that are elderly seniors is that a is
that a targeted population that you'd
like us to go for that could be one I
mean I know my neighbor has a wall phone
you know he doesn't have internet
connection he reads he doesn't go to the
he's very distressful at the internet
and so he's not going to be seeing this
stuff is he active with the senior
center no so how would you like us to do
an Outreach campaign I mean we can get
things over to the senior center have
have paper copies ready for an iteration
that you're ready to present to the
public the senior center I think is a
little bit of a club in this town right
now I'm not sure I know a lot of seniors
have gone to hodus is what I've heard so
um would you be would would you like us
to engage all of the senior centers
Delta count yeah but I'm I'm so so um I
think the Shopper is a good idea The
Shopper is something that is free it
reaches everybody that I mean not
everybody's mailed them but some people
quite a few few people get the
subscription it's something you can pick
up for free um so it's just a thought I
don't know the logistics of that and
certainly you know one would have to
talk to Tina Walker to see if that was
even possible um but you know who are
the underrepresented and
disportionately disproportionately
impacted community members I mean I have
an opinion about that but I don't know
um you know it's just something that was
on on this document yes please because
we want to get this accomplished what
are you calling under represented well
what are calling Under representative
you're the one I just brought up seniors
from the housing needs assessment so
what is it that you consider under
represented people who aren't tied into
technology so I don't know if that's a
maale effort I mean um you know we have
everybody's address that we send water
bills to but um you know is it a door
knocking
thing I don't know we do have a our
consultant we did send out um mailers um
in the public process so people did
receive something in their mail I think
I yeah thank you I I want to say what
I'm saying is we have changed a lot you
know there's some very new sections here
I I know people you know had a lot of
opportunity to see what you have been
doing
but this kind of new section is what I I
might just suggest that you do another
public hearing on the new sections where
people can come in the same way they did
for the other sections and and comment
on it it was effective and reaching
people who may not be so much on social
media but could come in person
and thank
you yes um who are
okay Stephan I'm not make I'm not going
to like say that right here tonight
because I'm just like putting it out
there I don't have an answer right now
um but I just wanted like we need to
contemplate
this yes you recognize me as for the
floor um so um the process that was just
presented for publication in a newspaper
for a public hearing um what we could do
is instead of just using the Delta
County independent we could use the High
Country shopper
um we could ask the merchant Herold to
also publish these you know an upcoming
date to present that public you know
public hearing for the next iteration of
the draft then
everyone then that way we've we've we've
gone to multiple media sources for
people that may not have access to the
internet okay so we have a member from
the
public my name is Roger barill and I I
just heard about this because I got a
email from Shay that there's this uh new
draft coming together about uh housing
and planning and uh it's been a big
interest of mine for a long time and I
don't remember receiving anything in the
mail or anything about
uh what the draft is or uh don't you
just mail out can't you just mail out uh
the draft everybody that's just in town
or something
[Music]
orwhere it's kind of thick and that's
why I was thinking maybe some of the
newest elements or something there's a
way of um presenting it I I wasn't sure
if it was possible
to the whole thing but um but I do I
mean to say that people have to find it
once you let them know and you know not
everybody's going to come to a public
hearings we've got Co season coming up
up again you know they're people who shy
away from these public forums as well
and I just um you know they could be
writing letters but they have to know
what's going on so um it's it's a
question and I appreciate your comment I
just and I just knowing about it I
didn't even know anything and this was
going on right now
so I guess I'm just not reading the
newspaper I never look on the town
website or
I don't get emails from town or anything
so I guess it would be just up to me to
find that stuff is going on I found out
because I I got an email from Shay that
because I was on on the interest L on
this subject okay thank you Roger
ly one thing you
could do is as stepan recommended put it
in you know the paper whatever whichever
ones and then say that there would be
copies at the senior center here in Pon
library and at the town hall and then
people can go and look at those and then
there'll be a public hearing and they
can come
and and um maybe their copies I don't
know I don't think they'd be flying out
the door but you could make enough
copies that people can take them or
bring them back if they want to be our
own lending library I know there's a
cost the paper but I don't think you'd
even be giving out a 100 but it would be
putting it out there for people who
don't have that access perhaps you know
you can make a few that people can take
them to read hi May I just want to say I
appreciate your concern for people who
are hard to reach one of the things that
we did prior when um we were the other
elements is we didn't we did the
newspaper we did we also posted flyers
and we did on online but we also did
word of mouth it's a very small town
people talk to each other and so one
thing I would encourage everyone to do
is when you have the draft you want
people to look at to let people know and
to host a hearing on the new elements so
that people can come and comment on
those in the same way they were to in
the past and I think that's in line with
the public process also I don't want to
speak out of turn if administrator wi
has other plans or the mayor has other
plans for our remaining 5 hours but
we're happy to help you advertise a
hearing on the new section so that
people can you know have a similar
process as they did for the other
sections and if we need to host
something um we're happy to do that as
well so we're just here to help and have
that go through the same process um that
the other pieces went through and also
to recognize that we can't make everyone
participate what we can do is just try
to let everybody know that there's an
opportunity to
participate thank you sounds like a
really good idea for the remaining
hours
okay
um let's move on to the next um topic if
I may sorry yes I'm sorry would uh if
you were to make that decision to ask us
to do that when when when might we
expect to know if you wanted us to
support that or
not well
um do you think this would be a good way
to use the remaining five is that
something the Planning Commission can
just decide I mean you can advise Bo
trustees the next me is the
12 okay would you like motion I'll make
motion that we advise the Board of
Trustees to work with the Consultants on
the master plan
to uh create a mechanism for
outreach for new public hearing and also
where people can find the information of
the existing and
[Music]
updated yeah that's a tough one um I'll
second if you want to continue
discussion yeah
let's okay so um can we say I don't know
if we want to amend the main motion to
say I'm to think what the main motion
was um um that would address the
planning commission's concerns you know
so we've just enumerated a few different
ways and um of of we the way we might do
it and I think we had some really good
points from the contractors so
so hopefully our concerns will provide
the guidance to how it's done is what
I'm saying you know because we're having
the discussion here I don't know what
the Board of Trustees would decide um so
we're just asking the Board of Trustees
effectively to use the commissioner to
help
address our concerns about remaining
contract yeah and you guys can direct it
as the planing commission as to how we
use that contract they just need to
approve that do you think our motion um
was sufficiently clear ask a clarifying
question yes would this and also
administrator when stand up would this
include and perhaps this is part of it
as a specific hearing on the new
elements or is this about the whole
thing because it seems like there's one
element in particular the housing piece
that hasn't gone through the same public
process and then there are other things
that we're changed and the plan that
people may also want to see but I just
want to clarify that yeah um Stephan is
your question relevant to or relevant to
what she saw it's relevant to the motion
was just made okay so
um advising the Board of Trustees that
you would like to use the remaining
hours for the consult Phoenix Rising
resources to help with public Outreach
for the final iteration of the
comprehensive Cent
is exactly what has been talked about
tonight
okay so
um the question the next question the
clarification we were wanting to maybe
address was is it the entire plan or
just the new the new sections is what
you were asking if I if I may just
suggesting think if I heard some really
good ideas that we could help you
execute I like that copies in the
different places for people to look at
and um you know maybe ways for them to
like the free libraries yeah I no that's
a great idea like I you know I'm happy
to help with those ideas and if that
makes it feel more accessible to folks
who are wandering around who may be not
on social media or don't have email
that's fine the paper Publications the
bulletin boards those are all standard
um I think what I might suggest is that
we need to clarify to the public that
you have gone through it and updated it
to your liking so there are changes
throughout the plan and there is this
new section and that I think if you were
to host something to get public feedback
in in a way that we did with prior
sections um that we host that thing just
on the new piece um and that everything
else we advertise is please look at this
but those are more like written comments
so we don't have to go through the whole
thing and there can be a very focused
conversation about whatever the you know
I still haven't seen the whole new
section but I did Stan did write to us a
little bit about some of the additions I
see what you're saying I I to me it
makes sense okay what how do the other
Commissioners feel about that we have a
motion on the
floor but so I don't know if I'm I think
it's good it's good
I um I'm a little
concerned I just want to make sure that
people are going to see the entire
document yes no I'm not supp say because
when it's when
it's hared when it's in compl complete
it's hard to do it so this could so
you're um suggesting that this be a
pre-public hearing to the public hearing
that we have to do by law right that's
what I want that's what I'm suggesting
for that section that we advertise the
whole thing as an updated completed
whole and that there's a pre-public
adjust on the new section because to you
know the public didn't see that section
in its entirety
before can I clarify something it's not
just one new section right there's three
new sections so there's healthy and
natural environment there is
infrastructure which is now made up of
water super trash streets and the
housing elements so there's
three new sections
um sorry what say the three again it's a
healthy and natural environment
infrastructure and so that's really a
rearranging of like water sewer trash
everything that was put in appendices um
into an infrastructure element and then
a housing element so there really three
elements that we're talking okay yeah
inter related to
me what was that those sound ball inter
related to
me yeah that's that makes sense so I
don't want to speak at a turn sorry
K also we had some
changes from zoning that went into land
use the zoning plan the zoning plan that
was the I forget what
statute are you referring to the
Highlight the highlighted page we have
in here on page age I believe it's
41 is that and which I think you
submitted
Lynn right and it looked like a lot of
what had been in the proposed zoning
section has now been incorporated into
the future land use correct so um that
needs to be looked at too
and um okay I'm going to leave it at
that because I think we'll have we can
clarify when we get
to just if I may it sounds like there's
you need to need a hearing to let
everybody know what the changes are and
what's new and to direct them to review
what's new and what's changed and then
to like we both have to ad advertise
those things and talk to people about
them and then have a chance for people
to comment on them okay I think okay so
we had the motion and uh was the motion
sufficient
to me do we want to restate that
[Music]
clarify would you like it read back I'm
not sure exact but would you like the
motion could you read it okay best i c
was um how motion to advance advise
Board of Trustees to work with the
consultant for outreach on master plan
and public hearing on
information um sorry and information on
where they can find the updated master
plan
doesn't exactly get
to if I page um that did not sound like
it is clearly letting the trustees know
that we'd like to do a pre public
hearing which shows all the changes as
opposed to and I'm assuming as K Rose
has described give the public an
opportunity to see everything that's
been added and we'll have some time
frame on that and then that what comes
out of that process is the one that goes
to the formal statutorily required
public here is that what everybody's
thinking so then I think that needs to
be revised just a bit to indicate that
this would be an IT iterative
draft where every where people are made
aware of what's
changed since the June 21st draft Yeah
you can say it's an updated information
like an updated draft and this is an
informational session about what's
changed did we have a motion
don't can you you want to
remand
Reis let's not let's we don't have to
get too
fancy you want to hang on to it and just
amend it yeah put an amend it based upon
that it's that we'll have a free
hearing before the final public hearing
on the changes and additions that were
made on the draft
Master C can I change that from a
prehearing to a workshop here you go
thank you Workshop less form yeah that
way we can do it in a different format
similar way we did with the other ones
where we had people come and it was a
little more informal and a little easier
I think for you know just a more comp
comtable
environment okay that back now with the
amendment want to State it as a whole or
me to piece it together this is not my
normal job
[Music]
sorry um oh St just stated as a whole
again okay um let me get back up
[Music]
to so the board the Planning Commission
makes a motion to advise Board of trust
to work with consultant
for outreach on the master plan and to
have a workshop before the public
hearing on rises in additions to the
master
plan I think it needs to be tied
together some would like to make a
motion
I you
mind I'd like to make a motion to ask
the Board of Trustees
to approve
the use of the final five hours five
hours with the consultant
to help the Planning
Commission reach out to the
public and alert them to a workshop to
be
held for consideration of all changes
made to the draft master plan since the
June 21st draft was
I think so I also think it's five it
could be six hours but it's something
like that oh
maybe just without the number of hours
justs remaining hours remaining hours
yeah so you did we get at it
you you already have a motion in a
second so was she revising a motion you
wanted to withdraw your motion and and
well there's there's been a second so I
don't okay think she can let's say no we
just vote and then and then we can do a
second do a second motion okay so all
those in favor of ly's
motion all those
against okay do I have a new motion P if
you'll read as stated
okay motion from page a motion to ask
the board of truste need to approve the
use of the remaining hours with the
consultant to help Planning Commission
to reach out to the public and alert
them to a workshop to be held for
consideration of all the changes to the
master plan since the June 21st draft
was
published we have a
second
discussion all those in favor
I thank you to thank you I think Landing
libraries is a great idea I love it it's
great we'll do it
okay um
okay so I was just kind of curious about
the Motions of of actions that of votes
that have led up to now I compiled a a
list of all the minutes and there
actually quite a few missing minutes to
meetings so
um I don't
know um I didn't have time to really
read them thoroughly um before I got
here
so I don't have a whole lot to discuss
on that topic right now but it's
something that's um kind of interesting
what what's What official actions have
been voted on by the Planning Commission
pertaining to the master plan and what
have we maybe skipped over but um unless
anybody else has anything they want to
say on that I'm willing to forego more
discussion on that
topic okay
um okay so let's get um down to the some
of the new sections of the master
plan um agenda item four it's discussion
and work on the comps of Master Plan um
a first topic is health healthy and
natural
environment um we are looking at page is
there a packet back on that table for
the public at all I don't
know you might want to go and grab that
and you can follow along a little
bit you see it
there um the healthy natural environment
that's in the agenda packet is on page
of this packet page nine
and then we have the one that Lynn
submitted in
Pap so the page m one is um kind of a
reprint of the previous meeting correct
yeah I covered my most CLE one up papers
here
um ly do you want to start off on the
discussion about this one since you have
it in front of what
page there's this page copy yeah okay so
there's page nine the current um plan
that we have
EnV um so I'll I'll start I I'll make
preamble to
this so in the comprehensive planning
process um you can plan both the buils
and the natural environment and um my
concern we saw maybe a little bit more
of that because people overwhelmingly
seem to express the desire of live in
this nice World town you know the public
had a lot of sentiment around the trees
our environment our surroundings um so
just to kind of see that we do um put
some emphasis on that because we're
talking a lot about the built
environment you know housing streets
infrastructure in that way and um to
maybe see a little balance into the
future with the our green environment
too and that's what um kind of
motivated Lyn and I to um I I don't want
to speak for you but to um look into
this a little bit more and so part of
that um um let me see is dark sky part
of this a healthy natural environment we
we kind of wrote a little bit more about
the trees um but do you want to take it
from there man sure um so during the
last meeting what was discuss was in the
healthy natural environment was there
were done things that we had put in
there and
the which is in packet that's the
original what we had submitted so I went
through U the whole master plan find
where things were that we had put in had
already been stated in other parts of
the plan so that's what this strike and
comments and is this one here
um I did I do think it's better to put
the dark sky portion under
infrastructure because it is lighting so
and and that would be part of the build
versus natural so removing that and
putting it I think it did go under
infrastructure and then we only other
comment that I don't think much was
changed for the River
Park
North corrid so when you take out
all the uh things that we put in were in
other
mentioned and other goals in different
parts of the um master plan it ends up
being kind of an overview I can read it
Urban Forest overview our town is
recognized by the ARB Foundation as a
tree City
USA Urban Forest is valued as an
essential element of our infrastructure
and environment our three line streets
and park can as part of the first line
of defense in urban climate mitigation
and adaptations and our ecosystem assets
asset excuse me forests deliver enormous
utility like benefits in cities of town
cities City forest in the United States
provide 18.3 billion in benefits per
year and this number is expected to grow
as urban areas continue to expand and
then there's um a reference
so after taking out all the things that
we initially put in that were mentioned
in other parts of the master plan we
have a goal one of manage our Urban
green infrastructure as an
interconnected web of natural elements
and spaces that should be evaluated and
maintained to continue to provide
services such as storm water reduction
carbon capture and storage reduction of
ke Ison effect enhance public health and
air quality pollution removal prevent
pavement Road pavement fatigue decrease
rain water run up prevent oh that's in
there twice okay and then um as a policy
explore available funding sources for
carbon Factory City forest credits
developed as an impact score card
there's a reference this Endeavors for
the first time to identify the
attributes of
Equity health and environmental impacts
of urban Forest projects new funding
sources and economic potential may be
available and then policy two create a
plan and follow recommendations of 2021
tree survey by Colorado State Forest
Service C appending and there's a
reference and policy 13 parking of
vehicles trailers and any equipment
should be adequately planned for and not
impact the tree
gr so that's how it ends up if you take
out all of the other
um um goals and policies that we put in
that first draft um that have already
been stated in other parts of the
master does that make
sense so you now have it um dis still
down to one goal and three policies is
that right okay I might add that um
Urban Forest which is on page 99 of the
packet um it might I don't know Lynn how
much you compared your goals to the the
there's only one goal right now under
Urban forest and there's three policies
so my question is do you want to have a
healthy
environment with trees as well as
continue to have have the urban Forest
under
infrastructure um this is question for
you answer
that would it be the
same Urban forest and trees well I'm
just wondering so you want to at this
point um the the master plan would have
two places in the plan dealing with
trees right and I just didn't know if
you have if you like the urban Forest
the way it is
does it uh the content does it
um uh rise to the occasion of being
separated and and be contained in in the
urban
forest and then as well as we have an
environmental piece it's trees and the B
Corridor I just didn't know if there's
any redundancy between the two elements
or and if there is you want to be clear
when it comes to
infrastructure because I'm for the the
infrastructure it's properly care for
carefully replace tree and park trees to
manage improve expand the town's Urban
Forest which is more you're talking
about page nine I'm on page 99 now 99
yeah I'm on 99 because that's the um
current
proposed Forest sub element Happ I just
take some pages apart and all of a
sudden we can scramble um 99 okay Urban
Forest yeah so when I distilled this
down I I left those things in the master
plan that's why there are strike threes
so you you compared them comp okay so
and at this point you feel comfortable
that it'd be good to have trees still
still be in infrastructure so they're
being considered yes and then also give
trees their own Doom for all the other
um wonderful quality in the
environmental that that's all I'm asking
I don't really have an opinion I just
want to make sure that you're good with
having it in two
places well when you think about funding
not to um you know we can um fund work
on trees the street trees through our in
the like the HT taxs the infrastructure
it's it's allowed and so it's important
to
always um kind of remind ourselves that
trees are are part of our infrastructure
but they're they're they're more than
that and that's why it just felt like it
was necessary to um kind of tie it to
other benefits too elsewhere in the plan
um so you know I I was I don't know
where I saw I was at the library and I
found something about comprehensive
planning and and it was by what was that
it was a vibrant cities.org or something
and I can't for the life of me I can't
go back and find where it was but they
talked about how um attention to trees
has to feed through into other areas of
your comprehensive PL so when you're
doing storm water you're talking about
permeable Sur surfaces you're talking
about and I think our our plan kind of
does reference the um water capture
perable Services um but also they're
talking about do you want to do it in
land use like if people create parking
lots what what amount of cover tree
coverage do you wants to is there going
to be required number of trees that has
to be planted
per I don't know I don't foresee a lot
of parking lot activity happening inia
but um you know just to mitigate some of
that black the effective black top and
the heat island affect that um more more
and more Paving and human
uh that's kind of exactly so that's
covered in environment policy 3
um hold on one
second um okay go
on so I do think to leave in whatever is
referenced throughout the master plan
with Urban forest trees to leave as is
and if we are to add a healthy actual
environment element with this and the
river Corridor then you know we we take
this redacted copy
and and use
that and so this is this is it okay I
should have I thought that in to without
the strike out
okay because these mention yeah
throughout the whole
Master
okay so um I I like what you've written
here Lyn I'm I'm thinking I want to
digest a little bit more because there
one or two things that might be
appropriate to add to it but as it
stands I think it's good um but um you
know I didn't have time to look at it in
depth so
um do I have
any opinions or ideas paage you've been
kind of voal Lucy do you have anything
to say okay I you answered my question I
just want to make sure that what's in
the urban forest was there was no
intention for one to supersede another
okay um okay well so are we on the right
track with this and you on into of this
at this
point yeah so are you thinking um that
well we could make a motion to include
it into the draft of the plan but it
sounded like you maybe want to have a
chance to just to look at a little bit
more I was um I'm not I I think what
you've done is fine but I'm just kind of
wondering and um
you know it's a comprehensive plan it's
kind of like the big Vision but um what
was recently explained to me is the
reason why you kind of go down toward
more like a few action items like the
rway plan is done is it because it's it
starts kind of directing the board to
what the Planning Commission would like
to see you know how the vision would be
implemented and um how was explained to
me is like annually a Planning
Commission might meet and say okay how
how is our plan being implemented or has
you know how are these actions being are
are they being ignored or are you know
are we going in the right direction and
um I don't know if I'm being very clear
about this but like our former
comprehensive plan we didn't follow it
very well but it it was kind of vague in
a way because they they didn't have the
action meom so um like in the housing
action plan it kind of gives you that
type of Direction and um ridgeways plan
for instance had the action items and I
know that we talked about just removing
the contractor's action items a while
ago but is that is that kind of making
our plan just kind
of how how are things going to proceed
you know if we don't do that I mean
what's the point of having action items
in a comens of plan and I I I don't mean
to I I feel like I'm off on a new topic
right now frankly but um so and I'm not
so I guess what I want to look at here
is like maybe some of the language um
some of the recommendations like what
about budgeting making sure the town
budgets for things you know I'm I'm
talking to I I'd like to meet with you
about that and maybe like put our braing
together maybe just keep it as it is but
on the other hand we might see might see
to revise a few things but okay but I
think that's it's really great it's good
yeah so in a master plan is an
overarching document and um action items
are done regulatorily and
administratively so I don't think you
have to say ensure you have budget for
this because the budget is what the town
has to do administratively to ensure
that actions in the plan are being input
I don't think I'm articulating it page
I'm just kind of thinking out loud and
then I wanted to ask Stephan because I
can't remember but aren't there some
sections that talk about ensuring
adequate budget for certain pieces is
there anything in the plan right now in
any of the
elements that talks about money
sure through the chair I'm yeah yeah
answer that yes so
um not that I'm aware of I I think it's
the simple answer is I'm not aware of a
comprehensive plan directing any sort of
funding to be made available on any sort
of annual biannual basis or anything
like that no I'm not actually talking
about that in that sense but that
specifically but I'd like to just you
know I think that meet with you about
that I think the policies kind of
indicate you know where the action needs
to take place it it's not like in the
housing action plan which is a full
action plan where they recommend your
one your two your whatever five where
this is it's page set an overview so the
policies kind
of indicate where the emphasis should be
when
and decisions on in on certain things or
there's variances or budgeting so um for
instance and the ridway plan the their
action plan the description of it says
this chapter contains a comprehensive
list of actions to help support the
implementation of the master plan it
should be as a tool it should be used as
a tool to guide the preparation of the
annual Council strategic planning Town
Department work programs Improvement
planning and the allocation of Staff
time so it's kind of a guidance document
um based on the master plan that was
developed by the plan commission and
when I looked at it it's just it just
feels good to me I mean it um and I
don't know I don't know how this
compared to the one that we got rid of
but we've add added so many new um
portions to this that the old action
plan kind of wasn't very relevant in a
way but I think I'm kind of strin right
now but it's since we have um we have
other items to talk about and we're just
talking about what we've created so far
and perhaps we can touch on this later
um but um I guess I just want to see
some action you know I mean I'd like to
see some encouragement toward movement
and action with trees because this town
has a kind of a bad history with that um
you know we always do water we do
sidewalks we do Street projects but I've
never seen the town comprehensively look
at its trees and aside from you know
pruning in the park every now and then
because we get a a grant for
that but that's my explanation of where
I'm going with my brain and and I would
just like to say we haven't had the Exel
spreadsheet you know we have that now
and the tree board is being much more
active and I personally would not be in
favor of adding anything that looks like
strategic planning to the compreh no no
have you looked at this I have but that
should be the Strategic plan which is a
separate which we actually did about six
week six eight weeks ago when I talked
to Tom Tom Wills he he was sorry to
interrupt he was very um it was very
inspirational what he said and it made
clear sense to me and um you know I'm
sorry you didn't hear it but he was
talking about why you know you go from
the broad kind of to the more specific
but but at the same time you're not
you're not you're not getting so
specific but it's it's just kind of
giving you um instances of how you might
um you know move forward with that you
know anyway and I would Aline that
that's not the Planning Commission that
is the trustees in St I trust what Tom
BS was saying and maybe I'm not
articulating what he said very well but
so it's hard for you to on that because
maybe I'm not maybe it's getting Lost in
Translation well no I understand what
you're saying I I I just think you have
to be
careful
so we've done that right there are
action steps we call them policies so
you've got goals or objectives and
policies to meet and so that's the
distillation of that much larger broader
picture mentioned in the introduction to
goals to specific policies within each
element of this document so we've done
that we we we have an action we have
action steps it's it's in the draft that
you are that you're reviewing to try to
change something at this point um to to
add additional things like that
is remember it this is a living document
right so once it's approved you can
still suggest changes to it as long as
you follow the process list of the
statute okay I appreciate that stepan
what you're saying about about the
policies are essentially our action
items what would be nice is um to um
without saying they're action items or
whatever to describe what the policies
actually represent like you know Ridge
weight has done so we're clear on what
the meaning of the policies are why
we've created them and what they're
there to accomplish or why they're there
um so so in that sense it would be
yeah sorry so I think what I heard Paige
say I agree with and that really is more
of the Strategic plan taking the
policies and then U identifying action
items within a time frame yeah so that
would be separate separate yeah I I
don't think I'm articulating myself and
I articulated very well I'm just kind of
thinking out loud about this so um I'd
have to try to make it in the form of
a do we have oh that CL wrong sorry it's
an hour ahead
sorry okay did I see a hand up over
there
no
so can I just tell you exactly what was
distilled within our documents so we
have under the policies housing and
neighborhoods goal one housing one
maintain Pon as a community that is
access to a range of income levels ages
and households by ensuring adequate and
affordable housing options are available
then that's distilled into an action
item so I'm going to read to you an
action item which is a policy policy
housing 3 provide FastTrack processing
and other incentives for propos housing
developments intended for persons with
special housing needs including the
elderly that persons age 60 years or
older the handicapped low-income
residents and large families so there's
an action item there that that that's
been so this whole goal has been dispill
down into a specific action okay and
that's like in the policies yeah okay
great agree so I I'd like to look
through our policies with this just just
make sure we're not reading anything out
or but I think we're on the right track
here so um oh go
ahead I'd like to make a motion that we
um include healthy natural environment
into
Master as
addition
I'll I did all those in
favor
okay okay so next item
next item
is here it is okay healthy and natural
environment so are we happy um so we
that that's we talking about Dark Skies
the trees and that R part
that
okay as an as side I I don't know
Stephan's not in the room perhaps you
can answer
it
page is is there any budget for the
master plan next year in the budgeting
process um
it is it is whatever is left in our
grant
agreement that's available because um
it's kind of has to do with healthy
natural environment perhaps but what
about disaster preparedness and stuff
and I know there's a gentleman that came
to the council and he they were some
group was create was it the they were
creating a disaster plan for the Delta
County and they wanted some funding from
the town and I think I said wow we can
include that in our master plan and I
think there's been this consensus that a
master plan is a living document and we
can keep working on it but how do you
keep working on it if you don't have a
budget for
it every
year okay okay so there's a couple of
ways one it can be staff time but a ha
the hazard mitigation plan is an effort
on Delta County Emergency Management um
to coordinate with every municipality in
the county to create a document that
includes all of our critical facility
needs and how do how how do how we react
to an to a disaster or some sort of
emergency um that is a separate document
and it's it's not a comprehensive
planning document nor an element it's
called A continuing of operations plan
and so what we're talking about are two
different things you're talking about a
comprehensive plan or a document that
for continuation of operations it can
also be known as a municipal
comprehensive emergency management plan
in which a coupe when that continuing of
operations plan is is a section so it's
a completely different document it's
really meant for Public Safety okay and
what is the comprehensive plan address
when it comes to hazards and natural
hazards flooding that kind of stuff how
how do we address those things um I
think you guys can have a of that so we
don't adjust dis in any way in the the
comprehensive plan well so what you're
talking about is for an emergency
management plan is once a disaster
strikes what do you do that's not a
comprehensive planning document that's
something meant for Public Safety and
administration what you want to talk
about are like steep slope um and
development so that's your future land
use plan that's where that would go into
into that element and I think we
actually have some in here already think
we with Zing I think so it would be
steep slope um flood plane management
but that also you know that's just
telling people where they should should
not develop right it's it's telling
people developers hey maybe this isn't a
best a good place to build a a highrise
right next to a you know a cliff
so it's it's in here it's just a
guidance Stu and storm water management
might be having to do with disasters in
a way right to mitigate the effects of
like floods or deluges we do have
something in infrastructure yeah we do
have something on storm water I
know um but I'm just want worried about
like high winds like taking down our
Urban forest or something no
and I don't know but then again that
goes back to all we'll talk about
maintenance and why you would do
maintenance and okay never mind okay so
yeah the blood water is in
infrastructure or the storm water um
development let's move on to zoning it's
Item B I found it if you can so that's
that's goal infra for infrastructure 11
protect the community from adverse
flooding and pollution impacts of runoff
with efficient Progressive storm water
management Pro practices policy INF for
storm water 5 talks about coordinate
storm drainage and flood management with
appropriate agencies including Delta
County local irrigation ditch companies
and the Federal Emergency Management
ages so so we've we've addressed that
and what page is that on second um in
the packet that is 189 okay
18 okay thank you I've got another
policy infrastructure storm water 7
establish and maintain flood plane
buffers to ensure compliance with FEMA
required flood plane regulations to
promote water quality and to improve
reran habitat when possible encourage
the use of natural runoff filtration
such as bile SES perious payment
pavement etc for on-site attention okay
and that was page still okay great
thanks I'm getting some ideas from this
okay great
um it's also mentioned in the healthy
natural environment Go one um maintained
uh an interconnected web natural
elements and spaces that should be
elevated and maintained to continue to
provide services such as storm water
reduction so it's in it's there in terms
of the forest okay great
thanks okay um and that
was that that doesn't have a page
yet okay but it's in this new amending
section okay great thank you
so um zoning uh next
um so there's a little bit of a zoning
element that was written here and um
it's on for that I was looking
at it's about p
11 thank you page 13 and the packet
tonight we have the some wording that
was drafted for potentially for a zoning
component of the master plan and that
was inspired by the
statute um I don't have my Statute in
front of me um but it does say that the
master plan should include a zoning plan
that talks about the height density bul
location of structures blah blah blah so
that's what um kind
of motivated this
so anything to add Lynn and I both
worked on
this Lynn so then my my question to
everyone is should we keep this as its
own section or should it be um included
into land use
um and I did take the land use section
and put it in in areas where the certain
things we came up with weren't there so
what is what's more appropriate I guess
was my question for the commission I
vote for it to be in the land use so my
question is when the statute says you
may have a zoning plan what is the
statute mean by that okay Stephan so
it's a zoning plan specific to
protecting solar access of of bable lots
it's not saying that you're going to
roll out this comprehensive Plan and
there's going to be a sweeping change of
zoning throughout you know zoning
categories throughout town this is
saying you're going to create something
that allows for this um solar access in
within your comprehensive plan um can I
make one suggestion to the to the
policies so we have multiple bullet
points and it would be more appropriate
to have each bullet point be a policy so
that first bullet point that we see on
page 13 it says policy Zone one that
should be policy Zone one the next one
next Bull point should be policy Zone
too that that
keeps you know continuing with the
instead of having bullet points under
the policies you have them as each each
one is a that's very helpful correct
okay and
[Music]
that oh go ahead a question for Stefan
so that's under the future land use plan
where I have the bullet points is that
what you're talking about yeah it's like
right here be
[Music]
has taken a l of these buet
points future fut and they're
highlighted in
yellow 41 right so we have 41 and we
have page 13
okay um St yeah there are some policies
that really shouldn't be in here
um specifically under this like policy
zone three that first bullet point
encourageing diversity of housing
options that meet the needs of residents
is Define and allow the locations
designated for residential uses by the
land use code that's that's really not
what that that section of Statute is
trying to get at it's so I would and
we've already addressed that within the
housing
element um the other one that second
bullet point there that says review and
update the town zoning regulations and
Maps I'm not I'm not sure I'm looking at
the right oh you're under three I'm
under 13 policy zone three at the bottom
of the page yeah that's that's not
something that that should go in there
either um unless it's pretty specific to
ensure that um we're protecting solar
access of bual lots okay
okay so unless it's specific to
something yeah let um I think it would
be helpful to read that
statute us I could read
it you want to read into the record yeah
I think that would it would be good to
hear what we're talk about okay um and
I'm reading out of the comment table I
have actual CRS okay if you want to go
do that what's what's the CRS number did
you site okay so we're CRS 1-23 d206 the
master plan and it's
C it's not C plan required inclusion of
a m oh I'm
[Music]
sorry okay y f sorry a zoning plan for
the control of the height area bulk
location and use of buildings and
premises such a zoning plan may protect
and assure access to appropriate
conditions for solar wind or other
alternative energy sources including GE
thermal energy used for water heating or
space heating or Cooling in a single
building for space heating for more than
one building through a pipeline Network
or for electricity generation however
regulations and restrictions of the
height number of stories size of
buildings and other structures and the
height location of trees and other
vegetation shall not apply to existing
buildings structures trees or vegetation
except for new growth on such vegetation
that's the CRS CRS 3123 206
F okay
so we want to um unless specific to
unless it's specific to
something more specific that that's
that's something you would recommend
striking so I'm gonna just put a
question mark by that and put a dash
line this one right there yeah and um
Stefan the one before that encourage the
diversity of housing options that you
you said that that's not really
appropriate there in your policy tree
right because we we already talked about
housing needs assessment the housing
element yeah and the housing element and
then um so do you want to continue on to
the the next bullet point after that um
so have we established that
um okay we kind of just started in the
middle of these bullet points do we want
to go through everyone or um is there
anything else that looks like could be
concerning yeah the develop of a develop
a pay and L of parking program for the
that's on page 14 correct that's
something that shouldn't be an a
confence plan at all that's Regin for
yeah
okay he's saying this one here I wish I
pen um it's sorry it's I'm on page
14 at the top there it's two regulatory
it's too
specific
um um okay so the next one identify
locations for lodging short-term rental
uses that are sensitive to local
neighborhoods and in compliance with
zoning
regulations and this is all part of the
zoning plan right just trying to tie it
back to the the title of the heading of
this section um is that appropriate that
again that's more Regulatory and there
is a a short-term rental regulating
ordinance on the November 12th agenda
for the Board of Trustees okay would you
say something more like to um um protect
the uh lifestyle or um what what is it
like the quality of life that the the
residents have expressed you know
wanting to
um like to keep that that the town would
identify areas that you know and so it's
like more of a um what am I'm trying to
say it's more General it's not so
specific but to um have some show that
there is an awareness that citizens are
concerned with um short-term rental
impacting the residential quality of
life you know because um you know so
you're not really regulating in the
comprehensive plan but you're
acknowledging ing that it was a concern
of citizens um in this process so again
that's it's regulatory it shouldn't be
in the comprehensive plan there's an
ordinance regulating short-term rentals
on the November 12th meeting for the
Board of Trustees okay um so it it
doesn't belong in this document we did a
housing needs assessment and a housing
action plan it was identified in a
housing action plan not a comprehensive
plan housing action plan that we under
that the town undertook to meet meet the
requirements of proposition 123 for
affordable housing and it was an item
listed as something that should be done
within within a relatively short amount
of time with and um after a meeting on
May 9th
where it was a joint meeting I believe
the brand commission Board of Trustees
maybe just the Board of Trustees um it
was talked about in pretty great detail
and it it was a work joint work session
on shortterm rentals and adus on my
birthday May 9th of 2024 and um during
that it was there was there was some
items that were listed um that should go
into become regulatory in pretty short
order and the me the after Action Memo
that I received from Shay hober of urban
rural Continuum said that the proposal
to have all Str strs licensed no later
than January 1st 2025 did not receive
any comments so I'd interpret that as if
it was generally acceptable so we can we
can expect to see regulations in place
going into 2025 for short okay you mean
state regulations or no regulation okay
so um but when you say regulations where
is that addressed is that addressed in
the um chapter 16 and the land use code
or is that addressed as a police
ordinance I have the draft in front of
me so ordinance 20245 in ordinance of
the town of Pon Colorado enacting
Article Five short-term rental licenses
of chapter six business license the
regulations of the P municipal code in
article 8 short-term rental regulations
of chapter 160 so it's two places within
our so I mean if it's a use if it's a
land use isn't that something that it's
appropriate to even acknowledg somehow
in the comprehensive plan without being
specific because if if it's actually
land use in chapter 16 it means that
that um comprehensive that kind of deal
deals with planning and zoning doesn't
it so the comprehensive plan is an
advisory document only okay what we're
talking about with regulating short-term
rentals is literally regulations that's
done on the legislative side of the
Board of Trustees as an ordinance so
something that becomes cified within the
P
[Music]
yeah okay I I'll not to be a dead horse
I I'm not asking more questions on that
but I I still don't think my question's
answered but but I I think the
um goals and policies in the housing
element get to ensuring there's housing
for residents and for so to me that's
what the plan says is make sure that
there are places for people to live and
then this is one of the tools that that
is that the town can do to ensure that
there's places for people to live so is
that all just places to live or is it a
quality of life issue oh it's all of it
it's all of it yeah I when you read the
housing just read the intro to the
housing element and it talks about and
and every one of their elements and the
vision statement is all about
maintaining the quality of life so that
to me that overarching desire that the
public expressed in all our meetings is
just baked in throughout the master plan
so does the housing action plan
supersede um the policy recommendations
of the Planning Commission I mean is it
something that's more specific spefic
for instance like it says get rid of
your setbacks you know change the
setbacks to make it more easy to build
adus or no the master plan is the
overarching okay and it wouldn't get
master plan shouldn't get into setbacks
okay because they well if we're talking
about solar setbacks and protecting
people's properties but not prescriptive
you're not giving the distance yeah
which is where that goes into the code
it's the overarching protect you to me
this is a protective document in terms
of you need to think of these list of
things when you're making decision so it
supersedes the housing action plan so if
someone says I want to build this like
two feet from my neighbor's property and
you don't have any setbacks because you
got rid of them all because that's what
the housing action plan recommended you
would still have to consider the master
plan first and what the will of the
people was in that document is that
correct okay so so the housing action
plan is not code yeah it it's it it's
it's not been codified it is not part of
a code there was no ordinance change the
housing action plan is an advisory
document to the Board of Trustees on how
they should regulate things in the
future okay so having a comprehensive
plan that's advisory kind of you know
especially for the housing element that
has policies and goals it shows a very
prescriptive way of enfor form in new
development or infield development so
that we stop urban sprawl so it's
completely two separate documents I
didn't want to tell you that the seventh
whereas in the proposed draft ordinance
of regular short rental says whereas the
Board of Trustees of the Town held
extensive public input meetings and
workshops to determine appropriate
methods of regulating short to rentals
and through those meetings it was
determined that uncontrolled and
unregulated short-term rentals may also
have a direct effect on the quality and
character of the community and
individual neighborhoods and properties
town so as a regulatory document is it's
it's referencing what we've talked about
at nauseum in all these meetings and and
putting it into actual code
okay and that's something that's in the
works what what what meeting is that
going to be present November 12th
November 12th that's correct okay
um Lynn did you oh okay well since this
is a subject going on and it's my my
main interest I uh first of I just
wanted to say I I scanned through the
the plan and I'm really impressed of the
depth of everything that's been U
developed so
far and as far as uh adus or tiny houses
and affordable
housing uh
I had a conversation with the Town
Administrator about my
proposal um to tear out a old shack of a
garage out of the alley and put in a one
and a half car garage in a little
studio uh with a lowf flow shower toilet
sink and I was informed that
uh that couldn't happen because of the
water tap moratorium with the additional
line issue
I don't know how far things have gotten
with that but reading this it sounds
like uh Abus is an important thing it's
uh promoted in this plan as a as a
somewhat of a priority and
um I was told that uh there's Grant
funds available to
support uh adus possibly coming uh but
the John administrator said that he
couldn't get it because uh he did have
the infrastructure of water sewer but
not I mean sewer um but not
water and uh so hopefully things have
been moving forward on those issues that
are in the
way
um I think that uh what I saw on the
plan is the positive aspects of uh
supporting green uh and energy efficient
development and in building new new uh
housing and uh adus are primed for that
it's uh really easy to to to build
really energy
efficient uh homes that support uh
affordable housing and
um and it's really overdue uh affordable
housing is like a crisis
basically and uh we want to support um a
community here that really um helps us
to live in a way that supports community
and having a an ability for me for
instance to have a a little apartment
for my daughter to live in or for me to
live in or other people to live in my
house so that we can uh live with the
people who we want to live with who what
is single family housing but my family
whoever my people are so that uh we can
support each other for taking care of
our animals when other people can travel
and come back and and and just make life
better uh and
[Music]
so there are adus going on in Grand
Junction for instance I'm hoping that
people are looking into how they did it
and uh what are some of the
infrastructure requirement place to park
or you know are you looking at other
communities for input on how to go about
getting this to work in a good way it's
ridiculous to think of uh having to have
an additional water tap to have a low
for flow shower uh and sink there's a a
person just three houses down from ma
who put an entire irrigation system in
their property on Town water
on a timer burning thousands of gallons
of water I'm talking about enough water
to water a tree to have a little slow
flow shower sink toilet so this deal
about an additional bathroom not being
allowed is really basically ridiculous I
have my water tap just like everybody
else I paid for it while somebody else
is running thousands of gallons to water
their trees or water their yard which is
at least as big as m
Roger I'm done with that I'm can spill
all that out I don't know I just want I
don't know what's all been developed so
I'm yeah speaking ignorantly of what is
is really happening I just wanted to say
that much because uh and I could say
more no it's good to hear your comments
I think um you're probably getting a
little bit down more into the specifics
right so it's good to have that in mind
because I'm sure the stuff will be
coming in front of the Planning
Commission
um and you'll have more time to talk
about it but it looks like
adus they're definitely something that's
going to be part of the plan and part of
the um but you know as we get closer to
that it's the Board of Trustees who will
probably be you know regulating things
as well with that and and there's a lot
to still be hammered out with the whole
water thing but the comprehensive plan
is going to be dealing with the next 20
years too so you know we kind of have to
think
in that sense yeah look time is going by
life's carrying on so it's getting in
way my life yeah I would like to have
the ability to live the way I want to
live now about 10 years from now it's
when you're years old you
know like time is now we need it no we
understand that I think there's a real
consensus in the community that you know
people want to move forward with
affordable housing opportunities we're
trying to figure that out and uh really
uh what else was I had in mind there but
um you
know we have an opportunity to have a
sustainable Community within our own
self here by doing this in the right way
so we really have to depend on the
outside world even that much really so
that we can create our own way of living
in an affordable way that supports
everyone
um and still
keep the quality of the small town and
not have to build a lot of other
developments and and such which doesn't
happen that easy anyway in P because so
many of the ranches and what not are in
conservation ements can't really be
subdivided in this part of the county
and so hopefully there can be a way that
we can create adus or other little State
Spate I mean like the co-housing thing
on the end of Third Avenue is really
positive thing you know anyway I'm
hoping that we can and it I'm really
impressed what I what I just scan
through and uh hope we can really make
this happen sooner than later and get
past this ridiculous thing about
this additional line that's been holding
us back otherwise get get it together
look at Grand Junction or whatever other
Avenue news you can to know how to go
about making this work because I have a
friend in Grand Junction it lives in
he's in his his kids had a garage so he
he needs support he's older they built
him in the ad it's I think it's a th000
square feet is maximum in the Grand
Junction or something like that yeah so
they get to live together thank
Roger okay great thanks for coming too
thanks for paying
attention okay is there is there a town
meeting tomorrow no it's next Tuesday is
that next Tuesday yeah it'll be next
week there there is next week next week
yeah yeah we got an
off um second Tuesday second fourth
Tuesday of the month okay so zoning we
were looking at um let's keep going
through this is that all right for page
14 um so we were
saying um you didn't like that next
bullet point the second bullet point um
third bullet
point
[Music]
um um there's a spelling error here oh
it's not Gentile density it's gentle
density the third bullet point I think
that's
also addressed in the housing action
plan well yeah I don't know I guess I
want to know exactly where in the
housing action plan this is being
addressed because I mean we are talking
about instead of allowing sprawl we're
going to take it all on here and does
that mean our lots have to all be half
as big as they are because we have way
more housing and that could really
impact the quality of life for the
people who live here so um I guess I I I
want to keep that I'm not saying strike
that right now but I just want to see
where it's addressed so I can you know
just like we yeah um we tried to make
sure the tree thing wasn't being
redundant elsewhere I want to kind of
see what this could
be repe repeating so that was bullet
point
three um develop fundamental site
planing principles to protect the value
of surrounding properties while allowing
gentle
density um small accessory dwelling unit
should be compatible with the lot scale
and size so if there is something that
conflicts that with that I I if we could
pull that up that would be great um move
on to the fourth bullet point Ure and so
all of these would be policies so that's
I guess Stephan was
saying um cutting out a you you know you
don't have 50 policies here you know so
that would be beneficial ensure
residential and Commercial uses of the
downtown commercial cor is clearly
defined and described in the zoning code
to provide locals stability and
contribute to economic
Prosperity I think that's that's good in
housing and in econ
okay so that could be in housing and Eon
I guess I'd like to
know um where that would appear
don't want to step on the toes of those
two
sections
um so repeat to me again what was the
point of the zoning plan as um it was
all just about the um the 3123 206f that
was the only yep um reason to have a
zoning plan to address that portion of
the
statute okay it would be good to look at
this again without in mind um
takes me a while to digest St
um okay so so you were saying this was
in housing in Eon so the one above and
below so I'd like to search for that
okay um policy zone four balance water
conservation with preservation and
addition of critical green spaces with
water sensitive
Landscapes so is that kind of redundant
too and that would be found in um
infra or in the water section
probably okay ensure growth is sensitive
to existing viewsheds is appropriate for
the community is based on land use code
rision section e land use code
regulations review that's in housing
that's in housing it's actually one of
the ones that Pete did like okay and
this
is can you find these in housing easily
do you
know how do you locate these
things so I didn't do that with this one
okay so you sheds
yeah yeah I I think all the references
to veds are typic oh yeah I guess there
was something in housing about
veds I might I think you have gone away
from what the statute asked for yeah I
think it'd be good to make sure that
what the statute required is going to be
included for sure because honestly a lot
of these are already in the other
elements I'd really like to see an
example of a zoning plan um that would
be kind of interesting to see what one
looks like actually and what do you mean
by Zing plan well when it says the
comprehensive plan rest of zoning
portion I mean what does that look like
what do other TS do for that zoning
portion I think that a lot of what you
had in here gets to where the the the
first point of it the solar you know
and perect solar access that portion and
it seemed to me if I could ask Stefan
another question that um the housing
element I
think talked about that already too
prot solar
access that's easy to find right but um
okay so okay so um so when we're talking
about the gateways and all that kind of
stuff that's been mentioned elsewhere so
this zoning
element basically has to do with
structure zoning and land use codes to
protect the solar access so that was
that was sufficient for that um
if we so let's just skim through this
really
quickly um Green Building adopt codes
for tiny homes consider live work spaces
this is all something that might go be
addressed somewhere else right say which
one again I was doing you go down to um
um policy zone four and I'm going
through the bullet points okay let me
get back to page
13 14 14 sorry
and you're update land use and building
codes to remove
barriers um yeah yeah and that's all
kind of that's it's not about the height
shape density B whatever that really is
already elsewhere okay so I'm just like
like that X
and I can still read it and consider
that I'm putting an X through mine just
to say it might be elsewhere not really
appropriate
here okay stepan so carbon within their
comprehensive plan have an element
called zoning and land use so it looks
like theyve
added that zoning piece into their land
use okay um let's
see and they say things like um within
their policies let's
look um their policy
1.4.5 review current UDC Building height
requirements and amend as necessary UDC
is something we haven't done yet
carbondale's a a home rural community
they're not a statutory community and
and what they've done is they've done a
comprehensive plan and they've they've
worked on that with a uniform
development code a ugc a UDC so um we
don't have that we
have different chapters related to
zoning and to land use and so that's
that's a little bit different okay but
they're also home rules so they can do a
lot of different things with their as
their Charter allows
yes okay so was there language in there
that you thought was helpful for eror I
just did a cursory review see if they
had okay so what was your um search
terms or did you just go to Carbondale
and look at their I gu the master plan
okay so it' be interesting to see what
statutory if there's an example of a
good set because even
ridway stat but I mean yeah okay so they
do things a little differently okay so
um essentially the rest of this is kind
of okay what about policy Zone
annexation that's kind of different from
zoning isn't it or is it um it's
addressed annexation is addressed
somewhere else in the plan future land
use future land use
yeah um
okay great so that kind of took care a
lot of that um if you go um Lyn um I
just want to clarify so what we're
really leaving in is just policy Zone
one for the
solar that's all I'm sorry but I was
thinking about I'm hungry and I really
want a peanut butter
sandwich what was that so based upon
this document we're just we're just
keeping in policy Zone one with the
solar
information the rest is thought we're
striking everything everything after
what you've written as Zone one that
first section Z to is all and it could
be incorporated into something else it
sounds like like land use zoning and
land use or something so we might take
these statements and move it somewhere
else in the plan right I think I I did
recommend doing that
putting whatever so it looks like we
just end up with
this on page 41 is where you had taken a
bunch of your bullet points yeah 41 we
can just pull those all out and only add
in the Solar
is that
CRA would would that
work two bullet points just go into
future land use or would they go
[Music]
into I got to get back to that page I'm
sorry1 13 and 41 14 and would it be
better so we were looking at just the
first policy is the only one you'd keep
with the two bullet points there and
column policy one and policy two on the
bottom P 13 there then everything else
is kind of struck in a
way so you would keep policy Zone one
and then those two would be policy Zone
one policy zone two yeah two points
where would they be appropriating the
master
plan
umbly land use and right now they're in
uh
um
sorry go ahead they're under uh Lynn had
added a bunch of the bullet points but
she um had these in particular are added
into key
considerations in the intro to the
Future land use which is on page 41 of
this
packet yeah they I just put what we put
in zoning in that so those would come up
right and so it would start with
maintain the town's agricultural Legacy
and its connection to Agricultural and
public lands would be the first remain
bullet because I think that's in the
original and then the next one would be
identify areas to accommodate increase
demand and then I'm not
sure well if you go to on page 41 where
it's what isn't in yellow is existing
text that was in there okay um in the
previous versions in
the why is town trying to maintain the
agricultural Legacy it's not like we
have agriculture in town
so that's all part of the
vision yeah there was extensive public
comments about maintaining this
agrarian kind of small town field so
it's interesting because in Fort
Collins the whole town is um zoned for
agriculture it's not like a certain land
use area it's like anywhere in town can
have a have a um agricultural use it's
kind of interesting Fort Collins
good yeah and then it it kind of
describes in detail what that actually
means but it's kind of crazy no it's
actually good I know but there's so many
people there it's interesting I
know I'm just coming to show so of the
yellow you did those are the two bullet
points that are on page
[Music]
13 right this is on page 42 yeah I was
looking at 41 so it's right in the
middle of the yellow yeah so I think
based on the conversation all the other
yellow would not get included other than
those two bullet points and I was going
to show this to
step and it's that something stepan can
do and since it's very just just wanted
you to see that so theny had Tak all
their bullet points and put them in it's
this is a kind of a
separatec on page 42 because um Lynn had
yeah so the yellow correlates to the
bullet points that are on page oh okay
but in the discussion we're having none
of those will get right brought into the
future land use other than these two
bullet points comp and it's on page 42
okay comply with CRS 38
38368 did you get that and I'm I I'm not
saying that we have to I just wanted to
make it clear what everybody did you and
you've got just what we're left with of
the yellow that the yellow just
taking like this one that you here the
development about small accessory units
shall be compatible with lot and size
and scale
and I just want to see where that's
repeated and in the housing before I
would take that
out and my question is does do these two
bullet points seem to fit under key
considerations in future Landers that
that's just what I wanted to look at
yeah and kind of get Stephan's thoughts
does it seem in keeping or is it too
granular for key
considerations I think the comply with
is absolutely should be there I mean
it's despite it being maybe granular
it's this is a good place to put it
under key considerations
okay that's all I wonder or did it need
to go in some other element like housing
or no as long as we refer the whole plan
when we do so we don't we look at
everything when we decide to do one
thing hopefully yeah
anyway um okay
so that kind of took care of that right
that was the zoning portion is that
correct we need to make a
motion yeah
let's do you want to make a motion
page are you happy with that yep okay um
I'm going to go back to page
133 and
just identify those bullet points anyone
second
14 scroll
down um I make a motion that propos
policy
Zone
one and the two bullet points underneath
that
sorry I'd make a motion that we adopt
the two bullet points provided under
policy Zone
one and those be relocated
under future land use key
considerations
second
discussion all those in favor
I okay
okay so the next
it which one you looking
atru no I'm looking for my
agenda C is infrastructure but yeah okay
infrastructure is the next one
yes so what we on
now at
19 I think it starts with the
infrastructure I mean it starts in 16
with a lot
of oh and I I would recommend that
instead of looking at this version of
infrastructure because I think this is
Stephan's original infrastructure
element that it'd be better to go look
at the infrastructure element in
the the entire plan because that has
changed es okay does that have a page
find it SC um Beyond I think
it's after so the comprehensive
plan the um stri and underline version
is on page 50 and now I would recommend
we look at the strike and underline
version because then you'll see changes
made to that infrastructure
[Music]
element um as proposed
last last meeting and infrastructure to
find looks like it begins on age 82 of
the thank you y just got
just a clarifying question of Lynn okay
Lynn that this infrastructure element
was in as a separate um piece of the
this agenda packet is that because you
had made some changes to it and had
emailed it to the seven
I don't think I think the only change I
made is I moved dark sky over into okay
okay so um we had a dark sky already in
infrastructure and I think you have
proposed to up to um revise it based on
yours okay and I
think
um I looked at it and I didn't see
anything that wasn't sort of already
captured um in in the placeholder of
your original dark skies because Dark
Skies you've had three versions three
iterations of your dark skies and your
last one maybe we should go back forget
what I just said let's go back
to the um house the infrastructure
element that is a standalone and it is
just before the table of comments
hang on I did add things some things in
there and that's why
I that's why I wanted to make sure that
I wasn't overriding you as a separate
thing for infrastructure so you made
some changes in addition to the Dark
Skies
piece in dark sky
element um I don't know if that got
changed into what our package I um
unless did you happen to embed it into
this let me
Mo confusing
every
um there's like four policies and I
think initially there were just one or
two two okay and this Dark Skies is not
in this excerpted out housing element
when I go to page 30
it ends at Urban Forest I think dark I
think the Dark Skies is the last piece
of
infrastructure healthy natural
environment no infrastructure
infrastructure oh yeah was the last last
pie page 99 oh and it's on page 100 then
is the dark
spies I'm few so why is why again is um
dark
infrastructure the street lights are we
talking about the electrical grid is up
what it's because it's all fixtures
light fixtures so you're talking about
the built environment built environment
okay yeah yeah this is what's on page
100 is okay great thank
you
and yeah if it stays an infastructure
it would be that otherwise it would go
back to healthy natural environment but
I think it's more appropriate in
infrastructure you know you could always
have a section healthy National
environment that would flush anything
out but would direct people to the
portion of the plan like dark skes
infrastructure but you can probably do
that in the table of contents I guess
yeah I think so under
infrastructure I think it's stronger
there
okay if I might I think what's on page
100 does not necessarily reflect your
latest version of the Dark Skies I think
it do do you yeah because when I looked
at it it looked like you had you had
changed language just a little bit but I
think it gets it everything you had just
you had some minor wording
modifications but if it looks good it's
on
100 yeah
discussion
this
question make a motion on Dark Skies in
infrastructure we didn't already do a
motion Dark Skies the
infrastruct no we didn't well so you
made a
motion about the healthy natural
environment master
plan um with the changes you
made one of those changes being dark
skies be M to infrastructure so in a
roundabout way
okay
great um so are we happy with everything
are you happy with I mean you must be
because you wrote
it right yes with it thank you okay
Stephan did you have anything to add to
this at all
to Dark Skies
yeah and that's on
page 100 there's a page 46 on there of
the comp that's 100 the
packet um other than changing the policy
to not saying 1.1
to I'm looking at page 15 is that not
the right place um no
100 look at
that so this is pretty similar to what
was already presented
just that's great so format it properly
it's
good I do have one question policy for
dark SK 2 um is the 2032 requirement is
that based on the ordinance it's already
in
place meet the requirements of the dark
internation when the first ordinance was
passed it's based on
um the only suggestion I would have for
that is to reference the ordinance that
way it's easy to
recall is
that or I don't like to have too many
versions
iteration and I think that that Orin is
supposedly is going to be changed so it
can be enforced is that correct because
it oh yeah that's one of the ones that
was in limbo there so but we have't
codified so maybe just the P the PMC
citation instead of actual ordinance
number so we do p ofc
cation does that make sense just to the
section the section remain
[Music]
before it could be enforced
correct yeah and then the measuring
equipment thing too but that's what the
measuring the Light
Equipment we we put it on okay roof here
okay so um so that's all okay right and
we have a notion that we made to we just
have a recap of the motions and the
actions that we took during this meeting
I don't know if you can just repeat
um
yeah motion to adise Board of Trustees
to work with consultant for outreach on
master plan and public oh sorry I think
that was no that was
and public hearing information on where
they can find information on updates
that did not pass updated replacement
motion from commission Smith or mayor
Smith sorry motion to ask the Board of
Trustees to approve the use of remaining
hours with the consultant help the
planing commission to reach out to the
public and alert them to a workshop to
be held for consideration of all changes
to the master plan since the June 21st
draft published motion
passed um m how motion that we include
healthy natural environment to the
master plan as an addition with
adjustments um motion
pass's motion I make motion that we
adopt the second bullet points under the
policy one that those be located under
key land
use and that's all the
motions emotion was a little obus and
you know that one um we have the
recording so I can catch I might have
missed part of the exact wording that
we'll catch on the recording to get that
precise in the minutes good because what
I'm afraid is I might not have uh
directed to what document I was looking
at okay so not to be a to but how are we
adopting the healthy natural environment
if we just said that we're kind of
putting the Dark Skies into
infrastructure right that's F question
where do we with the the verbage about
that
um where this is not an exact train
script yet so let me
see um
so at one point it was uh CH Watson we
are on the right track with this and
what we want to oh wait no sorry that
was motion you said not to me um
um that exact transcript I won want to
say for sure what all changes you made
but um I believe it was that the
redundancies that not sure how we wented
out and had been strien or commented on
be accepted that they be accepted as the
suggestions that you made in that
document did we say where the plan was
going to be or just accept it yeah
should we make a
motion we because I didn't I don't
really see where we made we actually
made a motion to move Dark Skies into
infrastructure I think it was a broad
statement with the suggested changes it
could be a little more
okay do we need to be more specific
commissioner how if you want make a
motion yes I would like to make a motion
that we move the dark sky element from
healthy natural environment to the last
portion of
infrastructure I'll second
down was
quick okay all those favor any discuss
discussion yes I would add that this
motion supersedes any other motion that
may have been made earlier in the
meeting okay as you would say yes yeah
this motion supersedes any other motion
made previously or
discussion all those in favor
I okay so um we're
8:00 or 9:00 whatever CL
you're um I don't know I think we
accomplished a few things here are are
um I don't
know I'm frankly I'm feeling kind of
tired I don't know I'm I'm ready to call
it a night I don't know if you're
satisfied with how far that we've gotten
here and we've made some progress that's
what was the last thing lost my agenda
um and we were going to do housing and
then um more I think we I think we
stopped the infastructure right and then
after that yeah I don't believe we had a
motion on infrastructure and the
remaining three it infastructure housing
and we we didn't have a motion on
infrastructure to accept the whole thing
you mean right oh we didn't we didn't
really finish our discussion on
infrastructure did
I mean we didn't go through it no I yeah
thank you
Luc okay so where did we leave up we
kind of got sidetracked by the very last
page of infrastructure which was Dark
Skies we jumped to the end
without I was like it nothing sandwich
nothing in the middle okay so on what
page are we on
then infrastructure let me get keep us
in this part this is the strike an
underlying
version it starts on
[Music]
page starts on page
82 okay
ask for a five minute recess sure
[Music]
the
updated2 right there yeah in the pack
okay
[Music]
SO2 so I was I was on the Planning
Commission I was also the
administrator and uh would take and and
they made be the
secondary so I would take notes I would
write the minutes during the
meeting as we were as we were having
discussion I hope they are pay
you um they actually paid man commission
members uh 20 bucks a meeting wow yeah
but State Statute allowed for that and
this in Florida Indiana Oh in
Indiana I know I often when I'm
secretary I'm
some nonprofit or board I do the same
thing I
just that's what Michelle P She was
excellent and she could she had it all
you me shorthand or something yeah and
then I just go through I remember she C
up right
that's I have them my goal was have them
within 48 Hours set to everyone so that
they can see it ahead of time yeah you
can do it to do that
yeah I I love doing that because
otherwise I'm going to totally
forget and I don't I can type faster
than I can hand write but it was nice
that Indiana Law allowed for what they
called
um God it was like
not it was meant just to compensate you
for your time but not like an actual
wage and as long as it wasu they said 20
bucks meetings
right I always told AUM I said depends
on how many meetings we
have that's our Dark Skies was right
yeah what page was dark skies on 100 100
on the strik and underline version I
think that's the version we're in
[Music]
yeah
here and this is and this is1 so
infrastructure started on
okay 82 up the really squared numbers
not yeah left
side okay are we all
back great
so so we're on page we're looking at
infrastructure agenda and it's on page
82 square box of the packet page 82 of
the
packet get the sweater of my
head um
okay
so so anybody have any comments to begin
with here opening this up
I wait for a moment and get
chocolate
only until
11 I'm G
grab would you like
wuts I have a
questioning what where we at
with oh
my all right most of the maps would be
broken out from the existing future land
use map it's just so busy that we can
turn layers on and off and pull extract
the layers that that we want to make to
meet the requirements of the
code
final final draft
looks
likee brocc a peanut butter and jelly
sandwich is that because she heard you
say that is so sweet that's good
listens how many
years we're still we're still
so has everybody gone through this yes
okay any questions or concerns or
changes that you want to
suggest
me
okay so and this is just so we're
looking at the water right now
so um we have the water we have the
waste water and then we have the storm
water is all part of the
infrastructure policies
said new development shall be connected
to both the municipal water system and
the talent sewer system
need an anation policy that supports all
that ability to do
that
okay
um infrastructure you know it's kind of
interesting there's this kind of
perennial problem every year that people
face it has to do with the irrigation
water coming through town and the town
is only responsible for some of those
irrigation lines you know the ones that
go to the
park but um there's just so many leaking
lines and nobody knows where they are
and it's part of the
infrastructure but it's something that's
kind of all the the ditch companies have
no responsibility ability for anything
after it leaves the ditch it's all based
on users basically
but you know you hear so many people
saying that I've got this well there's
one that was on Delta Street and he was
sure that there was an irrigation line
leaking into
his does the irrigation lines the water
system through town have have any
bearing on there is it just too Loosey
Goosey that we we could never pin it
down because it was never formalized and
it's just such a mishmash of people's
personal
systems in right of way I've been down
this road and I lost miserably so um
ditch companies have a lot of leeway
with what they can and can't do there's
not a lot of can't there's a lot of can
do um in including using our existing
storm water infrastructure to convey the
irrigation water to their to their
customers and and you can't block that
but I've been told stepan like the St
ditch which I'm on and they say anything
after the after their ditch all those
lines that come down the hill that's all
our responsibility and they have nothing
to do with it they're only responsible
for their ditches we even had to repair
our gate when it broke the wheel broke
so so I would ask you did did they
confer with a water attorney like I did
and gave an opinion the opinion is we
can't stop them from using our existing
storm water system to convey to their
customers okay what about the
maintenance of private
systems um you know do people have to
keep things from leaking and because
underground water it's only water that
goes over the top that you can sue about
but you can't sue for
underground water basically if it it
enters your property your kind of so is
my my understanding about that okay so
infrastructure Waters irrigation is not
part of the
infrastructure issues okay and that's
part of why for the fifth and Grand
project we had to get rid of any
conflicts with the pay on your ditch and
um we have to eat that cost
as
okay
okay yeah once it once it leads the gate
from the ditch once it goes to the gate
it's up to the individual land owners
yeah the dis doesn't want anything to do
with us they say so it's not our
responsibility it's all individual
responsibility yeah and the whole water
law thing is like you can cross a
neighbor's property with your irrigation
if if that's what it takes to get to
your property okay I mean we have a
situation on Maine where an irrigation
companies
transmission line is literally running
to the center of our storm water pipe
and there's nothing I can do about it
wow
interesting
okay um anything railroad related that
we we don't have any perview over the
railroads they were here before the town
was incorporated so but I know
irrigation lines under there water lines
under the railroads nothing that we have
to worry about in our infrastructure
there
okay
okay okay great so we have the just to
gloss over only quickly we have this we
have the water policies we have the
storm water and then we have sewer in
infrastructure and then we also had put
the urban Forest into that and the
sanitation and resource
recovery um did we we talked about
encouraging of Rec cing at one point
here okay so these are just kind of
aspirational things in a way the Big
Dreams
okay
so does anybody have anything they want
to add here and um do we have to make
any motions on this to include it or
have decided or was this part of
the I think we needu for it because it
really was not um crafted this in depth
okay and one thing I want to make um we
should remember there's a placeholder
for a
figure on page figure six I think so and
Stefan has the ability to make that
figure which
is what
placeholder page is on page
84 and it's the
infrastructure and I think the
infrastructure is just a general looking
at step I'm trying to remember that was
one of the maps
required
by
Statute see
streets public
facilities I know all here we go General
location extent of Public Utilities
terminals T facilities and that is
another one of the requirements by
Statute and it has to have a
map um oh on your comments yeah yeah so
during the break I explained to
commissioner how that those maps are sth
coming
um they will be for your next
iteration but they're also part of the
future land use map it's just that it's
so busy what we would do is take those
turn on and off different layers and
then make new
maps I
on the page 99 under the urban Forest I
I think there's one thing that I I
thought was kind of missing here
um provides greater support and
accountability for Homeowner maintenance
of trees in the public
rways and engage and Empower citizens to
participate in Street Tree
Care um that was policy
one um maintain compliance Tre City USA
policy to and F work to Foster
collaboration between the tree board the
public the local business community
business Community to support tree
mainten and safety and I don't see
anything here about the town making any
kind of
commitment I mean it's you know the town
has the money for this and
um I think the town that's the pro
that's what's missing right now there's
not a lot of town
collaboration about the third
policy
um encourage updates to the inventory
every three
years policy urb policy infra Urban
Forest one actually gets it that um I'm
sorry policy infra Urban Forest 2 the
tree board is an extension of the Board
of Trustees they've been an appointed
codified board and so they're doing the
work that the Board of Trustees doesn't
have time to do or can't do or is
delegated away and in this case they've
delegated that to the tree board which
is an extension of the Board of
Trustees so I mean how are they involved
in tree maintenance and like the town
spending like coughing up money to to
help with tree care for instance so we
have a codified process for how the
board is interacts with not only the
town but also with
um uh trees on public lands um that's
that's actually in the P Municipal Code
already um I believe there are changes
proposed for that um coming from the
tree board um kind of how they interact
and some of the the things they're
working on that currently and they're
engaged um during the budget planning
process to make sure that their policy
infra Urban Force 3 is updated that
Colorado State for service inventory of
trees is updated and they've given us a
priority list of trees within the public
rights way that need to be addressed
immediately the the forest service
inventory um had that the okay
um okay I just remember seeing in Cammy
Long's um thing it's like hundreds of
thousands of dollars of work that we're
looking at here and I just don't see how
it's ever going to get done and I don't
see the vision here I just don't see the
vision
and I don't see I think um you
know maybe the tree Board needs to look
at the comprehensive plan too I mean
because if we're providing that big
Vision that overarching like the big
Vision I'm not seeing it happening right
now is what I'm saying um and so how can
we like kind of get that encouragement
going through the comprehensive plan yes
step so with all due respect even though
you may not see it happening I have
plenty of invoices that show that it is
happening currently um it's been
reported on in multiple meetings
throughout throughout this entire year
that we are doing things that as the
tree board has requested to you know
meet what's the the things that are in
policy in for urban Force 3 um with the
Colorado State Forest Service inventory
of trees so we are doing it we are
putting money to it this year alone I
think we budgeted for $20,000 they've
exhausted that um on what on tree
trimming as in public rights triing okay
so we we are meeting those you know what
is in that what is in that Force service
IND so how how do you find out more
about this how do you reach out how do
you how does it apply to individual
citizens how do we get on board because
it's kind of mysterious what do you I
don't know what you mean I I haven't
heard about any of this and I there's
trees in front of my house that could
use some care and um how do we how do
citizens I I just don't know it's like
this mysterious thing I I don't know how
do we find out more about this I
encourage you to go to a tree board
meeting when they're talking about the
priority list and ask them to prioritize
or take a look at the trees in front of
your house and then that way they can
set up in the priority list I it's kind
of in the in the tree Cammy I don't I'm
sorry it's wow
okay I don't have a lot of faith in that
that's all it's kind
of yeah
okay yeah I'd like to see a a bigger
statement there I mean it doesn't say
the tree board has a budget Tre board
never used to have a budget the tree
Board gets decide to use Town money is
that how you're
saying or is that or is that the town
board decides how to use the the town
board is the is the bu is they're the
persons right they're the ones that
create and adopt a budget they work with
various Sports and committees um to
adopt that budget or to to hear requests
and decide whether or not it's going to
go into the next specif bud I guess like
I guess what I want to say here is I I
want to hear the town wanting to spend
money on trees not the tree board you
know so I want a commitment to the trees
I want to see a commitment to the trees
in this town and that's going to have to
be a financial commitment and we do have
like tens of thousands if not more
dollars coming in every year for this
occupational pot tax I don't know how
long that's going to go on for by the
way I think it's sunsets that could be
spent on trees
and I just want to know how that the
accounting for that works and the tree
board are a bunch of people who don't
live in town making decisions for us and
I feel uncomfortable with that so I mean
it just seems so distanced and it would
be nice to see that there was just some
statement
that I don't know I have to think about
what that might sound like so it's not
like too specific but it it would kind
of uphold the spirit of what I'm
thinking about okay would it would it
help if you just added the words in
collaboration between the town tree
board public local businesses yeah
between the town the tree board the
public and local businesses yeah
I think that would be good to just put
the word town is there any problem doing
that it's redundant the town board is an
extension of the town the tree board is
an expansion to town I I think we should
put town in there as
well
um can you put Town tree
board sure and then that
way between the trustees the tree board
the public I think the trustees might be
a better word town is kind of a vague
Town board tree board well the trustees
are the to they do the town they are the
town I mean the town board the tree
they're the people who are elected in
yeah and they're the ones who have the
first string so why couldn't you just
say because they have
to they don't they do when yeah
when i' have to
they can't just do stuff they have to
ordinance the last time I heard about
budget is they wanted computer software
that's what I heard the you were talking
about that's because of that was free
that was free okay um so so you could
just say um and expand or I'm sorry
between between the town and its
appendant bodies that sounds good I like
that and and what was that again they're
appendant appendant bodies
to you might form another body in the
next 20 years so I think that would kind
of cover it oh God I hope
not does that does that satisfy yeah
that satisfies me so you'll make that
change too
sure okay well you never know what can
come come in the next 20 years so that
that is a little bit more inclusive I'd
say okay that's good thanks oh do we
have to make a motion or is that just
just a simple ring change okay well I'd
like to make a motion to change a
wording to
say the um collaboration between the
town
and as what how did you say it the town
and its appendant and it's appendant
bodies um public and local
businesses ready for was that
last didn't get
[Music]
it all those in uh discussion second you
second I second okay all those in favor
I
allos okay
great Okay so we've kind of gone through
the whole um
who seconded that motion page
P we didn't make motion to accept the
changes to the infastructure oh we
didn't do the infrastructure Chang yet
okay we overarching over okay someone
want to make a motion did you want
to I'll make a motion to accept the
infrastructure element with the previous
previously approved
changes didn't that
work I said previously approved changes
which we changes yeah just the previous
motions previously approved changes from
this meeting from this
meeting I don't know the
word have we have motion a second um any
more discussion on that okay all those
that
carries so we we I think that
was so um with that being said um do I
have a motion to
maybe table the rest until the next
meeting do you want to wait a whole
month or do we want to schedule another
meeting in the inim here um to okay
Paige I'd like to have another meeting
before our December 4th meeting def
whatever sorry I don't know December 4th
next the first Monday in December
because well wait a minute okay can we
talk can we just yeah about rules we
just talk because if we that could
conceivably if we could have
suspension of the rules requires a
motion second okay I make a motion that
we suspend the rules for an informal
discuss in in in place of informal
[Music]
discussion sorry
second ly ly
how okay
so I wanted to get out my calendar just
to
look so the next formal meeting would be
Monday December
second and on that point just F I won't
I won't be there be on of time
oh I'm out of town December 1 through
six wow okay um so will you be zooming
or anything okay so probably beeting
end of
November yeah I'm generally available
I'm just a toek so since it's winter
time I'm not gonna be traveling as much
and I think I'm probably a little bit
more open during the midweek so I'm
pretty open as I think at this
point whatever day 25th is after
Thanksgiving so that
may go mid week
to or 20th or 21st 2 27 28 28th
do you want to do on a Monday or do you
want to do on another day um Pete I
don't think he was totally satisfied
with the Mondays so on this you want
used to do Wednesday the best right
before how about the 20th is that right
after a board meeting is that difficult
that's not after board meetings on the
12th and the 26th oh yeah yeah okay what
about the
20th yeah okay and I'm wondering so then
we could talk about the housing
element and at that point would we be
close to having that agreed upon draft
that we then would get C Rose's help on
yeah let's talk about the land use map
too is that something that I'm a little
confused by that land future land use
map ask before we get off um just on the
scheduling so the 20th at 6 PM yeah
that's what we're doing
let's just make sure
Calendar's nothing El nothing else in
here are we can do Tuesday the 20th 19
[Music]
20 to be good
ones and it's not near a holiday to
where he wants to stand vacation time
for his kids
okay 20th is open for this
one oh you check the I'm checking the
calendar I was looking at my
[Music]
calendar and the reason I wanted to
think about this
is
um so to have the workshop
with uh the stri and underly revise that
would include everything that we have
approved up through the
20th that will take some time to get the
word out for that Workshop so we're
saying November 20th yeah that's a
Thursday right it's a
Wednesday oh I'm looking at
202 so ask that question again paig
please so mostly I was thinking on
timing for having the workshop with the
public to see everything that's changed
since June
21st
um and I just you know
maybe do we want to talk about having
that in
December and pick
up I mean December 2nd would you're gone
but I think that's
okay because we wouldn't be well no we
would have to make a would we may make
an emotion no we can't make a motion at
a
workshop to do what I'm talking about
the
cerose um Workshop she's gonna help us
with so the public is aware of all the
changes that were made since the June
21st what kind of motion would you do
just to make a meeting I I you can you
can schedule meetings on the internet in
fact so why can't you do it at a work
session no I usually the workshop you
don't make motions it's usually just a
workshop at least with work session a
work session doesn't normally have a
motion so what you could do is you have
a work session and and then a special
meeting and then during the special
meeting the only item of business is to
schedule your next meeting and then at
that next meeting we would because
potentially there could be changes that
we agree to make to that ver that people
see I'm just going to throw out the 11th
just for conversation if we had the um
work session on the 11th some people
come in they ask for some
changes do we have to have another
meeting to talk about incorporating
those
changes and then we would have our final
statutorily
required meeting to adopt the the plan
do you see what I'm saying
would we have to have another meeting to
show the changes made to the one that we
uh showcase during the work session
Workshop could we go into a special
s and have a meeting and do it right
then okay so I'm trying to follow a
lot the next meeting you guys you're
planning a schedule for 11:20 is that
correct right and that would be a
meeting similar to
yes where we go over the housing element
and other elements time for
this and that would be on the
agenda at that time you will have you
will know if the Board of Trustees has
approved or considered your
request and you can you know for cose
and Phoenix Rising resources and then
you can schedule um a path forward from
there and that's dependent on whether or
not the Board of Trustees gives the
direction as to what happens next so
let's say for sake of discussion that
that we have C Rose help us do a meeting
in December do a a workshop in
December the only thing I'm going to
caution you is my daughter I've got
three kids my daughter is uh Clara and
the Nutcracker and December 6th and 5th
and 7th are out for me throw the oh I
think
the was trying to clarify was that if at
the workshop there was comments from the
public that want to be taken into
consideration they need to schedule
another meeting to adopt those I believe
that would be a yes unless you're sure
that you're gonna have enough there to
have a meeting so the 11th should be the
11th December 11th has to be out and I
was thr it out we have a public meeting
for the C water cap Improvement plan
one and and so that that that kind of
takes precedence okay so um and I just
was throwing that out mostly I wanted
what Kaja was she was interpreting for
me which I appreciate so if we have a
meeting in December we have the uh
workshop and people want us to make
changes we will have to have another
meeting to decide whether we want to
adopt those
changes and let me ask another
question
um would we ask for written comments
from anybody at the
workshop or are we just going to take
verbal it just makes it difficult if
somebody says something verbal how do
you how do you address it
[Music]
veral that that's kind of
interesting it's kind of hard to plan
ahead could they write them ahead of
time and can we um and and consult only
asking is only helping publicize things
right well I don't know I think we have
to be open oh yes can I offer a
suggestion please so what we've done
with other
housing what we've done with the other
elements in the plan is once we've
talked about it we've set this time
frame from where we accept WR comments
so if we do the same thing if you're
saying on 11:20 you're uh going to talk
about the last few elements or we talk
about all five or four of the elements
we discuss tonight and say Hey you have
14 days from the 20th to get your
written comments to us so we're ready
for the next meeting that you guys plan
that could that could you know that
could take care of a lot of about
housing element that doesn't that
excludes all the out in that the
consultant would do to bring people to
us it was a suggestion yeah it might
have been a suggestion in addition to
public comments may you I accept written
in addition to what stated the workshop
perhaps reaching some of those
underserved folks who can't make it
maybe they're house B maybe they have
other commitments they have children in
place but they can still make their
voice heard um I think the suggestion
was additionally accepting written
comments but making that public at your
November meeting so that everybody knows
to get those in by whatever date you set
in December or later for a public
meeting or Workshop sorry well we we all
always accept written comments I mean
people could be commenting what we
talked about tonight but it helps to to
to have a set thing but but let me get
back to um so you can have absolutely
she's a good interpreter yeah I know I
know so on the meeting on the 20th we
want to talk as a group about the
remaining elements right so that is not
the time to ask people to make comments
because it won't be done okay so Kaja
you were then thinking at the December
meeting or in advertising for the
December meeting we let people know that
here is the content that we want you to
look at and we'll discuss please come
with verbal comments or submit written
comments before the workshop
I would make one comment working in the
office um specify how to submit written
comments because people come in very
very confused um just in your
advertising but is that is that the
right way to do it so we have adopted a
draft that we're going to publish with
kala's help for a workshop and while
that's in publication and people have an
opportunity to read it we're going to
ask them to submit comments either in
writing or be ready to give us comments
at the Workshop is that what everybody's
thinking yeah what the
workshop Workshop the workshop people
can speak ponia is is a funny place I
mean Roger came tonight but it takes a
long time for people to actually realize
what's going on you got to give them a
little bit of space
um holiday I I don't know Pages yeah
well so we have all the minor changes to
be made from the decisions tonight and
there'll be other changes after the
meeting on the 20th those changes can
probably be made if we can get to a
point where we uh are saying let's put
this draft out for public comment it
probably wouldn't take long to clean it
up and make it available to the public
but all the Outreach needs to be done
early enough in that time frame between
us meeting on the 20th and whenever
Workshop is scheduled for people to know
it's there to be read to give them time
to read it
right do we even can we do this in
December I mean are people going to want
to do this in December I just hate to
see this keep getting pushed back I mean
I think you can start it but you might
want to just make the time frames a
little bit more generous because of the
holidays and people are going you know
going to out of town maybe to visit
relatives you know I don't know what
people do can we do it J that's for me
it's feeling like the workshop would
have to be pushed in
January and so well if we could start
like it would be interesting to see how
much time that um they think it would be
good to get the word out there and start
advertising
and Publishing it places and you know
what I mean and taking that time to
really get it out there so people can
see see it be referring yeah yeah that's
why I think December is probably not
practical but
January be a time yeah January when the
doldrums start happening nobody has
anything better to do than to you know
and instead of being pushed in that of
entertainment the time the paper time
for the
publication what about the second week
in January the 8th or that week week of
the
in January yeah and that and that puts
about five weeks
out
okay
ohal um I think the week of January 6
is reasonable to shoot for budget stuff
you have to worry around that time DEC
that's
the remember what was that last year the
year before there was something in early
January there was nothing okay never
mind so what if we did the the six or
the eth to start doing the
workshop
right say that again I was just looking
so the six switches Monday and that's
our normal meeting date so that's
probably okay yeah unless we have some
hearings would you recommend having this
workshop on our normal meeting
date
should um I do
have one application that I need to
check with an applicant on when they
want
to do it I might recommend that they go
in
February okay what about the eight or
the 15th or something I mean I'd be
interested to what Pete has to
say New Year's Day well we don't have to
decide it now yeah we're just kind of
looking for yeah but but mostly I just
want to have this conversation
because we we don't have to decide it
yet in my opinion for January as long as
we're all good with going January for
the work by mid January
if I have to attend remotely I will but
I I
do the
end that
would I'd
[Music]
encourage that sounds terrible I want to
tell you we check the January calendar
for board meets anyway
so is it can
we okay can I make a motion that weour
can I do that do that have to be the
chair I'll make a motion have a second
yes all in favor I yes I
so you know M have that tree report
right identify issues of trees are going
down nothing
Happ well it's just right now
theard making sure Widow
makers likey said the dirt
back
Crown
the
learning learning Council has added soil
pile of soil on top of it and planted
flowers on top