e
e e
um I'll call the meeting to
order or the work session I don't know
how formal we are during
session
so we do roll call during the work
session just to I usually just have are
we doing
no um usually we just have everybody
announce themselves for the
record Suzanne Watson commissioner
Smith thank you does does anybody's
going to be here or not he sure he
wouldn't be he wouldn't
be
okay okay
um great so um the agenda tonight is
just um a work session on the draft
element of the um housing element and um
I was thinking um we could just use a
presentation on this um similar to the
presentations we've made on other
elements but this one's kind of big and
significant the the first thing I
thought would be helpful um is if we
could have I don't know if this is
conclusive but um States statute 3123
206 G and J are specific to the housing
element um Colorado State Statute and I
was going to try to bring it up on this
really fast but I don't know if there's
any bringing up really fast is that
something you could provide us with
Samira so we can um maybe look at it
when we're looking at the housing
element and
um kind of review it to see if we're
covering the needed the needed points in
that statute I need the S of you um 3123
206 um paragraph G and
J similar to what we did with the zoning
[Music]
elements specific requirements
there so do we go to Lex Nexus or is
that just um Stephan's actually screen
sharing right now so he's looking for it
okay oh
hello you may so um I open the meeting
we all announced our
if you'd like to announce your name Pete
for this work session it's a little less
formal than Peter McCarthy okay and I've
uh I've asked
for Colorado statute 3123
206 g& J or what I've seen referred to
specific to the housing element so we're
trying to bring that up so we have that
in
mind when we're going over the this por
of the
plan do you know how to um get by the
password thing even I just put a few
like numbers in or something I mean I
could do Cy but it doesn't like that as
far as has an ENT password on it oh yeah
that's just I put a temporary in here oh
I see that's so you can change that well
I did essentially the same just one row
down so one two three four thank you
and it might be hooked up to the office
next door so you might want to tell it
do you
know it
should yeah thank
you do you go to Lexus Nexus or do you
just type 312 I usually just type in our
browser I'm using
CRS okay and then something comes up
okay might take you to lus next is
for and um yeah the most current one I
have 206 J is in the table of
comments 206 J and it says plan needs an
element devoted to housing which include
projections of population growth and
housing needs to accommodate the growth
and there's there's G as well right I
don't have g g is not in the comment
table but J is but what's the comment
table that you're looking at the comment
table that Stefan put together and then
I oh you know added in changes I was
just looking at some of his emails and
that he said the housing element didn't
from the um from the housing plan didn't
address those parts of the statute and
that's why we had to rewrite things and
I just to make sure that we're
addressing the appropriate portion
thatat and I'm just saying that table
had all the comments and then I had
updated it for after the meeting you all
had in August with all the proposed
changes and agreed upon changes so um
and that was in the last agenda packet
just if anybody needs to look at it when
we had our fourth November fourth
meeting but I only inserted right here J
this is
2023 l.c.
could
change I have a yeah old cof
you know we probably had a
z whole thing about the comp plan it
might have been in there but I don't
think it it was the 2023 version
so
204 right
here G and
J so page
235 2 58 um of the 2023 revised statutes
on ledge.
colorado.gov is where I'm at I'm not
looking for it I'll Trust you okay
welcome are you to the book
huh yeah the it's not easy to get online
yeah welcome thank
you so it's on the that
side so G
in Middle there J is right under
it okay and it
refers number one
is well it's other things is is
that to General character location
extend of community centers housing
developments whether public or private
the existing proposed or projected
location of exist residential
neighborhoods sufficient land for future
Housing Development for consisting and
projected economic and another
needs so I think that was one of the
maps that was needed but I could be
wrong does that sound right Stefan it
does there were four maps that needed to
be created Created and then if and then
the regional plan agreement that can be
incorporated by
reference and so is that the 2010 one
that would be that intergovernmental
agreement between the town count okay
and we can refer to that we've seen that
um but it doesn't really say very much
about housing does
it future land sufficient land for
future Housing Development for existing
projecting econom needs that's been
covered with the FL future land map and
the future Landing so and the
projections of population growth and
housing needs to accommodate the
projected population for spe specified
increments of time the municipality May
base these projections upon data from
the Department of local Affairs and upon
the municipality's local
objectives so how is that well so anyway
I just wanted this in front of us so are
these the only two elements that deal
with housing in the in in the state
statute
is I I saw a reference to that but I'm
not sure if that's
been
um um
G yeah and I mean there's the zoning
kind of but it's a little different we
address
that
yeah
okay okay now there's a placeholder
called Figure Four under future land use
plan for the public places and
Facilities map I think
is uh this is maybe not
there's there four maps
that it's funny it doesn't I mean
obviously that's the easiest way to
maybe
um Express this so I don't know if there
the written element should refer to the
math at all or what or anyway okay I
wanted to start with that as a as a kind
of starting for the
housing that um
other question I had just right off the
top was I someone was telling me there's
some discussion on Facebook the town has
been making some comments about the
master plan is that true and if so um of
course now with the computer I suppose I
can look but I'm wondering if we can all
be on the same page with that if there
have been comments made so we know
what's going on with explanations but I
don't know I haven't seen it for myself
I just heard someone telling me
something about Facebook I don't know
how many Facebook people
[Music]
you the last meeting
on no no there was a made today oh
okay e
oh I can't read that um my eyes aren't
good enough to see that
um
okay was it on town of
Pia Facebook of
spell that wrong got a place in
Hawaii
okay
um is it under news or well here we go
here's the so it's on the town of Pia
Facebook site okay that's
correct
that oh so um the housing element is up
for the for discussion during this
evening's Planning Commission meeting is
that that's what you've written we hope
to hear from you and your your thoughts
On's draft element can you read that you
can read the element here there's a link
to the town's site with element
um so it
has starts with a printed introduction
to the element it looks
like
and and that that's
it what's
that read further down the last two
paragraphs are address oh despite a
misleading post on the message boards
policy housing 14 States the town shall
discourage Fe development and demolition
practices and so we're talk it's
discussing some of the elements in the
thing the displac and the displacement
of very low low and moderate income res
special needs households this means that
the town will discourage someone from
buying two homes next to each other
demolish them and then build a very
large Mansion type house these policies
are meant to protect our small Val town
and that's that looks like that's it
right okay so there's a post that was
made
okay okay so we have this plan I guess
everybody's had a chance to look it over
and I'm just kind of wondering if we
could maybe have a little bit of
explanation the thought process that's
that went into it I wasn't
sure I mean before we start commenting
it about it and how it kind of ties back
to
the to the
statute um because apparently the
housing needs assessment and action plan
didn't address the statute and that's
why we need needed this housing element
in the um in the comprehensive
plan so I I'm not sure I agree with that
statement necessarily because the point
the housing needs assessment action plan
is a much larger document with lots and
lots of um statistics and things whereas
the comprehensive plan is place that
anyone wanting to do some kind of
development would go to look and see
succinctly what the goals and policies
are that the town's following which are
based on the housing needs assessment
but if you've read the housing need
assessment action plan there's a lot in
there that is not that helpful for
seeing what the town's
overarching um planning goals are okay I
was just looking at these emails this
email back and forth and I saw an
explanation that we knew this housing
element because um it didn't address the
elements in CRS 3123 T6 g&j which is
specific to comprehensive plans and the
housing needs
assessment um and the action plan in
this in its existing state doesn't meet
the requirements of CRS 3123 206 g&j and
that was from Stefan so I guess I just
want to
know M well what yeah but that's okay I
guess I'm just kind of confused because
I thought it referred to anyway okay
so let's
start probably the one thing that I
would say is not in the housing element
is what's it required of J which is a
population
estimate projections of population go
growth and housing needs which probably
is in the housing needs assessment and I
think that statement from there could be
extracted into the intro of the housing
needs assessment just my R reading
okay any more comments or questions or
any more presentation about this the
thought process that one behind it can I
just have one more thing um right now
the comprehensive plan is not
referencing that I Le I don't think it
is I could be wrong but the housing
action housing assessment action plan
should be a document that is referenced
by this so that people know to go look
at it not at one point it was somewhere
it's not in this but it was in the it
might have been compehensive plan
somewhere yeah I'm not sure it's
actually listed at the end or in the I
think it's mentioned in the beginning
that's where the reference is used I
think it's there but I think it probably
needs to be brought down into the
appendix which list specifically the
documents used and maybe un links you
know this is all electronic be links all
those me if I'm wrong but I think that's
the case what's that it's listed as a
document used for referencing for the
creation of the comprehensive plan what
which docum the housing needs assessment
and action plan correct so those are two
separate documents the housing needs
assessment and the housing action but my
point is I think they're referenced in
the beginning as some of the major
references but we didn't put them in the
IND and and I think once this is
approved it'd be nice to have electronic
links toow those documents so I think
that might be just one of the pieces
that's missing so page
68 needs assessment on page
30 30 of the agenda package no just yes
s this agenda
pack what was page 30 I'm
sorry what was that again L did you
mention what 30 and 68
page
68 yeah 68 of the packet talks about
yeah the housing and neighborhoods
element is informed by both the 2023
housing need assessment and the 2023
hous I was referring to a list that's in
kind of the beginning of the
introduction which gives the main
document
anyway it's in there it just needs to
be okay so my question is is the housing
needs assessment and action plan is kind
of a massive document so how does this
housing
portion adequately and equally cover all
the points and kind of crystallize
points is what I want to know to make to
make it easier maybe to grasp and
understand
um you know I I guess I want to know
what points in the action plan I mean
was the action plan for us or is the
action plan for the Board of
Trustees and how does our comprehensive
plan um kind
of address those elements and maybe make
it a little bit more
um I guess it's it's kind of where
what's the framework in there that we're
kind of pointing this to I mean spring
boarding from so I guess I want to know
what are the elements that were being
looked at um so I know that we are
saying that was informed but I want to
know how was it informed I mean what
specifically I mean that's a pretty
broad statement because it's a big
document it's it's binder I didn't bring
I mean it's a big document
so um that's my my
question I was having a hard time it's
like drinking from a fire hose and I was
hoping this would be a little bit
more um know maybe a synopsis of it in
some way that kind of get my mind around
it I kind of think the introduction is a
synopsis
introduction is new documents that we're
talking about and I'm uncomfortable with
those I think those are just references
not the documents were used just how
neighborhoods are created and the the uh
okay benefits of neighborhoods okay well
so I didn't really want to work on this
I wanted to hear that um the thoughts
behind it because I look at this and I
could take half of these words out I'm
not comfortable with them I think
there's too much here and until someone
can explain to me why it's here maybe I
can it can inform my um understanding of
this a little bit
better
um this Congress for the new urbanism it
doesn't fit in
ponia it it shouldn't be this is too
much for
us um principles of good neighborhood
design
that's why everybody's moved here Pion
is a great place as is and when I look
at this I think of the synthetic
neighborhoods and developments that I
saw in Edwards this summer you know the
River
Walk The
Village I feel really uncomfortable with
that it's a synthetic trying to kind of
Infuse that small town Feeling Again
into these places that have lost it but
I see this this is why ponia is such an
awesome place is because we have this
and I don't think we need to inject this
kind of synthetic stuff that I think
really appeals to developers this is
anyway so I didn't want to make this a
session where I started bringing up my
concerns because I wanted to
hear you know more about the thought
processes that went into this is the you
know one of the bigger parts of the plan
and there's just
I don't know when we did the zoning plan
we really talked about what we put in
why we were trying to put things into it
we cut some stuff out because it didn't
refer to what was in the statute and we
actually
repe rep so there I see things that are
conflicting in here and I see things
that are kind of repetitive in here like
that whole thing
about well what the Facebook was saying
something
about not demolishing things but then I
see things about demolition in here so
it seems like there's like
conflicting points in it and I don't
know what you and so what I've seen
happen in this town is when you don't
have clear directions and you can see it
this way or you can see it this way it's
too open
to um it's too open to uh um you know
can you can always find the answer to
support what you currently want to do so
there's kind of no point in having it
because it's too complaining but
anyway yes Peter are you able to buy two
lots and demolish the houses and build a
make a Manion on M mansion on based on
our current
zoning probably could you could I mean
just F property rights right I mean what
I'm asking is is that a policy that is a
change no I don't think there's any
policy that we've ever had that I don't
see where there's a policy in here that
speaks you can't do that either I was
that was kind of interesting to read has
anyone ever done that I don't know i' my
I'm on four Lots I have a neighbor on
six lots and a neighbor on five
Lots um I know you can subdivide them
but I suppose you could
also um I mean there's a new house that
went on up there on first and I don't
know how many Lots they were
on but that on First and Doris
but just that's one lot one Big Lot okay
and I own two two properties right next
to each other and I don't know if I
could demolish all the buildings on both
properties and and ask to turn it into
six
slots I don't know if I can sh cuz I
have I have two properties each have
three
lots um can I I'm asking if the code
allows me to turn it into a six
lot property but that's not what we're
talking about right we're talking about
taking two separate Lots demolishing the
houses and building one house which is
what I could do yeah that's what I'm
wonder I'm asking I I conceivably I own
I literally own two properties right
next to each other and each have three
there three lots on each one you and
that's what I'm asking is if since I own
them both could I come in and say I want
to build a house with the proper
setbacks and everything else but I want
it to be 5,000 sare ft across the
property line I don't know if that's
possible but I do have two three lots
that I could easily put a much much
bigger house on than what's there now so
and as long as I met the set packs I
guess I would be okay in the AR one so
well I know well we didn't yeah anyway I
can think of an example it's not quite
to say but anyway I don't see where this
addresses that I mean this doesn't
say what what policy in here actually
addresses that to we're going all over
the place I know I was just can I can I
address a couple things first yeah so
first
we have an existing comprehensive plan
and our comprehensive plan is from
1996 this comprehensive plan is woful
lacking should have been updated 20
years ago it
wasn't um and so that I think that's why
we're here right we've we've got a
comprehensive plan that really should
have been addressed 20 years ago we've
tried three times since this
comprehensive plan draft to get a new
comprehensive plan in place and have
failed we're at the finish line we're
trying to talk about some things to add
elements to to talk about editing
elements before we're ready to present
present a final draft that we're going
to ask Phoenix Rising resources to do
that public Outreach for
us I'm not sure if you have looked at
our current comprehensive plan and
reviewed what is in there but it it it
is lacking and if somebody were and you
know you you want to talk about com Bing
and de demolishing a house and building
something larger right now there's
nothing in our existing comprehensive
plan to discourage that from happening
and so again our comprehensive plan is a
guiding document it's guiding us on what
we want to be in the future and if
having that kind of language in there is
saying we're not okay with being like
Roaring Fork where you can come in and
build a what some have called a
mcmansion right you take a bunch of
downtown Lots build a big house over
those lots and now you've got a
condominium right what we're there's
nothing that's protecting us from that
that's why that policy is in the new
draft
but we haven't gone over this draft yet
right we've it's been on an agenda a few
times we've never had a chance to get
there I think it's pretty important that
we start going over it
um if you all are with going over it I'm
happy to do
that it's only nine
pages I do see that in u the housing uh
13 or 14 and
15 that's
address so what so what you're talking
about I'll read it out for the public um
14 says the town shall discourage
Redevelopment and demolition practices
that significantly reduce existing
housing stock in older neighborhoods and
that result in the displacement of very
low low and moderate income residents
for special needs
households and then policy 15 says the
town shall monitor all Redevelopment and
demolition activity to ensure that
comparable relocation housing is
available in accordance with the Federal
Regulations regardless of whether
Federal monies are used in the activity
and the town shall ensure that all
adopted and proposed regulations
maintain and encourage diversity and
housing types that will support adequate
relocation housing as
required and I think it's important to
know how to read the document so those
policies are what support the goal and
that goal for housing three is to commit
to inclusivity by ensuring A diversity
of housing options that meet the needs
of residents including those for seniors
and residents with special needs if you
go to the housing needs assessment and
action plan it talks about diversity of
Housing and being inclusive and so this
is a this is a goal that was made based
on what was in the h& and the housing
action plan and then policies to help
support them um jumping around I don't
think is going to be really good for any
productive conversation can we start at
the beginning of this housing element
well that's what I'm not starting at it
I I didn't write it and I don't
understand it so I did start at the
beginning and then everything kind of
went dead so do you want to start at the
beginning sure and so I I think it's
really important because there's you
know people see that word urbanism or
new urbanism and and you know there's
there's this kind of I don't know a fear
about that word and I think if you've
read the charter for the new urbanism
you'll understand that this is about
stopping urban sprawl so stopping and
I've heard you commissioner chair chair
Watson talk about Urban spraw and saying
that's not good for anyone it's not good
for this County and and to bring it you
know into more of a a town and
neighborhood so I think it's important
to say we stand for the so this is the
Congress new urbanism's Charter was
updated in summer of 24 we stand for the
restoration of existing Urban centers
and towns within coherent Metropolitan
regions the reconfiguration of sprawling
suburbs into communities of real
neighbor hoods and diverse districts the
conservation of natural elements and the
preservation of our built Legacy I I
think that captures ponia pretty well
and i' I've heard that in in public
Outreach sessions that we've had
Community discussions that we've had
there is this there is this deep desire
for for conserving our natural
environment and so I think that that we
stand for kind of encapsulates
that does you have a comment on it yeah
actually I do um so so you know
I I've been thinking about this how many
how many square miles is p on you four
square
miles it's under that it's under that
Acres how many it's four acres 100 acres
so not a section not but it's not very
big right the section 640 acres so how
do we spr in this little town and when I
go like on my walk up onto lambor Mesa
what I see is a lot of sprawl and it's
not in town it's in the county and I see
people coming here with their money and
everybody wants to have that 5 acre
ranchette that 20 acre ranchette and we
sell in the water tap we do not selling
water caps now because we have a
moratorium but that's where the sprawl
is happening that's where people need to
use cars all over the place that's where
you get non-w walkable communities it's
not in the town of ponia so that's why I
kind of don't think this applies can I
address that really quick so we actually
have an ordinance that says you will get
into a pre-annexation agreement for
building a new home and so this is
codified if you're outside of the count
outside of town limits you have a
pre-annexation agreement that says if
you want water you're going to build
your home to town standards which means
you're going to follow our comprehensive
plan you're going to follow any of our
planning ordinances zoning ordinances
land use ordinances and you're going to
get a building permit from the town
and I can't tell you if it's been
enforced prior to me I can tell you I'm
enforcing so it's it's an actual code in
our it's an actual ordinance in our code
that we have to follow the point of this
comprehensive plan is to also look at a
threemile jurisdiction right that's in
that same statute that we've been
referencing all night long and multiple
times within that three mile
jurisdiction there
is we're supposed to have some sort of
control or say over what happens within
that within that growth management area
that the county has to also approve and
so that's the point of this
comprehensive plan right it adds it adds
uh guidance for what happens to stop
that urb roll it it provides guidance to
the county that that hey we have
something in place that needs to be
followed and it directs people on what
is and isn't
acceptable so my understanding um with
that building permit thing and I don't
know have any building permits been
folded since you've been here for out of
town it's also any development on the
property right if they're on the town
water if they're they're directly build
by the town if they're on a water
company that it doesn't apply corre I
understand so one and that's the thing
is there's and then so when we're
talking about like even and there's no
building permit process in the county so
there's no way to even monitor
development that's going in on the on
the water system through water companies
and I mean I still say will maintain
that's where the spraw is happening not
we just we just recently had somebody
that purchased a property that has
underne that deed restriction it says
enter into a pre-annexation agreement
with the town of p and that that
pre-annexation agreement was in in in
place that property sold and now they
have to go through our processes to
build that property or build on that
property in order to get connected to
water I I just REM remember the Oldtown
manager's house well of course he was on
a water company but he's in the growth
area out there toward the Stop and Save
and it was less than a year ago well it
was about a year ago they were doing a
heavy remodel in that place and they
never pulled any building permits and
that was even in the growth area it was
very visible so
um I don't know it's expensive when you
start like like deciding to adopt these
kind of new policies and with Energy
Efficiency and it's just going to drive
the cost of things up but why don't you
move forward with this I I'll give you a
chance to I don't want to do back and
forth because it'll take forever here
steping so um just give you a chance to
present it and then you know we can
revisit I just want you ask I'm sorry
um let me just unpack a few things
here we published a final draft of the
master flan in June it did not have all
the legal elements that it needed to
have were you aware of that when we
published it yes after I read through
the statutes but Pete you're going back
on all history but let me just tell you
this was the RFP that went out I'm just
asking so so the answer was yes I didn't
know it until I looked at the statutes
were you with because the RFP were you
were you were
when were you aware that that that
Master Plan was going to have elements
missing I don't recall if this is going
to turn into this I'm gonna go home I'm
sorry because I've had these meetings
multiple times it's a simple question
well I don't think it's Reon it is the
RFP that went out was wholly inadequate
because when it went out in 1920 in
20122 nobody knew what a master plan
should have including our administrator
at the time that's why
we have had to do a lot of ketchup
because at some point at some point we
we were aware well the public
knew I'm sorry there is a big so so so
what's the relevance here the relevance
is we we we told the town that we had a
final draft from the consultant well did
did was that is that clear to the town I
don't know but the consultant wasn't
aware of the pie that had be
finish sorry this is work session so
it's a little bit more informal but I
don't want to I mean just that
interaction right there I I feel very
attacked just when I'm bringing up my
concerns so I don't need to bring up any
concerns we can we can if if bringing up
concerns is going to elicit a walk out
and a threat or a characterization of me
looking back then I can stop would you
like me to stop well I'm trying to
answer your question no you're actually
trying to stop me from bringing up my
concerns well
your concerns
are you know what if pieces were missing
which they were yes because the RFP was
not complete okay the Town takes
responsibility for that but that doesn't
mean that the work stopped at what RFP
asked for and then the other things were
so we turned in an incomplete master
plan published it to the T saying that
this was a final draft you're saying
you're say I get it there there's an
ambiguity there like right but could you
would you at least admit that the town
might have viewed that as as a m as a
absolutely not I was in that meeting no
okay no Pete absolutely
not
okay I mean this is the schedule this is
this this is what we've done what's on
our screen right now is what has been
done for this entire comprehensive plan
is going all the way back to the First
Community engagement session that
Phoenix Rising had on April 27th 2023
and then everything that happened since
then so if you're going to ask if when
did I know that there was an element
that was missing or elements that were
missing I would say probably June 24
21st when it was submitted to staff and
then if you if right after that the next
month in July 18th there was a joint
Board of Trustees and Planning
Commission meeting to present a plan and
determinate determine a process and
adoption for that you know to adopt that
plan by August 2nd there were comments
that were made we we got comments back
from everybody we started discussing
that final draft in August 5th
if I mean you can see all of this stuff
so so sry yeah no no I mean it's it's
all right here okay yes I I I think I
totally agree with what's on here I I
don't think any of this addresses my
concerns at all
so my my concern is that we we now have
two two of the most important elements
of the comprehensive plan we missing
from the final gr we hired a Consulting
Group they did all this work to get
community feedback and then they but but
as part of that for whatever reason
because we our he was incorrect because
the Town Administrator at the time and
obviously up until June 24th didn't
realize that that that those were
missing from from the the comprehensive
plan we are at a a place where I'm at a
place where I think that the
comprehensive plan except for these two
elements is is reflects the input from
the community I do not think that the
the housing element reflects the input
from the community I've made that clear
I asked on September well it's been
about two months now so so it was the
board
directed the board directed The at some
point the board said and the Planning
Commission the board and the Planning
Commission directed The the stepan to
write the house to incorporate to
incorporate the housing element or sorry
the the housing action plan into the
housing Element no no it was to create
housing element the word the word
incorporate it wasn't incorporate the
housing to accept the housing that that
was in
2023 yeah so what and then after that
the Planning Commission had nothing to
do with it so the housing was not
supposed to be an incorporation of the
Housing Act
the housing action plan and needs
assessment is too big a document to just
be shoved into the comprehensive plan it
need be distilled and in the May meeting
The Joint meeting you were not in
attendance to the Planning Commission
and the trustees both both said asked
Stefan to create the housing element
that we're reviewing now based on the
housing
investment may this was a May decision
made by The Joint planing commission and
the trustees I must not
no was the it was UN for that I'm just
wasn't our meeting canceled no it
doesn't please listen this is what
happened the the motion was made by both
bodies to ask the administrator to
create the housing element based on the
housing need assessment and action plan
and I have to tell you that was in
September no it was in May it was
we're sorry sorry about that September
it was in September I'm sorry sorry but
it was done and we now have a really
good element so so so so now we're in
agreement so it it was but it it was we
disagree is and I'm I have looked at the
language it was to incorporate now and
I'm not saying that that means not to
distill or that it needed to be the
whole thing but it was to incorporate
the housing action plan into the housing
here is the motion the motion carry uh
trusty Hunter makes a motion uh seconded
by trusty stelter to ask Town
Administrator when to have the draft
order element so that was that one
carried you animous right underneath
that it says commissioner how makes a
motion seced by commissioner Hunter to
ask the Board of Trustees to ask Town
Administrator when to come up with
objectives goals and policies for the
housing of the master plan the motion
carried unanimously trusty ster makes a
motion seconded by Hunter to direct Town
Administrator windome objectives goals
and policies for the housing the mass
plan motion carried
okay so but but is it not there's
there's never been language that we were
going to incorporate the housing action
plan into the housing element oh I was
it was done in 23 there was a motion
well I think the board at that time
thought I think that was their thinking
was the housing action plan was going to
be all this housing stuff so the
contractor with a comprehensive plan
didn't have to worry about that that's
that's the sense I got is being an
audience member a member of the public I
don't know how wise that
was the contractor they were informed to
work with Shay who would be contract for
the housing needs
assessment but that she would be
conducting the housing element at which
point when both documents were complete
so we were not instructed to create that
element we were specifically instructed
not to create that element because it
would be created from out of the process
okay when our when this process was
completed there was to be a process of
incorporation some of the findings from
that cson needs assessment did go into
the draft that we submitted but not as a
separate element they were incorporated
into other aspects of the plan I just
want to ask what was the other element
that you felt was missing was it the
infrastructure
element um was it what are
infrastructure elment in that plan which
included water and then we were directed
in different times to pull trees in or
out of that or sidewalks and Roads as
separate or Incorporated you're talking
about the statute g&j is that what you
mean what's missing I just had heard
that two elements were missing so I was
just trying to clarify one the housing
element we were told explicitly not to
because the sneeze assessment would be
brought in in the end and incorporated
into it yeah you told not to who told
you was was it the Planning Commission
that so during the course of our
contract we had several different points
of contact because at one point the
Planning Commission wasn't meeting
anymore regularly and so at that point
we took direction from either the board
and or the mayor and the administrator
so there was a point where we started
with the Planning Commission they
stopped meeting I'm not sure what
happened it was inconsistent and then at
some point we went back to direction
from the town there was a change
Administration we ended up with the
elements that were there including
infrastructure which did include water
streets trees
sewer and sidewalks and then there's the
parks and uh element of it as well how
those elements got broken out into
infrastructure or not were rearranged
several times um but all of those pieces
were in the draft that we it and we were
aware that it did not have the housing
piece but again some of those findings
were in incorporated into the broader
aspects specifically around the land use
recommendations or type of areas like in
town where we would have a historic core
or where we would have you know um more
light industrial um and those
definitions were informed by that
housing Bo
assessment and if I make so chair if I
may we're in a work session okay I
that's right rules are suspended so um
what Phoenix Rising put together Phoenix
Rising research put together was um an
infrastructure section that ended up in
the appendices and you had like water
each individual part in the appendices
and what was created was based off of
their work was this infrastructure
element um everything in this document
that's in red was is added and it's more
given it's more added for historical
context where we are at um what got us
to where we are with our water
moratorium things like that I just want
to um clarify expand on what he's saying
is that originally that had all been in
the original document and then we were
directed to take it out and put it in
appendicies where that information was
significantly cut down if you want I can
give you the 34-page version of the
water element alone we still have that
version but there was a lot of like back
and forth as to what was wanted to be
included where so just to expand on what
Stephan is saying about where in
dependes and correct and and so um what
you're looking at now is goals for the
infrastructure element so these were
things that we've already talked about
guys have already approved them to go
into this final draft that that's been
that's done um but they were we turned
them into goals and then policies so
there's a general infrastructure section
you know that talks about um you know
good policies like coordinate
infrastructure repairs and upgrades cost
utilities and other property maintenance
needs needs that's that dig want policy
right if you're going to tear up the
street might as well do the water pipes
underneath it that's that's what that
policy says um then water so anything
not in red is original water
element and again if you ever want to
see we did a
whole much larger discussion and summary
because one of the initial things in the
initial RFP that was not really geared
towards a real comprehensive plan was a
summary if you want a summary of
everything we found in the like hundreds
of pages of water documents which I'm
sure you've also read at this point I'm
happy to provide you that summary that's
the thing that's like 34 pages and like
here's what recommended next steps are
because in our initial RP it said tell
us recommended next steps based on all
of these papers and it named them all so
that original section had all of that
stuff and that has all come out is not
in here except for in terms of how the
policies are guiding management which a
lot of those management best practices
were derived from those initial mostly
the large engineering reports on the
system and and so to to be really clear
you were instructed um with that
original RFP to have a condensed
comprehensive plan and and and make it
as as small as possible um which doesn't
really didn't really accomplish what we
had to do so yeah and I think you know
we were originally guided to a statute
in Colorado that says a comprehensive
plan only has to include like a
recreation and tourism element and not
the expanded version where it talks
about all the other elements about what
should be in a plan I also consulted
with several different planners of
reading the RFP they said this does not
look like a traditional comprehensive
plan when administrator when came on
board and made it clear that he wanted a
traditional conservation plan we went
out and hired Shake Coburn um of urban
rural Continuum who has a planning
degree and does this for work so we
could create a legally Like official
document that would fulfill the needs of
the town from a comp plan standpoint
however that was very challenging for me
because we had just done a Year's worth
of work on something that was mostly a
summary exercise un reccommended next
steps for based on the large amount of
um data and then also if you haven't
seen it we did share the full data room
or Google folder that had all of the
files we were instructive to review in
that process so it it has been a messy
iterative process and that's I'm happy
to answer any questions you have about
that or see any versions of
it when you came up with different
elements did you provide citations of
community feedback explanations of what
those policies would be things like that
um I'm not quite sure about how to
answer that question so we do
site there was a version where we had
cited all of the official documents like
CX document on X page for this thing on
the water or sewer um and then there we
also heads sited uh Community feedback
and then we provided all of the notes
from those sections in the data that we
gave the town so we'd say like this you
know and was every single thing in there
cited directly back to those things no
but in if you look at a comp plan that's
not traditional practice it's not like
an academic paper where it's like you
know so and so so and so this year
so you know again originally when we had
been directed to do a summary we were a
lot more thorough in citations as it
evolved we did defend each of the
policies are linked to community input
and or large documents that the town had
provided Ed as background and then best
practices in the planning community so
again I'm happy to answer like specific
questions on that
um my my questions aren't really for any
of the I do think that provided
background for all the policies you
wrote the reason we're the reason the
thing that I am stuck on as everyone
here knows is in September when the new
housing element was written the goals of
the new housing element are absolutely
derived directly from the housing action
plan the 28 policies are not they're
they they are of
course linked to the goals but they're
there are they are as Stefan wrote back
in an email derived from his experience
of writing comprehensive plans and where
we are at a logger head is that I asked
for an explanation citations Community
input for all those things I have been
given none of that in fact the first
explanation I've been given for any
policy was something I had to read today
off Facebook so even though I've asked
for that in writing many times going
back two months even though I asked for
a vote to then direct because I was told
I wouldn't be get getting those I asked
the the rest of the Planning Commission
to vote to direct Stephan to get give an
explanation not to incorporate those
things into the housing element but to
just give an
explanation I've been given no
explanation so given no explanation of
these housing
policies at the last meeting no we was
on the agenda so I've been trying to get
this to make this discussion happen in a
public public setting and you weren't at
the last meeting and so here I am today
at this meeting ready to go over it and
instead we're we're doing this we didn't
talk about it at the last meeting
because that agenda was way too big well
you you said that you didn't want to get
into it because Pete was exactly but it
was also too late that when you can't
clog our agenda that way I didn't ask
for that to be put on the
agenda I I I I sent first first of all
first of all I did not fail to attend
the last meeting as you put in your
email the last meeting was set only 16
days in advance we have not had regular
meetings on this commission for months
now I've
asked I've been asking to have regular
meetings we do not have I I look across
Colorado if there's first first and
third Thursday of every month Planning
Commission has a meeting our meetings
are all over the place so it is not my
fault that I can't attend meetings that
only get set six this is this meeting
itself was only the last two meetings
were only set 16 days ahead of time so
because of that I I took the time to
write out very detailed questions that I
sent to you five hours before the
meeting I've been asking the same thing
for two months which is a written
explanation these these policies some of
them may be good some of them might be I
asked this before mayor you said that
these are just you you cited one of them
and said this is just common sense I
don't think when it comes to most these
things that they common sense I think
that there are many many policies that
appear to be Common Sense on the surface
and when you dig down into the details
they are not that's why I would like to
have some elaboration on what these
policies are and I have been denied that
so I would like to add that I have no
problem with any of the goals or
policies in the housing element I've
looked at them several times I've read
the housing needs assessment action plan
I like the whole content so I think
rather than you decide that there are
things you don't like you have already
identified I think two three four five
six seven policies you don't like which
is really constructive why don't we look
at those policies and you can explain
what you don't like about them but I am
not going to vote to go through every
piece of this because they are common
sense and they do come from housing
needs assessment
and the community input for the
construction of the
plan if they came from the housing needs
assessment the housing policies then it
would be easy to cite them they're not
re they're not at all B all
what thing perhaps we should read them
and go over yes let's do that rather
than go back and forth is that
acceptable to everyone if we read them
and us so we're going through your work
tonight right that's what you're going
through you say read them and go over
what what is them the housing out okay
yeah that's what that's what I thought
we were going to do so I was a little
surprised by the silence at the
beginning of this meeting I was I
thought it was a chance for you to kind
of you're the one who wrote it St and so
like all these other portions that we've
written I saw this when we agreed to let
you write it as a springboard to kind of
start greasing the wheels and it could
be amended it's not like the final draft
just
absolutely right and that's if I may
what what I heard though was you asked
for that right off the bat and there was
silence but then at the point when
Stephan said can I go through this and
he started going through it then
commissioner McCarthy had a question and
we ended up talking about this so I I
think through it yeah administrator is
trying to go through this actually he as
Stephan asked if I had a a
comment but I believe that was because
you were raising your hand okay
we're gonna get sided here we should
just go through it okay if I so the
introduction section is explaining
exactly what this what these goals and
policies are attempting to achieve um
you know this these great neighborhoods
things this comes from u a University of
Notre Dame study on what makes great
great neighborhoods uh in so it's
identity shaped by its physical settings
streets architecture history and
residence can read through all of
[Music]
those but I I think the real meat and
potatoes here that that there's there's
questions on goals and
policies um this Vision in and these
values I don't I haven't heard anybody
say anything negative or have any
questions about the visions and values
so I'll just go into goals goal number
one maintain pay poning as a community
that is accessible to a range of income
levels ages and households by ensuring
adequate and affordable housing options
are available we did a housing needs
assessment housing action plan talked
about affordable housing goal number two
um or housing number two enhance and
maintain the character of P's existing
residential neighborhoods balance the
need to accommodate INF field
development um Stephan I'm I'm sorry to
interrupt but um so going back to
housing one how would the town do that
what are you what are you thinking when
you say um um how by ensuring how does
the town ensure adequate and affordable
housing options are avilable so that's
what the policies underneath the housing
goal I'll that I'll just go back to that
when you get to the policies is it the
case that the goals are derived directly
from the house F correct corre I I mean
like almost for not verbatim
um because so the housing action plan
housing needs assessment was really done
to help us achieve prop 123 so that's we
opted into proposition 123 that's to be
Avail to to be able to get State funding
for um meeting affordable housing goals
and I think we had to meet five five a
year for four years five new homes that
are affordable in four years to be able
to to do that but as part of that you
had to finish this housing needs
assessment and then have an action plan
and so that's that was really meant to
be prop 123 and so we've taken what was
done through that 170 page document and
try to distill it down into these goals
so kind of yes but it's not
verbatim um commit to inclusivity by
ensuring A diversity of housing options
that meet the needs of residents
including those for seniors and
residents with special needs we we do
have a special needs population here
that that are independent people that
live on their own um housing goal number
four preserve views to the mountains
natural amenities and SC from from the
public ground so I mean that's that's
what I've heard in some of our public
Outreach meetings is we we love it here
because it's beautiful right so you're
trying to prot protect that Senor V
housing five identify recognize and
protect payon is unique and
irreplaceable history and cultural
parage that should be cultural not
cultural
marage yeah housing six preserve protect
and stabilize the character and
visibility of residential neighborhoods
particularly within areas with natural
hazards such as flood plane and steep
slope conditions or require demolition
when Rehabilitation is not possible nor
economically feasible such as in areas
where a significant concentration of
substandard housing exists that
contributes to negative neighborhood or
environmental conditions that's them of
flood maps so if you're going to build a
house that's or your house gets wiped
Away by a flood and you want to rebuild
that house or try to rehab that house in
a flood zone you're going to have to
follow FEMA guidelines for for building
that house housing seven encourage
building and construction strategies
methods and practices that promote
Energy Efficiency through low impact
design principles including the use of
renewable energy resources and the
construction of new homes and the
rehabilitation of existing homes so the
state is promoting this Energy
Efficiency thing with new homes and and
and remodeling homes it's also promoting
like straw bail construction so
different types of construction that
we're seeing happen already in town or
right outside
of okay um so how do we meet housing
goal number one that's that maintain
pionia as a community that is accessible
to rrange of income levels ages and
households by ensuring adequate and
affordable housing options are available
policy housing number one work with
Delta County private water companies and
developers to develop housing units
designed in price for employees living
and working in Delta County with a
primary focus on those living and
working in ponia or within the ponia
census track
not on that particular policy but what
are like can you define what a policy is
here yes so this is a guidance document
right so this is when when you're
looking at a comprehensive plan this is
this is the community telling a
developer or the town the admin
government what is acceptable to our
community for building that's that's
essentially what I just want to clarify
if it's helpful I don't know if it is or
not but one of the things that was a big
point of confusion with the public was
this word policy um and like does it
mean that you know we have a parking
policy that says you can't park here and
to stepan's point like this is a
guidance document and really what it's
supposed to do is say these are the
things that we want to live up to how we
live up to them is actually going to
require rules laws and new actual
functional policies that are passed by
the Board of Trustees to actually
become the way we do business this is
supposed to be the guiding document on
how we do business and there it can be
used if some developer comes in and says
we've got this great new development and
a bunch of community members are like
that that is not consistent with our
goal that we have for our community it's
going to block our Scenic views and
destroy our agricultural Heritage this
document will not have the policy that
prevents
that uh development from going in but it
should have the guidance that says what
we want so you can like point back to it
and so the word policy I hear is almost
like policy light it's like it's not
like a law or a rule um and that was a
big point of confusion in community
understanding of what this plan was um
and really that it should be broad
enough that it's not overly prescriptive
but then the Planning Commission and the
board after it's passed should take
directive from it to go out and go ahead
and like how do we implement this also
to your point earlier about like well it
doesn't affect anything outside the town
technically it should it should have the
2 mile radius around it so we should
also be able to influence the character
of development like we don't want a kfo
to go in right next to town so we would
want this plan passed because that two
mile radius would say okay this is not a
type of use that fits within our
comprehensive plan like guidance you or
three sorry
and to to clarify Kos are confined
animal feeding operations and they are
the worst so yeah sorry I don't it's
been I like live in a different land
most of the time right now so it is
three miles but it it isn't just it
doesn't just pay on your proper right it
does influence the character of the
surrounding development and community
and it really should do so especially in
light of what we discovered in the
process where competing views between
what Delta County views as desired
development and What the residents of
the pay on your view as desired
development this is not to say anything
here or there but just that please think
of policy as like policy light and also
if anything looks overly prescriptive it
probably shouldn't be in the conf you
know what I mean it should be like it
should be something you can guide
yourself back to not something that
tells you exactly what to do so in your
professional opinion having looked at
all these policies that restricted so I
have not reviewed the housing policies
in detail at the last plan I was the
last meeting we came to an agreement
that we once the once the Planning
Commission approved this draft going out
that then we would support Community
engagement and education around this new
element at which point in time I would
formally read all the stuff that's in
here and you know be prepared to do that
but I'm not prepared to tell you that
today because I've been waiting for the
Planning Commission to get a draft that
they felt like they wanted to share with
the public and then knowing that that
would change likely based on public
feedback um that's how we've operated
thus far we we not having Direction yet
to review it I guess that's kind of
where the the sticking point is isn't it
because you submitted like we were able
to approve a draft to go out to the
community trusting your guidance
but now we don't have that we will only
get that once we approve it to go out to
the community I I don't know that that's
you will have to work out your process
internally and also again on this stuff
we really looked to Shay and urban World
Continuum so you know I I don't know the
answer to that no I have they just did
the housing action plan they didn't
really do
enough but I did she did work on our
team and did incorporate some of them
like said into the land um the areas of
town and like so no she did not write
this like St
that I me I don't know what to say the
process is different you know and that's
why I recommended at the last meeting
that we do an educational hearing to
educate on why these are out there and
then gather feedback and a number of
different ways from the community um and
then provide that to you all to
incorporate
back you know into into the plan and
we're kind not kind of we're doing
exactly what we did with each El right
so Planning Commission work session
future land element it was these
policies were created they were
presented we had a work session on them
and we accepted comments and we set a
date or timeline on those comments
tonight we're going over the same thing
it's it's the same process um and we've
been waiting to have this housing
element on on on to be discussed on
agenda here we are tonight um policy
housing number two promote the use of
alternative zoning techniques and
mechanisms to provide a mix of housing
types within residential neighborhoods
which can include reducing minimum lot
sizes and encouraging accessory dwelling
units that may be restricted as a
long-term rentals with affordable leases
um this policy uh you know this these
alternative zoning techniques what that
would be is kind of what you see in the
future land use element when we're
talking about mixed use zoning
designation or
or those kinds of things that you're
seeing um in that future land use map
for the votex school being you know
reclassified as something that we'd be
okay with being mixed mixed use so
that's that's something I was kind of
have sticking up on um Stefan because
when you say alternative zoning
technique techniques so you're talking
about mixed use not makes sense but what
could alternative zoning techniques mean
I mean that could have to do with any
property anywhere in town you know it
could be some alternative that we
haven't heard about yet so I mean that's
it seems so open-ended to say it that
way so so you don't want to be too
restrictive so that if there is an idea
that you actually like you know it would
come in and you could go as let's say it
comes in as a plan unit development put
and they've got this this idea to have
different zoning things like they might
want to have a convenience store in the
middle of this Hut that comes in you
want to give yourself the ability to
consider that as the Planning Commission
because that's where ped goes through
first before it goes to the Board of
Trustees but it has to go on the right
Zone you can't do that in like an R1
zone right think think about it as like
new development brand new development
they're annexing in a town because they
continuous
continuous sure sure but that's in town
already so you have to find one that's
not we voted to Annex it in town for the
P I know that's that's now it's the
state
silver okay yeah was in
town but but it's but it's a zoning type
that's you know it's it's this sheared
communal space kind of Courtyard kind of
living right communal Courtyard kind of
stuff out
there but we have shared space in the
middle and so you don't want to make it
so restrictive that you can't consider
those things right this isn't just
saying you we're going to allow it this
is saying you know this is a guidance
document that when something comes in
you can review it and say hey this is
where the comprehensive plan would
support this or this is where this
comprehensive plan doesn't support it
yeah I mean it seems like there there's
two housing policies in that in that
single policy there you've got the the
alternative zoning techniques and then
you have something about accessory
drawing units that may may be restricted
as couldn't those be two different
housing policies they sure could be
sure if You' like to break them out
that's something that can be done I mean
they seem not they seem tent
tangentially related but not necessarily
related at all yeah I'm just going to
put a note there to think about because
I I can't like make that decision right
now but I'd like to contemplate that if
that's okay so okay sure policy housing
number three provide FastTrack
processing and other incentives for for
proposed housing developments intended
for persons with special housing needs
including the elderly person's age 60
years or older the handicapped
low-income residents and large families
this is something that prop 123 requires
in order to get State funding for so um
having some sort of FastTrack processing
that was something that was um came out
of like a goals to achieve within
housing action plan and so that's why
that's included in there so that we're
not stopping or precluding ourselves
from applying for State funding um to
help with affordable housing what is
Fast Track Pro processing 60 days or
less for so you can't have public
hearings you would still have your
public hearing you just it would it
would be approved within 60 and then
that's if there's a special use review
you would have to do public hearings but
this is like somebody turns in an
application because they want to build a
an affordable housing unit let's say an
R3 right so R3 is our highest density
area that that means that internally as
staff and with our third party
consultant we'd have to turn that around
within 60 days
so this is a lot of information this is
what I've been asking
for okay you said you didn't need any of
this is this new information for you or
are you aware I find it all interesting
but I didn't need it you know I felt
like I trust all the input that's come
into this housing Al but this is what we
do this is exactly what we should be
doing is going through this element the
fast track makes me a little
uncomfortable I think of Mary and haste
and Leisure there are all sorts of like
adages about fast tracking but that
that's okay I'm just expressing my
hesitation I'm with what that means what
are large F fast
TR
um that could be I don't know what
whatever I mean there's no definition
for large families but this is this is
just an example of that so let's say
it's six people seven people in a house
could be multigenerational and that's in
the proposition that as it's handicapped
low income no providing FastTrack
processing I don't think you can
discriminate against people who aren't
related to each other living together
anymore so can you actually say things
like large families can so part of what
my email was two months ago was to get
these details so that I could go back
and research and look at them I have not
been given any of that so are are you
able to get this I mean of course okay
good of course but like it's a much it's
much easier to have the explanations and
writings to together to go back and
research these types of things you were
pretty adamant about not providing those
things where you not we are going
through the same exact process that
Phoenix Rising resources went through
for each element and I'm giving it to
you now that's that's this is what's
happening you're also saying that I
wasn't here it this I've been ask I have
been asking for it for two months you
weren't at the last meeting where it was
on the agenda I've been asking for forer
get I've been asking for for we're going
through it now Pete and I've been asking
for it for two months okay let's have
some decorum
here no impatience pleas we're going
through but I'm not prepared to to I
don't have all the details you're giving
me like propositions and different
things I don't have that in front of me
I haven't been able to so research those
things no but it wasn't reference I
asked for
references can you get a transcript of
this meeting is it going to be like
transcripts are yeah I know it's a
little numers it's not it's not the same
anyway okay I know but that's really ly
how you get the transcripts on YouTube I
haven't ever been able figure no I I
just can't when I when I review I have
to watch and rewatch and
this used to do it get all the
transcri okay so let's
um continue so where we policy housing 4
okay um it says acknowledge the role of
the private sector as a necessary
partner in addressing the community's
affordable workhouse Workforce housing
need the town doesn't build homes right
and so this is this is saying that we've
we we're acknowledging that a private
sector builds
homes policy housing five are you going
to do this for every
policy can I get through at least this
first goal first before you start I I'd
really like to get through that one yeah
okay so let's have an method here so
Stephan you're going to get through the
goals and then if you could just take
some notes we can go back and um is that
okay okay so the town doesn't build
homes is what you saying that's correct
uh policy housing number five use
annexations as an opportunity to expand
pay owners supply of affordable and
Workforce housing and continue to
require preex agreements for new
construction within the growth D area as
a condition of getting domestic water SS
policy housing number six support the
development of housing options designed
to accommodate multi-generational needs
to to allow residents the opportunity to
age in place policy housing number seven
take advantage of all opportunities to
ad me an affordable in Workforce housing
to ponia and the surrounding area while
being mindful of the town's desire to
avoid over concentration and overly
dense in any one
neighbor that is it for that first
goal okay
so um going back you did you have a
question about policy number four
acknowledge the role of private sector
as the necessary partner in addressing a
community's affordable and Workforce
housing
needs so the purpose of this is
someone's looking at this to understand
what our policy like
is I don't know how in acknowledgement
that the private sector builds homes is
the policy l
I
just how is that I just don't understand
how that fits into into the set so you
think it's kind of unnecessary how how
would the the Board of Trustees use that
to enact polies because it would give
the staff the ability to spend their
time meeting with a private person who
wants to build a
house remember this is intended for the
staff to use as guidance for the
overarching multiple ways that housing
takes place in the community there is
nothing unor about that
statement no one said it was UNT ask you
I know but you you act as if it's some
it's a bad
thing I'm
sorry sorry hold on a second because
this is this is this is going on way too
much this apologize continuing
characterizing what I'm saying it is but
let me ask you if you
could if you could say it differently
you you have an attitude in your voice
that's very it's quite it the the ad Min
you're just threaten to walk out it
feels very critical as opposed to being
more
constructive maybe a question if you're
going to criticize then then be be an
equal opportunity criticizing I have
question just to to people that
acknowledge the role of the private
sector does not mean just little old mom
and pop trying to work on their house or
are we giving like preference to
developers is that what we're saying
there's no preference here this is
acknowledging that the town doesn't
build homes that we have to be we as
staff have to be able to work with
somebody in developing a a plan that
would be okay for the Planning
Commission to pass or at least consider
and then have it go to the Board of
Trustees
for their consideration so if that's the
obvious process that we have to go
through is that a policy you need to put
in that's what why do you have to state
that if if this if if you hadn't read
this before now would you have known
that that's the way things work yeah I
mean the town doesn't build homes we
never have we can't afford that number
one and number two if you have questions
you go and you ask things of staff and I
know what's been happening is then the
building inspector charges you up the
woo he sure did so like normal people
are priced out of that
so so if I
can on social media today right the the
there's a post that took off because it
said the town's going to demolish houses
I'm not demolishing anything I can't
demolish homes that's I mean can you
condemn them there is is that I don't
condemn the building official condemns
so where are these lighted neighborhoods
I kind of am curious about that we
should have a light map if we're really
talking
about to the go if we're g talk about a
few different places if we're GNA talk
about actually and actually doing
something about BL then we'd be talking
about Tiff
districts okay were there any other
questions are like housing five six or
seven yeah this using annexations as an
opportunity to expand and the supply of
affordable workplace housing um I really
think that we need to have a clear
annexation policy frankly and so maybe
we re need to recommend developing clear
annexation policy
um I would just say that that we heard
that a lot from the town and the
community that we did need a clear
annexation policy I would suggest to you
that that's going to be a whole process
that's coming up with that and it's
going to be quite there are a lot of
differing opinions on that and yet
there's some really important
considerations the town needs to look at
to remain a functional entity from a
budget standpoint and um that's going to
be uh a major undertaking and one that
should be done head
on I don't know if a comp plan ever
gives that specific of a direction
though but I think you could after you
have learned from the comp plan go out
and say okay everybody we need to go do
this and that's what we should do from a
comp plan is in that process learn what
policies you want to undertake right
afterwards okay I just saw it in
ridgeway's comp plan and apparently
ridgeway's comp plan was very good so I
thought maybe you know and that looked
good to me specifically addressed I
don't think Bridgeway said go create an
anation plan right they did say have a
they they did say something about they
say something about like establish this
thing establish it don't exactly so that
would be the type of like level that I
would recommend exactly you should do
exactly you don't want to get stuck into
that you really need a bigger process
for the yeah so I mean if it could be
written in a way that's appropriate
let's say but you use the words yeah
because it kind of triggers the thought
later on right and and like you said we
should as soon as this is figured out on
the right words are established the plan
you guys should go do that that's going
to be a big process this Planning
Commission will be leading and need a
lot of community input and some real
budget background done in order to
inform it in a cohesive and like same
way
yeah we do have a chapter 15 on
annexation and
pay so really what this is referencing
is we would use that procedure to you as
an opportunity to expand and bring in
affordable housing that is you know
around the fringes town
into into town um and that but that
procedure for annexations was last
updated in
2015 I believe it's on our
Consultants um sustainable what are they
Sustainable Solutions Solutions um who's
working on our code rewrite to also talk
about um updating some things in
there okay so how housing policy
six support the development of housing
options designed to accommodate multi
General M General sh can't say that
needs to allow residents opportunity to
age in
place so this this could mean many
different things it's it could mean that
you would have multiple Generations
living under room roof it could mean
that there are homes for um the elderly
to downsize into that was in our housing
needs assessment um so that they could
vacate like a larger house sell it and
then move into something that's all in
one floor that's smaller we actually had
a resident come up at our last board
meeting who wants to do just that um
that was talking about wanting to build
something so that her son could move
into the larger house I mean so that's
that's what this housing policy is meant
to achieve okay questions okay um seven
take advantage of all opport
opportunities to add needed affordable
and Workforce housing to ponia and the
surrounding area while being mindful of
the town's desire to avoid over
concentration and overly densed
Construction in any one
neighborhood okay so um we've addressed
like an exing so we're not like doing
just the stack and pack strategy but
there's
actually creating more housing in areas
where there's no housing but not
sprawling because we're not big enough
to sprawl right yeah think of this
policy is like a catch all right it's
it's saying hey look if there's a grant
out there that helps us put in
infrastructure for someone that's
wanting to build affordable housing we
should take advantage of that and and as
staff it's giving us guidance to say hey
look Board of Trustees this is something
that we ought to go well after it's
within our
CS infrastructure okay think of it that
way that's but it's it's a catch all to
keep who pay the match for those kind of
Grants I mean is that going to be born
by the the town in general like if they
have a 25% match or something could that
drive the cost of housing up for
everybody else by not being prescriptive
it could be any anything it could be the
town matching it it could be a public
private partnership with the developer
saying hey we're gonna We Will We Will
Pony up this amount for for the match
but you've got to come up with the rest
it could be anything it's just saying
that we're we're we're not going to
close the door in that
opportunity
okay to with that did you have a
question no I'd like to suggest that we
move on to go that's what we're next
here was the last one so roll housing
number two and so we didn't have any
questions about seven that's kind of
that's yeah that was kind of cut and dry
right okay B housing to enhance and
maintain the character of p is existing
residential neighborhoods balance the
need to accommodate infill
development um housing 8 policy housing
8 says support enhancement programs and
efforts to strengthen existing or aging
residential
neighborhoods what is aging are you mean
people aging or housing is aging housing
right housing that's not energy
efficient
housing that um is doesn't meet the
needs of the people actually living
inside of it it could be any of that
okay how neighborhoods with crumbling
infrastructure which we that a lot like
trees and stuff um trees trees could
yeah it's everything within that element
so trees could be included right because
we're talking about um
keeping our our downtown and our
residential neighborhoods cool we do
that with tree
Camp
okay um so policy nine
was support flexibility yep support
flexibility and building design and type
to all neighborhoods to continue meeting
the needs of communities such as senior
housing intergenerational families and
special needs housing um this is
partially derived from what is in the
statutes about um like group homes and
Senior senior housing
um you've got to have a provision of
that in this in your in your
comprehensive plan um but it also allows
for like um uh ADA Compliant homes or uh
or like different types of design uh
like straw bail HS things like that
different types of building materials
okay butd printed in the houses thing
now um question about that but I I I
guess the thing about the um housing
action plan and housing needs assessment
and all this like Adu stuff it's kind of
turned zoning on its ear because things
aren't really R1 anymore you're looking
at R2 everywhere and so I guess what I
wonder about is when we I mean it's like
do you have any security as a homeowner
to know that anything goes I mean or
Does anything go in this new world of or
so when we say these things I I always
wonder what it actually means yeah well
to to be clear we're not doing anything
with zoning with our comence plan there
there's there's no zoning changes
happening we're not changing anybody's
zoning I know there's no zoning but the
thing is if when we start talking about
two houses for a lot that's R2 it's not
R1 anymore so so I'm not saying it's a
good thing or a bad thing but I'm just
saying there's this this fundamental
shift now that we're talking about two
houses for lot in R1 you don't have R1
anymore you don't don't have single
family one single family residential
anymore and so with this this company
plan is saying look at accessory
dwelling units that came out of the
housing action plan right says look at
access allowing for accessory dwelling
units but be be regulate them right and
so this isn't regulating adus it's not
allowing adus it's just saying we will
look at it and consider it okay yeah
because that's legislative right that's
yeah I don't think I'm communicating
very well but let's just move on in in
your opinion would I mean maintaining
the character of existing residential
neighborhoods would sure something about
short-term rentals be appropriate here I
don't think so um so that's that's a
very specific use this is talking about
infield development so um I have a house
that's dilapidated it is uninhabitable I
want to tear it down I'm not going to
build
something that's not in the same
character of that neighborhood so so
it's not going to be like a four story
kind of in so the infield development is
the key of that role here not not the
maintaining the character of the
existing residential maintaining the
character is just that as well so is it
not having I mean is it within the
character of a residential neighborhood
to
have half the homes be hotels seems like
that is very relevant
like
businesses you know unocc seems more
relevant than almost anything that's
there well what would what would you I
guess to what would you propose there
because if you're you've got to be
careful to not propose like actual
regulation or or like legislative action
it's you know what would you propose to
be in there encourage owner
occupied owner occupation of of houses
and Resident I don't I don't but it's
not well then what do you do with
longterm I mean I'm happy to
prop yeah seriously propose a policy
that would be good um just keep in mind
that we we're not regulating anything
you know you know doing any sort of
regulation in this it's just you would
have to use words like encourage or you
know support things I guess that's what
but regulation very well likely can come
out of this right this is policy light
as we yeah this should I mean one of the
things that's so hard about this whole
conversation is that you all need to
have these conversations but they need
to Happ them once you have a direction
that you can then go have them under and
so it's like the pre thing right and and
you can't have those conversations now
because this isn't setting the law but
you need to give yourself direction to
go ahead and if you need to reestablish
Zing re establish zoning if you need to
have a conversation on what the
interpretation of that zone is or if
this new comp plan
directionality may need to change this
may create a directionality that creates
a need to change the zoning in the
future so you do need to be aware of
that but again this is not this is not
the actual thing that's making the
change it could influence future change
and so the housing action plan one of
the items that has to come out of it so
I can finally get the rest of the grant
money for it so we have to give
short-term rent ordinance in place
regulation ordinance and that's on the
1126 agenda because it get it got
carried over from the uh the last
agenda um so it is it is coming those
regulations are are coming for public
comment and and
discussion um so we're coming that's
coming on the Board of Trustees at the
next week on Tuesday so um when you're
talking about info and I don't know if
this is the right place for it but and
it kind of ties back to
infrastructure you know there are lots
Big Lots I mean I've got four Lots
people think I've got this huge yard and
why don't I just build another house but
you've got to understand a lot of these
properties have sewer lines going across
them you know from the backyard to the
front yard they've got water lines
they've got gas lines what happens when
people start building on top of those
when they're doing infill do we have to
be clear that I mean but then I'm
getting a little specific we have to be
clear that there're we don't want to
start getting cont to where people are
building on top or setting adus on top
of infrastructure and that so if it's
their service line I mean they're going
to have to relocate their service line
but our
Mains in town certainly uh I can't say
that they all most of them run within
public easements um a good 98% of them
well when they enter the property that's
a service line and so yeah and they're
not in easement anymore but but that is
something that's taken care of with a
site plan the building permit process
and the application process that's not
something that would be discussed in a
comprehensive plan that's that's that's
building code is what it is well I was
just thinking info when you're talking
about info it's an exciting
word and I think that's a good question
like that's an appropriate question to
have here how would this direction
influence something that you want to
think about in the future right that
that you're going to have you're going
to want to do something about because
you don't want it to give you a
direction that you don't think is good
for the town right um that being said
you don't need to get into discussions
and Zoning like this this is not a
zoning talk but it will inform it so you
know that's a good way to think about
it so if we had a housing policy number
10 that
said hypothetically promote owner
occupied owner occupied homes for like
short from rentals or something along
those lines then how would that
influence your meeting on
Tuesday well I don't think the
comprehensive plan is where you get that
prescriptive I don't think the town can
I don't know how the town I I mean
even even even having that policy in
we're doing that anyway right so we're
there's there's a cap on the number of
licenses the proposed ordinance I know
some don't agree with
how how many licenses that's we've done
survey um but there's there's also um a
a predisposition for primary residences
to have to get licenses for single
family bedrooms that's also included
within that for single family homes that
are running out just a single bedroom
that's also included within that that
cap um I know I have a neighbor that
that's how she relies on some income is
she has a short-term rental that she
rents out one bed one bedroom it's a
primary residence and that you know
whoever rents it goes through a back
door separate interest so you know we're
already we're doing that with this
upcoming ordinance on the 26 so this
sounds like a land use ordinance is it
coming to the Planning Commission it it
doesn't need to what you can and can't
do with your private property it doesn't
need to and so there was if I did send
out an email with a response from the
town attorney that explain that it's
legislative and that that goes before
the Board of Trustees
well people in this town do what they
want
anyway so good
luck renting out bedrooms move on can we
move on to the next goal or course a lot
that's why you get get yelled at it's
fat so there you go
okay so where are we at now um
flexibility that one senior
housing yeah so goal housing 3 commit to
inclusivity by ensuring A diversity of
housing options that meet the needs of
residents including those for seniors
and residents with special needs um I me
that's pretty self-explanatory goal um
policy housing 10 Al what could be
policy housing 11 encourage new
developments to accommodate a variety of
housing sizes household types tenure
types densities and
prices policy housing 11 support the
development of a range of housing
options as may be appropriate in
different parts of the community
including but not limited to small homes
accessory dwelling units town homes live
work units and limited small scale
apartments or
Condominiums policy housing 12 support
strategies that help local residents
maintain resident occupied housing
rather than housing occupied by second
homeowners policy housing 13 expand the
supply of housing that is accessible to
seniors people with disabilities or
persons with Mobility limitations
through the use of Universal Design and
visitability principles in the
construction of new housing the
rehabilitation of existing
HS policy housing 14 the town shall
discourage Redevelopment demolition
practices that significantly reduce
existing housing stock in older
neighborhoods and that result in the
displacement of very low low and
moderate income residents or special
needs
households policy housing number 15 the
town shall monitor all Redevelopment and
demolition activity to ensure that
comparable relocation housing is
available in accordance with Federal
Regulations regardless of whether
Federal monies are used in the activity
and the town shall ensure that all
adopted and proposed regulations
maintain and encourage diversity and
housing types that will support adequate
relocation housing is
required Poli see housing 16 expanding H
expand housing options for the Aging
population to facilitate Aging in place
such as adus in and intergenerational
households and housing products for
downsizing
households policy housing 17 support a
Continuum Continuum of Care for
Independent Living to Assisted Living to
transitional
facilities that's a lot of
housing
[Music]
um um new development
okay so these goals are specifically
about seniors and special needs no so
it's commit to inclusivity by ensuring A
diversity of housing options that meet
the needs of residents including those
for seniors and residents of special
needs yeah it seems like like
um long-term winter would be a good one
to
add
that um can you explain
so long are getting moved out of town
because there's less and less less L
places for to rent can I explain exactly
why seniors and residents for special
needs is included that's a protected
class it's a federally protected class
that's why that's included um if and I
understand that I mean long-term renters
are like get get in the booth I get it
housing prices are nuts and interest
rates are even crazy and homes are just
being taken as hotels it's probably the
big so policy 12 support strategies that
help local residents maintain resident
occupied
housing rather than housing occupied by
second
homeowners so aren't you kind of like
being pretty specific there and I mean
when Pete is concerned about um
short-term
rentals um and then also it's kind of
interesting because in 11 above it live
slw units that's almost like having a
spare bedroom that you rent out that's
your that's your income right there so
that's almost a live work unit right no
that's that's um I guess it could could
be it could be but it would be more like
um what former mayor Mary bachran did
right she she has a home occupation
license and she does a like a seamstress
out of her house I think you should have
a home occupation license if you want to
run out of bed
shortterm well that's that's essentially
what a short-term rental license is
accomplish that's not in the zoning code
though and live work is in the zoning
card if you read the ordinance there's
there's also by special revie there's
special use review in R1 and E1 because
R2 already allows for two homes on a
property and R3 ALS also allows for
multiple housing so you know it does
require special use review which means
any short-term rental in a residential
neighborhood
like the majority of the housing in our
town would have to go to the Planning
Commission first well that means it
needs to be a zoning ordinance it can't
it has to be in land use if it goes to
the Planning Commission that's right
it's that's right it's it's a
legislative action to add that into the
existing
code okay so you're bypassing the review
process for changing and making putting
an amendment in chapter 16 what review
process what do you mean it says
anything that goes into 16 it's in the
Preamble for chapter 16 it has to go
through a public process it is a public
process well what public hearing is is
about for the
26th okay i' have to read it I'm sorry
we that
conversation yeah we're
never I mean I just want I just want to
the record that I emphatically disagree
that that it is that I I think that the
as you've seen my my email the lawyer
didn't site any evidence to support his
claim which is highly unusual for mat
okay but let's so let's let's move on
otherwise we'll be here all but I would
like to go back to the hous of
policy okay I do I want to kind of get
at that because it almost sounds
accusatory so what I'm getting at is
this is the actual email from the
attorney this came from the attorney
let's do it and I mean he gives an
answer all right here I'll I'll I'll uh
dear attorney bachner your dismissive
two sentence response reflects
problematic legal practice and warrants
careful scrutiny let's compare our
respective legal positions my conclusion
is firmly GL grounded in statutory
language CRS 3123 305 expit States no
such regulations restrictions or
boundaries shall be adopted amended or
repealed until after public hearing at
which the Planning Commission shall
submit its recommendation that's that's
the statute ordinance 20245 plainly
Falls within this requirement as it adds
new class use classification creates
development standards modifies permitted
use establishes new zoning definitions
your position in contrast offers no
statutory citation no legal reasoning no
explanation for exemption no procedural
support this approach raises several
concerns
you assert a legal conclusion without
providing any supporting analysis
essentially asking citizens to accept
your bare assertions two your claim of
errant conclusions in is itself conclus
and fails to address the specific
statutory requirements your refusal to
expend Town resources on citizen
inquiries about legal compliance
contradicts your obligations as Town
attorney to ensure transparent
governance four the attempt to Shield
your legal reasoning from public
scrutiny raises serious question about
town accountability I would direct your
attention to Colorado rules of
professional conduct 2.1 regarding the
duty to exercise independent
professional judgment and render
candidate advice unless you can
articulate specific grounds for
exempting these zoning changes from
statutory review requirements your
position appears to prioritize
administrative expedience over legal
compliance respectfully P
Cary I I haven't heard one I I haven't
like I just heard no I don't agree but I
have I'm I'm citing specific statutes
that say that this needs to go to the
Planning Commission and our esteemed
attorney is giving me a
nah I mean that's have to take up with
him but I would taking it up with all of
you I I would encourage you to read 3123
305 which talks about changes such and
this is for zoning this is part three
for zoning such regulations restrictions
and boundaries May from time to time be
amended supplanted supplemented change
modified or repeal um
that's by the Board of Trustees it's not
no one's arguing that the Board of
Trustees have have the right to pass
laws okay I I this is this is a common
pattern I State something you rephrase
it as a different question and answer
that question I understand but I I'm not
the one that answered that that was the
attorney so something I'm sure's I'm
sure he's going to reply that sure he's
going to reply no he his email said that
he would not be replying because of
expending town resources so that was the
final
answer okay so let's move on I would
like to go back to policy housing number
12 okay you like to uh so occupied by
second
homeowners I I first of all I would say
that that investment property so most
second homeowners the the economics of
it is that they buy a second home to
squat on it so that they can they can
reach the benefits of the equity
that whether whether they're occupied by
the C
homeowners a more a more inclusive
terminology here would be an investment
prod um so what rather than housing
occupied by second home owners or
investment properties no rather than
housing used as investment
properties would you consider somebody
that owns um a second house that they
rent out on a long-term basis in
investment property
yes so is that a good thing or a bad
thing say that again ask your question
again so would you consider someone that
rents out a home on a long longterm
basis more than 30 days right um would
you consider that an investment property
yes you know I think there's some stuff
this not to there's some stuff in the
statute about like even with a
short-term alss I remember hearing it's
not been litigated yet but it's all
called housing it's all called
residential and
and I don't I'm kind of wondering what
the statutes say about
rentals the point there is that that
really doesn't encapsulate shortterm oh
I see what you're saying okay what would
you
suggest to change and I think it will be
addressed in the ordinance in the
ordinance but I I don't believe so I
actually think the ordinance the
ordinance if we were going to support
strategies that help local residents
maintain resident occupy just cross out
rather than housing occupied by second
homeowners just say support strategies
that help local residents maintain
resident occupied housing period right
but you're saying that the housing
ordinance does that no I don't it could
short term yeah it could I mean this
wance is still in draft so that would be
the place to get to it though if you're
concerned about shortterm rentals and
who owns them as opposed to this plan
that's where the you know the regulatory
part comes in to actually have some
teeth now I don't know right now I don't
think it's precluding no there is a
there is a 200 days occupancy so
resident yes so most and so but we're
getting off on
that 200 days was decided because you
know what uh what is it 180 something is
considered
um primary if you're over that half for
365 200
is is more like this is your primary
residence Pete would you be happy with
that if they just took out the ra
because the rather than housing occupied
by second homeowners gets kind of
specific and it eliminates so it leaves
a little bit more open that way sure my
question is how how again it's like what
are we doing here so how does this
inform like here's a great example we
have a short-term rental ordinance let's
say that this was in place how would
this inform the
[Music]
board how would this how would you look
at look at this and look at the current
short-term rental ordinance and use it
to
inform what should and should not be in
there are you asking me that question
I'm asking I'm asking maybe You'
prioritize short-term rentals that don't
take away from the housing stock for
inst it's because the homeowner still
lives in the house so it's not elim no I
I mean I understand that I'm but that's
in the current short-term rental
ordinance there isn't a preference given
to owner
occupied there's a cheaper fee too there
is so that preference is built into the
fee right so that primary residence is
for running out a single bedroom it's
$150 for a license that counts towards
the cap as opposed to $500 for second
but if we had so so the reason to have
40 properties right is because we want
the CH all this right is is that no no
so the reason is because there are
currently so using the granic because
you did a demo I got a free demo yes and
I looked at Gran because I'm not sure if
you've looked at that software yeah so
I've used it before it's really
intuitive it it goes uses Google's metac
crawler it picks up everything and then
it it takes that and and also uses data
from the state for who's paid um for the
lodging tax and then it does all of that
I used to be weekly I think it's done
daily now and in that within our town
limits there were 38 active listings
that had shown that they had gone off
the market or come on within the last
two months which is a good indicator
that that was something being used as a
short-term re and so with that number
that 38 number it it makes it with the
reason 40 was decided on is because
those two extra licenses take into
account single bedrooms sweet grass
would have to get three because they're
not their they're not a home they're
they they're individual rooms being
rented out that don't have like the
other amenities like a kitchen and and
all that stuff so they'd have to get
three of those licenses to continue to
operate and so that's why that 40 was
decided um other communities have used a
percentage basis based on your existing
housing stock and so if we have 765
houses that's what was in the housing
needs say 765 775 something like that
5.2 2% is 40 so and and a lot of these
other places go like 20% of housing
stock and that's way too many I've got
two short-terms right next to me and and
I've already had one of those people
send in an email that wants to have uh
wants to have language stricken for a
local person contact I'm like I would
never recommend that because we had an
issue with that same property
sood I understand all that what would I
my my my strong disagreement with the
current short-term rental ordinance is
that the idea here with Shay was that
we're trying to find a
balance I'm assuming that balance is
between the needs of the long-term
renters and these people who are renting
that these out for for that so
grandfathering in all of the existing
short-term
rentals given the fact that the
long-term rentals have clearly been
suffering for the last 10 years or more
in this town how is that a balance
so I
want I think we're getting
maybe but but I do want to bring it back
to the policy so the reason why I'm
asking about this for this policy is if
we're supporting strategies that help
local residents maintain resident occup
housing let's just full stop there
okay then I would look at the short-term
rental ordinance let's say this existed
right
now and I would say that that that that
really doesn't do it a short-term rental
ordinance that support strategies for to
help local residents would prioritize
those 40 licenses to people who want to
rent out their the resident occupied
homes instead we're we're giving we're
actually prioritizing the majority of
those Str strs are not resident occupied
homes in fact they they single family
homes that were taken out of the housing
market away from what could have been
resident occupied housing and and used
as investment properties so my question
is is like if that exists if we had this
thing then then how would the current
short-term rental
ordinance re really reflect that housing
policy so could you amend the current or
I know it's hard on things
are but but but what we're trying to do
right by what you're trying to say by
reducing that that those the number of
licenses would be that the people that
have already bought these houses they're
off the market right there are they are
being used to short rentals currently
and what you're trying to do is by
reducing that number is to force
somebody
to turn that property into a long-term
redle essentially right and so
I'm be that would be this that would be
the Fallout for that ordinance and and
it could be challenged and seen as a
taking and if if it's seen as a taking
for for somebody that has bought that
property because we had a we had a
laxidasical policy on short-term rentals
it's it's terrible like I haven't
allowed any like any you um as a matter
of fact I mean you guys had a public
hearing about one still things
legislative is it a taking and if it's
quasi judicial where it goes through the
Planning Commission is it as much able
to be challenged special use review for
those so residential residential homes
right so if you're operating on uh Third
Street you know residential neighborhood
um you would have to go that's R1 you
have to go get a special use review
favorable special use review before you
can even apply for before you actually
get that license you can you can
actually apply for the license encumber
it depending on the outcome of that
special if if it's denied goes back so
the neighbors get to have a say
correct what I what I what I hear you
saying is that if we let's say that we
did 20 right you're saying that that
would be that could be legally
challenged I I would so the the but in
that same in that same line of
thinking 40 homes were taken away from
long-term renters there is in our
current ordinance something that says
that that you have to have 30 days
anything definition it's not it's a
defition you're right you're right but
it's but it was still so so where's the
balance if we're only concerned with the
taking away from people's investment
properties right versus how does it
support strategies that help local
residents maintain resident occupied
housing so so going back to like this
this policy should have been in place in
2014 right before before Airbnb went to
Austin before it went to what is South
by Southwest when when they really hit
the ground running and that's what
Denver did that's what bowler did that's
Fort Collins did they had this these
restrictions in place 10 years ago I was
in San Francisco when they passed the
things and people lost their short-term
rentals okay so there is absolutely no
what you're saying we call this bud in
in in my
industry getting a little off the when
you don't have when you don't when you
when you don't have an actual thing you
just kind of inject this fear do the
thing we absolutely can we could
restrict all short-term rentals this
town if we wanted to were there were
there lawsuits against San
Francisco I we live in the United States
of America can we have a five minute
recess pleas yes why
go you got my permission thank
you you can keep talking during the
break I don't I just
I don't we seem to be selectively using
the fear of
lawsuits we mean I'm meaning you
specifically selectively using the fear
of lawsuits to support the things that
you want not the things you don't want
so like can you be more specific please
well we have is there a lawsuit against
to town right now for what for the
removal of the trustee the sh Sur is
okay did that prevent any of the actions
that we did in August I didn't do any of
those actions I didn't say you did but
but did you did you warn against the
lawsuit for them doing that I mean they
you of Trustees was fully aware that it
would be that it would be as a matter of
fact it was threatened right during
during those meetings right and and they
thought it important enough to to do
even though there would there would be a
lawsuit so why is protecting and
bringing back 40 households back to this
community that would have existed 10
years ago have we done something why is
that not worth a legal risk there's a
Financial Risk there and you asked me
about San Francisco all the lawsuits
were dismissed so so there's a Financial
Risk there right yeah and and that
Financial Risk exists because somebody
had bought a property yeah with with an
intent to turn it into investment
property with a return on investment
okay and and unlike what happened with
trustee with former trustee Bruner yeah
there is a there is a chance that that
property could have the rights taken
away from them by artificially reducing
the number to four because if if we were
to say if I had conclusive evidence
today that said that said there are only
20 short-term rentals operating within
the town of ponia I'd be happy to push
that to so if it wasn't for the fear of
lawsuits you would support 20 I think
you have to I think you have to
weigh what
happen right and if and if you think
that you're you're G to win you go for
it don't think we'd be successful some
these Pro because they've been theyve
been able to operate for a decade as a
short-term re and if they didn't get the
chance or the ability to get that
license I'd be really concerned that
they would have a leged stand
up we're not trading new
territory I I can present to you I mean
many
cases between 2022 and 2024 that 2
per and and that might be something to
help sway a decision for the board at
their next meeting and if you I'll tell
you what if you get that in if you can
get that to me by by Friday afternoon it
can include
it
well but you need to get it so
[Music]
we are on the next section so do we want
to go to goal four yes
okay all right goal four housing for
preserve views to the mountains natural
amenities and Scenic mes from the public
Realm policy housing 18 maintain Scenic
Vistas from rights of way public
facilities and public lands to Open
Spaces jumbo Mountain Mount Lamor lands
and Peak the core commercial District of
downtown ponia as shown on the map and
to of view shed gateways and store
contents policy housing number 19 ensure
views designated on the map and titled
view shed gateways in historic context
are integrated into planning for the
development this may include dedication
of land setbacks height restrictions
modified building orientations or
modified placement level
think think of this is in conjunction
with infield development you tear down a
house you want to build a three-story
house all the way up to that 30 foot new
houses around them have already been
built that have a view and now you want
to obstruct that view um we would we
were saying hey look Planning Commission
um in consideration of a special use
review or h zboa in consideration of a
variance you would allow for a different
orientation of that building on that
property that structure on that property
to maintain views for Neighbors as long
you know you might allow for an
encroachment to some setbacks things
like that we're saying we're allowing
that as long as you can ensure that your
neighbors continue to have their view
unobstructed this this actually was a
problem up in Lynn's neighborhood um for
new construction
so a new house was built and obstructed
a view I think it was a former trustee
who um ended up selling this house and
buying the house next
door were there there other like I guess
my question is it's like sort of around
like show your work like are there
policies
that got left off of here are there like
that you could have considered as part
of
this I don't know what you mean we've
got two policies here right like when
you sat and you you looked at how go
number
rep how did you
approach how did you approach how did
you pick these two as the housing well
so the first one is really based on a
map that was presented early on um
before it got incorporated into what is
known as the future land use map so
there's this this gateways map that
shows what our gateways are and then
what our Scenic views are and so um one
of the things I have to do is update
that map to make it so it can be
inserted into this into this element um
but it's it's that's where that one came
from and then
um let's see uh these are just
suggestions so if we're if we're
ensuring that views are maintained for
Neighbors um you can include like like I
said this dedication of land set backs
height restrictions modified building
orientation modified placement a lot
that I believe um was a language that is
already in you
um I believe that came from was Ridgeway
something to do with f and it's
similar to what they put in one of their
bullet
points suan put in their zoning what's
this is what I've been asking for all
along we've been waiting to have this
spe I can't write on well it's like
I understand so it was so I know you s
about statutory duties my statutory
Duties are running the town and then
it's also within our code of ordinances
that's really is very prescriptive then
they have a contract that I have to
there's no statutory Duty for Town
administrators to even it's only for
city managers and they're supposed to be
elected I I understand that but but
there was so there was a conflating of
that word statutory in our code of
ordinances I I have a very specific set
of things I'm supposed to do believe it
or not attending Planning Commission
meetings is not one of them and and so
I'm here to do this um because we've
been waiting to have this this public
meeting to go over these things and
that's why we're that's I mean is that
that's not entir can we just move on to
the next goal please yes or talk about
here this we really have this is good
stuff to get through so um and sure
views
designated I feel a little funny about
like designated view sheds I mean do I
get a view shed
I mean it's like we're all in the
country here I have a view I'm kind of
on the North Slope and I just have a
view of the skyline there but I don't
see Lamborn Maus so does that exclude me
from like someone building
and like if you live in a bowl like
what's your view
shed you know I just I feel it's like
certain people are getting these view
sheds and other people are going to get
screwed so I kind of feel uncomfortable
with I mean if don't have a view shed
right now well what what you why would
we ensure that view shed I mean it's
listed up above it's you know you got
Mount lamber jumo Mountain have lambor I
don't have jumbo Mountain but I do have
L the edge of lambor Mesa that is a
Skyline that I don't want to see houses
up there because it's GNA like start so
it's like but is that going to be on the
map I think everybody who moves here is
kind of expecting this it it wouldn't be
it wouldn't be houses on lamber Mesa it
would be your neighbors building a 30
store a 30 foot house no they don't they
can be 30 foot because it's a steep hill
sign I know and what we're saying is
what we're saying is we'll modify that
structure so that it maintains view
sheds of the neighbors okay that's what
it say I mean we actually had one go up
at the head of R ground there and I
actually get shading now in the winter
time and it's up on the irrigation ditch
basically is that to yeah hope that not
do that VV
I didn't know that it should have been
built called Laura's Tower when was this
built when Ken M was
there Stan there's nothing I can do
about that got approv he signed off on
the roof before the second floor was and
here's the best part if you had this in
your comprehensive plan you could have
considered maintaining that we had steep
slopes on there but it was completely
ignored and the neighbor wrote a letter
to him steep spe slope is for landslide
in like exactly this is different this
is maintaining your view they didn't
even use the rules that we had
well that's what we're
trying that's what we're trying to know
but the thing is you can have these
rules that it depends on of course but
this is the framework and then we get
the
regulations framework where we have a
okay okay goal housing number five
identify recognize protect Pon is unique
and irreplaceable historic and I should
say cultural heritage policy housing 20
protect historic and cultural resources
for the aesthetic cultural educational
environmental and economic cont
contribution they make to maintaining
and constructing Pia's identity and
quality of
life policy housing 21 acknowledge and
support ponia Artisan artistic and
Multicultural Heritage and Community
diversity in planning Town facilities
programs events and
resources that was it for that
goal any I mean those were pretty
self-explanatory right um okay and
you'll notice that in policy housing 21
I really start hammering in both our our
audit letters our management discussion
analysis our budgets and within this
comprehensive plan this change that
ponia has done from a mining or mineral
Centric Community to trying to change
our identity to this creative culture
and so you'll notice that those are
going to be in a lot of policies because
it has it has significantly changed our
economy it has significantly changed our
economy and there's there's it's not
just anecdotal evidence there's hard
evidence coming from the Department of
Revenue that says so really and there
is specific to pay specific to Pon
absolutely because the town that has the
ability to see every
everybody's taxes by company yeah and
was the case right that spreadsheet is
actually pretty intuitive and I can
drill it down to even special events and
find out if some so we can compare um
who has been listed on a special event
and if they've paid those sales taxes
and I can match them up and those that
do not pay sales tax we actually have a
provision that we can um of go after
that so it's getting more sophistic
it is Department of Revenue has has been
uh has been updating what how they track
it's not the gift economy anymore
correct um goal housing number six
preserve protect and stabilize the
character and visibility of residential
neighborhoods particularly within areas
of natural hazards such as flood plane
and steeve smoke conditions or require
demolition when Rehabilitation is not
possible nor economically feasible such
as in areas where a significant
concentration of substandard housing
exists that contributes to Nega
neighborhood or environmental conditions
so you said that had to do with FMA
areas right it could be within you know
flood plane and has are do we have any
buildings in FMA areas we sure do and
where are they so they're along Fifth
Fifth Street or Fifth Street and they're
also along um price Price Road Price
Road but there's some in town limits by
the library I thought the library said
they were not in the flip they are not
but the houses right up on the bank okay
okay
yeah um okay but in general in general
I'd like to know where the substandard
housing is is that going to be on our
map too if it's outside of FEMA we don't
I want to see where the target is there
are no targets so this isn't something
where we're going to go we're going
after this one this is this is to say
that if it's not economically feasible
to rehabilitate a house de demolition
would be considered so who gets to
decide that is that the homeowner well
no that's that's actually building code
and a building official decides that
based on code it could even be a fire
marshal um who decides that something's
unhabitable because it doesn't meet fire
Cod that's kind of scary to me I mean I
think of my neighbors and um I think of
what could go up if someone decided to
take something down and it's kind of
threatening the rest of these goals
should get at that though because there
was a big thing about if the house is
taking down they can't just put
something else up that has to match what
is needed in the neighborhood that was
one of the what do you mean what is
needed I mean there's a goal we we just
went through the goal there's one here
already so I mean single family sure
whatever but I mean they could move it
on the lot put it on your property line
more sou exposure well that's but they
shouldn't be able to because of all the
setbacks that guess we're just to see
well and there's the goals here are to
protect some takes a house down first
they can't just I mean there's already
five five places where demolition is
discussed and that the town can have
some say in what's going back in place
that was one of the policies the town
has the say but the neighbors can't have
well no I mean there's still all the
zoning setbacks and everything Suzanne
so's house is
lot someone could just move it right on
the property line it would be a
nightmare I don't think they could
because they could as long as it follows
the zoning regulations
the only zero lock we have is no six
feet when things are uphill from you six
feet is very close is what I'm saying so
I'm just I just like it scar me and and
when I think of CHS and Redevelopment I
think of Charity Creek I think of the
observatory park and what I saw down
there was so so sad what people
developers when they get their hands on
things well I think that's why there's
some sections in here there's also an
international building code that we've
adopted that talks about steep slope and
how high up you can go on a slope I
don't know how steep this slope is
that's that's interesting that would be
really interesting to put that on the
map what the Steeps what the slopes are
um it is on fut it is on the future
landuse map and I believe that is a map
that we have to provide right in the
comments I think it was steep slope and
flood point I
think they say 30% what is it in our
code 40% which we would have to do high
Hazard areas and I and that's that's
that's coming but you're not going to
pick out individual prop yeah I know but
I that's what it's like it's a little
threatening something because we've
never talked about blight before in this
town and you know there's a lot of old
coal miner shops around here and it's
because people two of them put together
and stuck in a I know but it's because
people can't afford anything else and so
when you start requiring tear downs and
and new Energy Efficiency standards it
becomes really expensive it's not
requiring it's encouraging
encouraging and the other thing I wanted
to add is there's a really nice
table in the housing needs assessment
there's a table of all the places that
people get assistance so um and a
neighbor across the street just took her
two years but she got a new furnace she
got new windows through this program
that's one of the ones on so this is an
exam this is an example that maybe what
we could ask for in Delta County is our
county commissioner rid of the housing
rehab Grant and and the housing rehab um
low interest Loan program picked it up
five years ago they got rid of it so
chaa picked it up I have information up
there
so Colorado Housing Finance Authority so
they came and uh gave us a bunch of
materials please pick one up they got a
bunch of Rehabilitation low low interest
loans or grants that they that they're
willing to give to anybody in town Delta
County now or somewhere else they sure
are so they're off montros and but she's
come to visit with me and she's also
very close to Dana with Delta Housing
Authority they used to come to the town
once a year and they do a presentation
and people could know what was out there
they make a presentation at the meeting
Delta Housing Authority doesn't really
do much here anymore yeah they used to
be a lot more active yeah but chaffa is
very theyve with we would donate to them
the town would like cop up 100 bucks or
something I don't have that bud I don't
[Music]
Canim yes policy housing 22 commercial
uses that are adjacent to Res
residential districts May expand if the
expansion will not have an adverse
impact on the character or viability of
the surrounding neighborhood or if the
expansion will substantially increase
non-residential traffic in the
surrounding
neighborhood policy housing 23 support
encourage individual homeowners and
developers to increase reinvestment that
improves resilience storm water
management and Water Conservation type
improvements landscape and her
structures on private property as well
as enhancing the design structural
quality and aesthetic conditions of
existing housing in the neighborhoods
and the neighborhoods through the
pursuit of building form standards and
upcoming updates to the town's Land
Development code which ensure that new
development Redevelopment preserve the
existing Community Care policy housing
24 support efforts of community- based
organizations and neighborhood
Improvement initiatives which contribute
to the stabilization conservation
enhancement and Improvement of existing
housing structures and other physical
facilities within neighborhoods policy
25 the town will create programs and or
incorporate tools within its Land
Development code to reduce substandard
housing that will also help to identify
specific structures and or general areas
for rehabilitation Redevelopment and if
appropriate
demolition by one one comment on
policy
23 is is are we now getting into the two
prescriptive Zone and
maybe I don't know I'm not a
yeah I'm not an expert here so so I
don't think so what this is really
saying is like we're going to promote
people to start uh that that want to
we're going to encourage homeowners to
make their houses more resilient to
climate change more resilient to um you
know what we see in the springtime with
with de of water and um and then also
promote like Energy Efficiency right so
you're going to you're also not going to
we're also going to promote like using
less water zeroscape could be something
that's considered for homes um we have a
couple of homes in town that when they
when they do uh a couple of properties
in town that are residential not
commercial um that when they use water
to irrigate it's like hundreds of
thousands of gallons a month we're
paying for it um but how do you you know
we want to promote something to reduce
that for water conservation things like
that I um I have a question that's not
in here but when you think of that slope
along there Rio Grand for instance you
know the water problem in Rio Grand that
comes down wet the whole street there on
to the south of Second Street remember
thatuh they've been looking for that
started when that Hillside started being
developed because people start building
things and they divert the groundwater
and they just dump it on because there's
no infrastructure there to put there's
Springs along that Hillside so I mean
again we have to be cognizant of things
conditions that are in place that can
impact surrounding homes the town
property the roadway under main roads
and that's kind of what policy foot 23
is saying is you're you're promoting
reinvestment to improve resilience in
storm water management it's not storm
water though it's spring water oh that's
a whole another nightmare when you're
talking dit when you're talking ditch
companies they it's not ditch companies
this is year round there's a spring that
comes down oh it's not an irrigation
ditch it's spring it's not it's spring
there's a year round spring that my
neighbor it was dumping onto Delta
Street and I eventually took it and I
piped it all and I put it back into the
tail storm store my yard and it wasn't
it's just that's what people have had do
around here you just have to like try to
solve these problems I I didn't know
anything about it but if it's a spring
we have to look at water rights who
actually has water rights for that
spring if nobody does then the town will
put in short it and I'll find a way to
pipe it to our our water plant so well
we've had it tested it's really hard
plants but I think that's that's another
problem that we saw there with that
steep slope development there there is
actually year round Springs on there I
mean certainly irrigation and irrigation
on top of the NES adds to it but there
are actually year round Springs that we
I don't think we're cognizant of and so
when we talk about developing these
areas we can also create problems
because we don't have enough information
about um
things and and we can't create policies
if we don't have the information in
place either we currently require um
like for for certain development we
require not only with your site plan but
how you're going to manage your storm
water and so um let's just talk let's
let's just talk about it that it's
groundw water and storm water maybe we
want to add groundw as a word into in
sure that's something that you can a but
when you get a permit you have to you
have to do a study of the water table
correct and then you have to mitigate
I've never heard
that here he's
not the it's in the building you have to
do that a site plan
you have to have you know what if you're
unaware of it until you cut down the
trees and start digging a hole and all
of a sudden it's like the trees aren't
there to suck it up anymore and it isn't
it's about the water
cable okay so we'll just add ground
water sufficiently vague but it's
mentioned right yeah it's just something
to be cognizant that's it's great storm
water and groundwater man
management that's a that's a
start okay okay go housing seven
encourage building and construction
strategies methods and practices that
promote Energy Efficiency through low
impact design principles including the
use of renewable energy resources and
the construction of new homes the
rehabilitation of existing
homes policy housing 27 encourage
individual homeowners and private
developers heuse currently acceptable
bring housing specifications as made
available for us Green Building Council
for the rehabilitation of existing
housing structures con
constructions policy housing 28 promote
and enforce efficient design and
construction standards as those become
adopt as these become adopted as part of
the international building code the town
shall also promote commercial and
residential standards such as passive
houses that are promulgated from time to
time by the Colorado Green Building
guil So when you say encourage these
requirements correct and can the board
tmin a
requirement say that again can the so
you said the board can turn to encourage
individuals to they can start requiring
things in their laws well they would
they would have to write an ordinance
that says this is
required
um I would I would caution them that if
it's not the international building code
as a requirement not to make it a
requirement
there's some things that it's awfully
hard for old homes to conform even the
international building code is actually
not all that great for old
bones but in my opinion so this could be
something like um you know what is it
that double paned gas Windows replacing
your windows in your home um it could be
getting a heat pump system for your hvc
um all of which receive state federal
tax credits um so those are all those
are all things that can be dealt with
that so this is something I was walking
in the snowy morning the other day 5
o'clock in the morning along First
Avenue there and I came it was that new
modular home that got put in there and
there's this it sound like a car running
just kind of idling and I was like what
it's like it's their heat so the more
like density you get the more conflicts
you're going to be getting between
homeowners because all of a sudden
they're like noises and things that you
never knew were going to exist with
these new homes and I'm really concerned
about that that were you know not
addressing and and I'm sure that it was
the hum was silent enough to not violate
noise the Colorado noise rules but it
would be enough to drive a neighbor
crazy if you couldn't step out your back
door without keeping that hearing that
constant hum so what do we do about
things like that well um we do have
noise ordinance so it's not loud enough
to violate the noise ordinance I kind me
her that would be interesting just to
see but I I doubt it would be loud
enough um but those so I do want to say
if you do have a if you do see something
um that you think is maybe a violation
you can report it through text my go
anonymously and then we go look at it
that's good to know I don't think it's a
violation though but it's something that
could be a real annoyance and it comes
with increasing density when you're
packing people together and this
obviously wasn't density in this area
but I was like God how would you like to
live next door to that so you know
there's there's some things that you
guys could require in um in like uh some
of these policies where you could say
appropriate screening you know through
bushes or something to help with reduce
noise levels you know consider consider
noise levels something like that you
could you could put that to one of these
policies easily
which goal do you think that would go
under
um maybe with energy efficienc because
these heat pumps are all part of that
I'm just preserve protect and stabilize
the character and visibility of
residential neighborhoods particularly
this is housing go
six so areas of natural has I just
wonder so
density
doesn't
character it doesn't impinge on the you
want I just wonder if you add in um
something auditory auditory
nuisances that's why people want to get
away from the Cities A lot of times as
they get tired of these conflicts and
living so close to people and I'm afraid
that we're going to bring it
here there maybe it does go under
housing seven as like policy 29 or 30 um
where are we the very end yeah in in
um and maybe that's ensure that all
um efficient design and
constru I don't know how you that where
you where are you reading from I'm I'm
thinking out loud oh but are you
thinking of a new policy yeah under
housing
seven um Inc it's some sort of an in
ensure that all energy or energy
efficient designs and
construction
contemplate
both light trespass and noise trespass
or something to that that effect okay
that's just acknowledging because then
then you're also covering dark SP
yeah okay
so having gone through this what we did
with our last elements is that we opened
up a period of time to accept public
comments and feedback um what we
recently did with the short-term metal
ordinance is we put out a survey um we
didn't do a survey with the other
elements but I think that because this
one has been so controversial maybe it
is wise to get a survey so we actually
have feedback um my only concern that we
have that I have is that um we want to
hear from people in town and not not
folks that live out of town I guess
those people out of town we want to hear
from too because we do have a growth
manag area right but but you know I
think it would be up to you guys to
decide what you would weit higher would
you wait an opinion from in town higher
than out of town or not so so are you
suggesting a Survey Monkey specifically
we bought Survey Monkey for a year so
we're gonna have lots of surveys folks I
I mean I if I can just I did not think
that was a very good survey put out
today or yesterday oh no no because you
it was it was biased in the actual
questions you're like explaining your
reasoning and then asking a question and
you're basically
editorializing in your question and then
asking a question which is a which is
not how you do surveys this is an
academic survey I I understand but but I
want to tell you one thing so what was
going on with that with what was going
all over social media was completely
Incorrect and I don't it was all opinion
and not fact-based and so what those
what that survey did it provided a link
it's fixed I know the link wasn't
working but it provided a link that goes
to the actual short-term rental
ordinance and that it also talks about
what is that meat that is in that
ordinance yeah for those questions did
you notice that in the the email that
you included from Shay that it said that
you would you would bring Shay said it
said that that ordinance would be
brought to the Planning Commission I'm
I'm well aware of what Shane recommended
okay recommended sure yeah yeah it was
from sh yes but it was what she
recommended and it was what you said you
were going you did say to us in a
meeting you were going to bring it back
to
us for the
so um the survey do you have a printed
copy available for people
too uh no we we don't have a PR TR
because I know people like neighbors of
mine who don't do
computer and have them come see us and
we'll we'll get them set up with
something they can set it right there
and take that Ser very easily know how
motivated they
are we should have a hereo well they
just I guess we could yeah and then um
what I what I do is have uh probably one
of our staff members then add those
responses into the Sur because it's it's
going to give us ANS so we could have a
printed one add it to would you be
willing to share that with the Planning
Commission in writing I think we should
analytics no no before you send out the
survey I think we should be able to
approve it you mean for short for the
short-term rental or
this survey
the abolutely I'm not asking that we
approve it I'm just asking that we work
together to to get
to I mean this absolutely this process
has going on for a decade trying to get
the company Supply
past and yet we still we still released
it without a housing element in June you
know so it's like there's no there's a
reason why it's taking a long time
problems to get
you years maybe seven
years we
didn't comprehensive
plan not in
2014 Tammy was going to try the write
part of it that was in 2018
2019 okay well okay so thank you for
doing over the those
a lot to go I mean I may have feedback
feed but I appreciate going yeah thanks
I thought it was a meeting in itself I
mean so it was good to be able to
reserve
one one meeting for
this okay so any more
questions um I know you can't make
decisions but is there a period of time
you want to accept
[Music]
comments we're coming up on holidays too
so I think it should be a little
extensive takes a little longer did we
have a date for a public hearing on this
whole on everything yeah what
happened forgot it's on Tuesday's agenda
there little less than 00 left for Shay
not I mean not Shay for so Tuesday's
agend is on 10th of December right she's
yeah she gave a December um no we I I we
said to be determined in January because
we decided there's no way to get all
this together in the advertising and
have people come in December okay okay
so that was oh I mean you're meeting
where you're going to decide if you want
to spend the money no this is Tuesday
yeah what Tuesday to the Tuesday this
Tuesday 26th 26th
Okay calendar is um asking the trustees
to release the
$393 left in the to rows for her to help
advertise when the full draft is ready
for everyone to see and to get it out to
people so that they can come to and it
wouldn't be the hearing it'll just be a
meeting for people to weigh in on the
20 um
26 the second Tuesday yeah I will
attempt to go through
the the transcripts and put the sort of
details for each of whatever the housing
policies are here share that with you to
make sure that you know it's not is out
of character we agree with it so that we
kind of have something to look at
because I think that the people who
aren't here that will be useful for them
to also look at yes agree thank
you and you will get comments before
Friday for the short or I will thank you
so I can include them in a
packet I really don't want to work the
weekend
again
okay so um I guess so now comments you
were looking
for ask people so how do you want to do
you want to ask for comments so now that
this has been open right and we've we've
had this public discussion along this
element um maybe we start accepting them
until
um let me look at
we did two weeks for the other elements
but we're coming up on holidays I don't
think that's that's enough
time so what do you have in mind for um
the meeting does anybody have
preferences for the meet the regular
meeting um coming up here can iish I was
kind of wondering if so maybe maybe we
accept comments um to December
31st and then at your December second
meeting I should have a survey language
ready for you to look over so then you
can decide on Final language that survey
can go out on December 3rd and 4th then
you have all that time to
gather feedback does that sound
okay so do you want to talk about the
survey at at the next
meeting that's that's what I'm saying
I'm suggesting that is I'll have survey
language for you to go over and tweak I
I I I will not attend that meeting um
okay but I will I will endeavor to have
whatever your final things are after
that second meeting to have it into a
survey and publish the the week of the
second so I have to take time off the
second the first Monday the normal
schedule okay so we can like look it
over then yeah the second the is it the
first Monday yeah the second
yeah December 2nd survey
language
yeah you want to just keep it to
that and because you've already approved
all like you've already said okay to the
other elements we haven't really talked
about future land use map or anything
future land use map but that's put it on
I got more maps that you guys have to
look at too so would you have you would
have
those
that's so potentially I'd rather you
just like look at survey
and too much to look at too many things
just yeah takes
long
okay that sounds
good okay great so the survey
language next meeting will be the topic
let
IDE
right so I know there weren't motions
made for this but there were some minor
edits to the policies are you all good
with those minor edits being put
in um before the survey goes out oh yeah
can so can we just see the
minor December edited we can see the new
edit what I'm saying is we can't do a
motion tonight but can we go ahead and
put that into to the draft so everybody
can see it on for the second we can
agree to
it sounds good to
me
okay yeah you hit the gabble no it's a
work session
any thank you everyone thanks