e
e e
call I guess we can just I guess
commission chair
Watson and I said chair Watson oh I
think you did you need to hear hears or
can we just say our names oh yeah you
can just say your okay that's where we
were there you go um commissioner
Smith okay so um I have a letter of
resignation here
um I don't know have you guys have it
heard anything about this or I did hear
about it hav't read it so our
commissioner um McCarthy is resigning
from the Board of
Trustees um I'm going to read out his
letter of
resignation um for the
record dear Board of
Trustees oh so I'm I'm doing this before
the approval of the agenda I don't know
do we want to approve the agenda first
or this kind of deals with roll call so
I'm I'm just going to read it out I
hereby resign my pos position position
as planning commissioner effective
immediately two weeks have passed since
I submitted a detailed documentation of
serious governance issues to this board
um uh presumably it's the town board
because um we're we're not the ones in
charge as the Planning Commission um
your complete silence speaks volumes
about the state of oversight in our town
I take this step only after witnessing
the systematic dismantling of the
Planning Commission Authority and ex
experiencing persistent hostility while
attempting to fulfill my duties the
November 20th work session transcript
clearly
documents uh um bullet point the Town
Administrator threatening to abandon his
duties when I asked basic process
questions bullet point the mayor and
administrator working in tandem to
dismiss legitimate requests for
documentation bullet point my repeated
requests over two months for written
policy explanations being
stonewalled bullet point a pattern of
administrative retaliation when
Commissioners raise
concerns the Planning Commission has
been reduced to a cere a ceremonial role
expected to rubber stamp decisions
without prior review or
documentation when Commissioners attempt
to exercise meaningful oversight they
face hostility and dismissal from town
Administration your continued silence
regarding silence regarding these
serious issues makes clear that proper
oversight is not a priority for this
board I cannot in good conscious
conscience contribute continue serving
on the commission um where asking
questions and requesting documentation
is met with threats and
retaliation the community deserves
better than performative governments
governance my duty is to the citizens of
the town since I can no longer
effectively fulfill that Duty and this
compromised environment I must step
aside for the record Pete McCarthy
former planning commissioner
so I'm uh you know obviously very
disappointed in this the Planning
Commission is an opportunity for
citizens to start becoming involved in
their local government um you know and
just involvement in local government and
should be an opportunity for us to start
learning our code learning how it
relates to the laws the processes the
whole fact that citizens are we are the
we the people we are the governance of
this town and I'm incredibly
disappointed that um this commissioner
um you know we
didn't I don't there's this environment
that has allowed this to happen and
instead of bringing people up and
letting the new people catch up and
understand um the processes and how
things work it's just like there's this
Steamroller going on um
I would like to bring to your attention
it looks like there's some
um correspondence that we got in the
form of an email that Stephan W passed
to us the Town
Administrator um with a correspondence
between commissioner McCarthy and the
town attorney and it was in response to
the um adoption of an ordinance um
dealing with short-term rentals
um and I I you know um he wants to
understand the rationale for bypassing
the normal process which in our code
chapter 16 the zoning code and confers
um um the involvement some involvement
assign some involvement to the Planning
Commission as a um not decision maker
but um what do you call that giving a um
recommendation to the Board of Trustees
before an ordinance is adopted can I ask
how this is relevant to the agenda um
this is relevant because someone has
just it's not on the agenda we're not
this is not an action item and I'm
making a statement here as the head of
the Planning Commission I'm not sure
it's it is okay call the police and
arrest
me the legislative the attorneys we got
an email and I'm sharing this with I
understand reading the letter ofation to
explain why commissioner McCarthy is not
here you're inappropri okay take it to
the Board of Trustees please
okay this is the attorney position I
know we heard it at our meeting on
Tuesday okay that your interpretation is
not the legal interpretation well he
didn't address my concerns
16430 Board of Trustees public hearing
do you know fin to the prior to the
final adoption of any amendment to this
chapter do you read the reference the bo
of Trustees shall hold a public hearing
thereon have you read the public hearing
that they refer to it's puds and Zoning
no it's not
PE change to this chapter listen our
attorney made a statement you are not he
not reference this suan and so I I have
I have made copies of all the revisions
to our code that you made it has nothing
to do with puds it says any section this
are not a lawyer it
says I am my concerns and this is
exactly what's happening there's no
communication with a Planning Commission
there's no Hest discussion it's you and
Stephen wi taking the authority away
from
these this is absolutely not true our
attorney explained to you what
he did not he did
not not the Forum here you go I don't
want I'm commissioner this is chair page
16 anyway this is this what I'm refering
you do not have legislative Authority we
are here to work on we're not doing
anything legislative tonight page I am
pointing out an issue here you know we
can't fix that these are all the things
that I know but there was an email
relevant to this I am sharing this with
you I did not email you back I did not
have private Communications with you I'm
doing this publicly giving you the
paperwork here um citing my concerns we
just had a planning commissioner resign
because of this issue that's going on
the way you and step and this thing that
you do together do you know we don't do
anything together it's all in public
including our attorney dealing with your
comment at Tuesday's meeting no he did
not not deal with my con page no he
cited a different ordinance he did not
site ordinance
16430 and you can look it up if you'd
like
166 1430 shall be given as provided in
yes so look at what it what it
ref I am I am not going to there is no
point in my interacting with you with
this
Forum we'll have our attorney that's for
me to deci he will give you a
full understand like a discussion with
thatne the trustees have just passed an
ordinance Suzanne in
viation I I don't have authority but I
have concerns as a member of the
Planning
Commission the meeting yes I'm letting
you know P look point of order stop
interrupting me
I'm sorry we need to continue with the
meeting so I want to just say how
incredibly hard it is participate in
this body when we have had this
administrator who has undermined me
privately to the Board of Trustees AB
yes he slandered
me relation to
the I have no trust in these people you
need to go sit down with Stephan and
talk to the attorney at the same time
I'm talking about it and then yeah
because this is not constructed You
Don't lecture me P not no I hear your
word and you don't have to lecture me I
am the chair of the Planning Commission
and if you don't like it you can kick me
off you do not get to create your own
agenda this is a for we are not making
any decisions I am making a statement
with the agenda that I passed to Samira
the format that I wanted follow this
summer there was announcements up ahead
and I have been consistently undermined
nobody you know when I wanted a meeting
so we can establish our processes
someone mysteriously cancelled it here
at Town Hall I mean this is this
recording pattern that we have been
subjected to and you're on the inside so
it's awfully nice for you you have this
intimate convers you know contact with
the staff or we don't have that we I'm
trying to explain to you we feel like
total Outsiders who's we well I don't
know probably I'm not speaking for um I
mean McCarthy but I'm sure he has the
same feelings as me he's obviously just
resigned as an outsider everything that
is done with the Planning Commission is
done in public and that's why I'm
speaking about this now because these
emails that keep going back and forth
they're disturbing to me I don't know
what the emails are you I don't either
because I haven't had a connections but
Stephan's been emailing Planning
Commission members and I haven't been
receiving the correspondences because I
didn't have an email address and then
when I asked for the emails from um
Samira the clerk I'm given like the the
date of the email but there's no text
and there's no body so I just got an
email from Stefan that was sent to the
board and the Planning Commission about
this attorney statement and I'm sharing
this with the public right now that's
yes and why don't you ask
way wait the way to share it with the
public would be to attach it to an
agenda for the next meeting no um if
it's not something that we are voting on
I am making an announcement is what I'm
doing um and I'm sorry the next agenda
would be in in uh January that's too
late it's too late it's total water
under the bridge by then well and you're
assuming you you would not want another
meeting in December no I don't have time
for that it's peak season right now I
you know I I just need to say something
I don't really have time for more
meetings either and I would really like
to get through this agenda so we can
look at this question there which I
think is really important to get out to
the public so we can stay on track with
our schedule for the master plan you
know the meet public meetings and the
proposals yes so I have some um
printouts that I made for all of you you
got those I didn't have time like to
make
ation make a motion we haven't approved
the agenda
yet well so we're not I'm not gonna um
I'm not going to consider your motion so
Suzanne this is not the Forum to get any
no don't like me Page look um I will I
will agree to move on because I'm just
gonna get your your heels dug in and
your obstructionism I am what I'm saying
is there can be no decision made at this
I know I'm making an announcement is
what I'm making and you you you
interrupted me you didn't let me finish
my train of thought and I can't Toler
that tolerate that from you you're the
you're the mayor you're representative
of the body as a member on this Planning
Commission but you have no business
interrupting me I'm the chair well the
problem is you are doing things okay
let's not argue you don't get the last
word agend the public knows about it
because I'm talking about it we're not
making decision we're not taking any
action they I don't need to um agendize
an announcement I'm
sorry I I feel like you do but you don't
this is my body here that I need chair
if you want to be the chair you can be
like Mary Bach and get the lawyer to
tell you you can be the chair suan okay
let move why angry why are you
projecting these things because I think
has been treated very poorly by you I've
tried to contact you privately with text
letting you know what um what
um ordinances were broken and you have
Stonewall I'm not going to respond to
you suzan that's why I'm not
professional right I don't care no we we
faed with a lot of really unprofessional
things coming from matter right now what
we need to do is get on with this
meeting and if you know the other
complaints we so do we have a um do you
want to approve the agenda as is
written I'll make a motion to approve
the agenda written I will
second all those in
favor
okay so first order of business on the
agenda is this
so what do we think about the minutes I
have one
correction what's your corre P it is on
page it had to do with the motion for
the public meeting oh on page it's five
of the packet it's under item number
two and it says uh the motion was made
made that held about all changes to the
June 25th draft it should say the June
21st
draft June 21st
do you have any
other points that you'd like to bring
up have sorry
just okay so with that change in mind on
page two of the minutes changing 25th to
21st draft of the master
plan um do we have a motion to approve
the minutes
I'll make a motion to approve the
minutes second all those in
favor to
EV I said with that change oh good thank
you if you want to run the meeting
you're welcome to sorry I didn't hear it
um okay
that the way
um actions and presentations changes to
the housing element discussed at the
um Planning Commission work
session so there are a few um verbiage
changes basically to some of the
language
here yeah and they've been highlighted
in
blue I have a big change I'd like to
make but I don't know if it should if we
should let this go to the public first
before so we can hear more from them
before you know I start getting into it
um so with that said do you like the
changes that are highlighted or stripen
under line and blue cultural
heritage page five page six um let see
it's page n of the page 10 a
packet down the middle there are you
finding it l yeah okay page 11 okay page
11 and then on 10 there's a one little
word that yeahor cult
Heritage don't remember oh it's was it
it was just
spelling page
14 um adding and groundwater
management which I think is a good that
was something you brought up that was a
good
point on page 14 of packet yeah right
and then
um page 15 is the policy there's an
added policy um housing policy
29 and again I believe you brought that
up the noise I was concerned about the
noise issues so okay I think that pretty
much extent listen to
the yeah and then other than that I
think there's a a lot that needs to be
cut out of page on page seven of the
packet and the Preamble is really
lengthy and
it's a little wordy
um I also had concerns about the the
blight I I want to know where the blight
is in this town are we why are we using
that word is there specific
Redevelopment plans that we're setting
up for is it the old school building is
it the sewer Pond property or is it
people's personal houses you know
there's some reason to include um you
know these numerous references to that
but I guess I want to hear from the
public I think you know and I mean if we
present this this to the public
hopefully it's not going to be just a a
d that one um which one are you looking
for like oh it's throughout
this one because we could add that to
the questions yeah exactly so I'll be
looking for that I don't this isn't my
um mark up copy this is a new copy from
the packet my my marked up copy is in my
vehicle and the far
outside um so I think we talked about
Redevelopment and info
infill
is Rehabilitation of existing homes
that's um that's not it um demolition
also housing six preserve and protect
stabilize the character inv visibility
so that's something page 10 there's
something
there neighborhood
environmentals I don't think BL is in it
yeah but that's essentially what that
means require Demolition and
Rehabilitation
that's I think that
was did we address that at the last
meeting
concern about what did that actually
mean so there's there's some like
contradictory statements here but again
if we want to bring that up in the
survey and use it as maybe find out
where people are with this um it shows
up demolition shows up the first time is
on page 10 of the packet yeah that's
what iing six there it shows up five
times
M but I'm thinking is if you want to do
a question it'd be good to pull language
exactly that mimics exactly so do you
want to address that when we get to the
question part because I'm not saying
that I'm changing this at this point and
we were just looking at the changes that
were made in the last meeting so um do
we just approve these little changes in
blue that were approved at the or
discussed at the last
meeting you want to make a motion to
that effect yeah does someone want to
make a
motion um okay so I'll make a motion to
accept the um
um well here's this is interesting
there's a housing policy question mark I
did that because I don't know where it's
going to go okay so this is not the
final draft so it's okay to leave it
like that right this was just for this
tonight so um I'll make a motion that we
accept the changes that were discussed
in the work session and presented at
um meeting Planning Commission meeting
as um um written in the the packet
here see as present it tonight in the
packet
second
um okay all those in favor I I all those
opposed okay um okay so that takes care
of
um item number
one number two is discussion of survey
language so this was a survey
that um administrator win at the last
moment at the last meeting said that he
has a Survey Monkey program that the
town bought and we might as well use
it um so this was a survey
um dealing with the housing portion of
the comprehensive plan to um kind of
Identify some of the potential questions
or um that we have um and how the town
would like
to um or the town's people you know just
bringing things to people's attention
and find out what their desires desires
are um by answering this
survey
so uh tonight we were going to look at
the questions that have been the survey
so far as created by set win and see if
there's something we want to add to it
or expand on it um
[Music]
to tailor it a bit
more I thought maybe s sure go ahead um
I thought we might have possibly
add just looking through the the housing
plan are you in favor of encouraging
accessory accessory dwelling units that
may be restricted as long-term rentals
but affordable
leases I thought that was kind of
a important question for people to okay
look at so that's not on here no I this
would be a these are two things like
okay so you've typed it out there yeah I
just Ted let's just um write it down for
the time being here and we can amend the
wording if need be um could you repeat
that okay I took that right from the
housing plan are you in favor of
encouraging accessory dwelling units
that may be restricted as long-term
rentals with affordable
bases adus
just and faor encouraging adus
right that may be
restricted as long-term rentals with
affordable bases and that's direct
wording from the housing plan
okay
okay um just thought that was important
because some people think adus might be
short well because they're looking at a
way to make some money so they can stay
in their house maybe by you know so it
would give them and that could either be
a yes no or yes no
discuss okay okay they have you know an
idea why they didn't okay like that I
think it would be good to hear okay the
one thing I wanted to add was affordable
leases the town really has a hard I'm
not sure the town can can do anything
about what people charge well that's
directly from our housing plan so then
we i' have to I'd have to read the
Contex of the housing plan because that
uh I just don't we can't regulate that
so do you have do you have the where
that came out of with hous plan well
probably you know Lynn the way that you
can um affect affordable leases is you
make sure the size of the house is small
enough that you just can't charge very
much for it and that's where the town
could weigh in is they could restrict
the size of these adus so instead of
being 900 foot house like is recommended
which is quite large eight no I think it
was nine wasn't it I think excuse me I I
didn't see this in the housing policy I
just did a search for it but it looks
like they struck uh which can include
reducing minimum lot sizes and
affordable leases but then in page 11
policy number question
mark um
that's where I got the wording from
encourage approaches such as do you see
that reducing minimum lot sizes and
encouraging this as policy question mark
so maybe we need to sprad with
affordable leases out of there it's the
town
really yeah I think that was you know
again kind of targeting towards
affordable housing and trying to so the
way the town
can
um affect the cost of housing is just to
make sure it's not too large of a home
yeah you know that's maybe the way that
the town can do it they're not saying
you can't charge money for it they're
saying um it's only going to be this big
maybe it should just be um in the
wording in this questionnaire restricted
as long-term affordable rentals because
I noticed that the word affordable is
Contin
on through policy 7
on so maybe we just you know on on that
questions strike leases and just call it
affordable long-term affordable rentals
okay so we just approve the changes but
doesn't mean that we can't go back and
um but we definitely want to know what
the public thinks even though this
wording is in here right so we can leave
the wording in with the no here that we
might need to work on that well I think
we should change it on the questionnaire
uh that may be restrictive as long-term
affordable rental and consistent with
the rest of it how about encourage
approaches such as reducing minimum lot
sizes reducing square footage of adus
you know so you can talk
about but that be a question you could
you could add in here yeah I did also
think it might be good to add in another
element from that plan and support the
development of a range of housing
options as may be appropriate in
different parts of the community
including but not limited to small homes
accessory dwelling units town homes live
work units and limited small scale
apartments or
Min okay that was a policy too right
that's another polic which number was
that let me see if I can do a search for
it I think Condominiums was a new word
but
it that it looks like it's on page
12 policy
11 I was say policy
11 what did
[Music]
small
accessory that's kind
ofing small homes accessory ding units
small accessory draing units Town H home
so what you're doing is you're kind of
talking about scale you know the
size um the size of develop the size of
these units you because whether it be
home or Adu right that was brought up so
much in the you know when people made
comments so they don't want to see giant
houses but they realize there's a
housing shortage and how do
you you know how do you approach that
without with staying in scale of what
the town already is maintaining the
character of the
town okay so I'm wondering um
I'm almost wondering when we before we
put the survey out would you pass it
through the town attorney to make sure
that
our you know we aren't making any
mistakes like oh you can't say that or
you can't limit it that way or or I
guess we have to finish our work here
before we go that far I'm sorry sorry I
kind of jumped in on it maybe we should
start at the beginning and go through
each of the questions
okay um I do want to jump in as well
though is I'd be curious to know from
people what kind of density they want to
see here I mean we're talking about
increasing density it's like and then we
talk about gentle density but I'm not
sure what that really means and I'm not
sure I want to know from people how
close they want to live with their
neighbors because I think a lot of this
housing plan has to do with infill
development and um reducing lot size
adding adus and and this is
all going to create a situation where
people are living more closely together
and I'd like to know um how people feel
about that I mean do we limit it to
certain parts of town do we limit it I
mean is it just all over the place you
know how are we doing this type of
development and what do you see that
relating to there see I kind of think
that year that policy housing
11 is is a good way to go at that
because Suzanne I don't know not sure
how you would create a
question with answers because this is so
variable across
town I mean maybe if the question had to
do with setbacks do you are you in favor
of reducing setbacks to allow denser
housing well our setbacks are pretty
small reduced as they are and six feet
side yard setb you know or five foot
side yard set back six foot rear yard
set back in the back lot for a house
that's pretty reduced and so do people
want to be and that's for accessory
buildings that are limited to a 16 foot
height do people really want to see that
kind of development with more houses in
it and so that's what how do we ask the
public that question question there's a
question here in this document what do
you see for housing and neighborhoods in
the next 20 years and then you could
have some you know because people might
be I don't know so you might say as to
setbacks as to height as to density as
to whatever you could add more bullet
you could add things so it's a
discussion pump them to right into the
Tex box so it's like um would you like
to see smaller Lots with houses closer
together or or would you like to see
more apartment buildings or do we want
to see some mobile home parks you know
the funny thing is hotus has a lot of
mobile home parks and I think it creates
some very affordable housing situations
for people and um you know what do
people want to see
here tiny home developments that's a
nice open question I think for people as
long as people know how to because if
you don't don't get enough people
understanding it you might get answers
from all over the place which would be
cool it might be interesting to see
where people are at maybe we should PR
and then you want to maybe refine it a
little bit more based on the answers
well and as people come to the meeting
you know we can say here are some you
know people's thoughts about what do
they want to see for house and
neighborhood what do you people think
you know we could create a discussion
yeah because it's pretty open-ended and
I think it should be so that we get
creative thinking and we're not sticking
in our box of the Poli the problem is
you're just getting a certain sector of
people coming to meetings it's not we
can't I know I know but what I'm saying
is um so just because people are willing
to come and speak up that's the
direction the town's going to go but I
mean there are people who are homebound
who so how are we going to get this out
to everybody I know we had that
discussion so what K Rose was been she
was the senior center she was yeah are
you referring to this survey or are you
referring to the well the the comments
and discussions based on survey
questions survey responses I think I
think when we talked about Outreach we
were asking C to help with a broader
Outreach than we but that was for the
plan for the draft plan whereas this
right now for the right right but you
can only get it online or people could
come in and pick up a paper one and the
staff could input their answers or we
could print some out and I could drop
them off at the senior center you know
we
could drop them off at the senior
apartments we can L instructions because
they can't they have the survey monkey
has to be in you have to input the
answers in order for Survey Monkey to to
function so they would have to write out
their answers and then the staff would
put them in it can all be anonymous but
it would have to be typed in to get so
that everybody's answers are cated the
same way but that may be one way to
reach out to people who
are do you have um Sam um down at Town
Hall are there people with email
contacts that you know about people who
don't have email contacts or I mean I
guess you have text my gu
but text is the only how many people
have signed up with text oh I don't know
the answer to that off the top of my
head but a lot more than we expected
okay um and those are all in town
residents or they out of town residents
I think out of town residence too yeah
so this survey is only for in town right
I guess oh no they can it has if you
look at Stephan like talked about this
during the work session we want to know
if people live in oh right the first
question answers that so out the town
people can certainly fill it out yeah
Sam is the the town is it possible for
the town to put it on their Facebook
page too oh yeah we can do that we put
it on the web page and we can because a
lot of activity it's just all geared at
digital proficiency proficiency and I do
have a problem with that because I know
people who don't do computer well can
you besides the senior apartments and
the senior center can you think of other
places the surveys could be Dro well we
talked about that with
the oh yeah yeah and the thing is you
don't want multiple one person to be
filling out 10 surveys and you know that
kind of thing does happen so you know
excuse me one person filling out 10
surveys oh you know so does Survey
Monkey when you're doing it online it
restricts you to only one one time that
you can take yeah I think Stephan had it
set up so that couldn't do it multiple
times from the same computer from
different computers I think just the
same email address so Survey Monkey goes
to email addresses well you email you're
I think I think you he and the other one
could ask people you know give us your
email address if you want to be um
contacted and then somehow he said write
in town out of town in this second and
last question so in a way he was using
that so the same person couldn't just
keep doing it again and I mean I I go to
senior lunch thing at and help out there
and I can just at one of the lunches
pass one out to each person and then say
you know bring this back the next senior
lunch or fill out here afterwards and
then I drop it's just it's like this is
these surveys just go out to people in
social networks and what do we do about
people who are not in the social
networks and I mean that's why at one
point when I was talking to Tom Wills he
said you could have had a door knocking
campaign in the beginning of this plan
stuff because that's the way you really
get for people um you know P hang tags
from door knobs or or whatever you
know but so I think
anyway idea of taking paper copies to
the senior center yeah that's only one
group of social people but I think some
of it's word of mouth too because if
it's out in social media people say have
you seen there's this survey and if you
can't do it the town you can go in and
fill it out on paper the town can have
some of the counter or or you can call
the town and have and mail it to you if
you like you know if we make that an
option or Sam is there way it
could um somehow in a short way be put
on top of the um utility bills the town
bill that get sent out we have a small
amount but it depends on we have a small
amount of characters on there um you put
something on there but a lot of it's
going to depend
on they might have already sent off Bill
stuff this month so then you'd have to
wait we can double check with step in
tomorrow just to be sure it okay so but
you know if they want to call Town Hall
suppose they can ask for a copy the
snail mail to them they like if it's
hard to get down here up you know
sometimes people don't come in would it
make sense to just put on the door you
know what your post like we we have a
survey for the housing blah blah blah
please come in oh like we do for the
Public Notices so this is what it look
yeah or just so they're like oh I'll
come in and fill that out
so do something like that and that might
get more people to versus drop in and
just ask
so um what what do you think about just
going through this item by item so we
can see and then add
in you think about
thatan um sure
okay so is the first one yeah what's
your relationship okay I think people
should say if they live out of town um
so the I'll read it so so people who
might be watching know what we're
talking about um the first survey
question that we're considering is town
housing and neighborhood survey what is
your relationship to the
town
um I live in
town um number one I own property in
town but live outside of town I have a
town address but live in the
county
so um
I really think the
only other people that would be out of
town that would be relevant are in the
growth area that we've
identified um because people who aren't
in that growth
area I I don't think they need to be
telling us how we need to grow it's
really the people who are living in this
town um experiencing the impacts are the
ones that I'd like to hear from I mean
there's this swath out by 133 that we
have a growth area planned out there I
don't know if it's for annexation or
whatever
but yeah unless they all get to be aate
residential and Hobby Farms um I don't
want to hear people out there saying you
guys all need to live with your density
there and we don't want it out here but
that would be interesting to hear
actually so so do you feel when these
three questions it's covered or should
we add something else in
well living three miles out of town if
they don't have in town address they
would people might not know what that
growth area means
any so I'm wondering do you think if
people live out of town they would just
skip this question and keep going just
you know what you could say either other
or um
other or they can um write in the area
that they live in you know I don't know
how you enter that in survey monkey but
um they can you can have a box we're
doing yeah yeah I think that would
probably be the best if we're getting
encourage right in for other things um
would that be a text box just for I mean
maybe wants to put their address just
just say other
explain or something like
that the question is what is your
relationship to the
town so other
your father be other and then then you
have a text box for them to type it in
yeah
so what do you want to see for housing
and neighborhoods in the next 20 years
so that's you could say higher density
High livingo living closer together keep
it the same other you know you could
have that fill in thing I think on all
of these well yeah some of them are yes
no or whatever but I'm wondering Lynn's
proposed question could be turned could
be added on like I think ly you were
suggesting that on this
one um
examples yeah but that's
um that that was one thing that was
really frustrating to me um with all the
workshops we
did things were like too worked out and
it's like well that's not where I be but
we were only given the option to answer
things within the context of the the
topics that were presented you know on
the bulletin boards in the the dots that
we were supposed to put up on the wall
so it was almost like some pred
decisions going in there with housing
study actually and that's why I like
this being more open-ended people can
write whatever they want yeah actually
that would be a great
idea uh what would you like to see as
the next survey hang on a second what
are the topics you like to see for this
um what are the concerns that you I
don't know well but I think they that
this question kind of people could put
in whatever they want to see so um as
say put in there freefor all it let
people know that they can get creative
with that one maybe you know right
because then if we have the one from
policy 11 do you support the development
of range that's kind of a yes no and
then you it could be yes no in a text
box for comments because there's so many
things listed here accessory dwelling
live work unit small scale apartment so
it could be yes no and then text box
comments or it could just be
comments and what about neighborhoods I
mean what what does that mean I can see
housing but what is
neighborhoods I mean Pion is kind of
like one big neighborhood in a way
because we're so small so what does
neighborhoods actually mean
here I would say uh up on Pan-American
as a
neighborhood yeah I mean I think you
know like our HOA the neighborhood and
there's a lot of emphasis on
neighborhood with having a front porch
so that you engage with people walking
by um you know a lot of people really
like looking at the Landscaping people
do and identifying different you know
plants as they go along um and not I'm
not just talking about our place but I
do that all through
town and it's really fun so the town I'm
I don't mean to sound but the town is
not an HOA I mean so that you can't run
the town like an HOA but what you do see
that I've noticed in Crawford is that
there's like
a nicest front yard award that they
might have in the summer I've seen that
before like the best nicest landscape so
they do things instead of um making
rules for people they um and that's more
of maybe kind of a town function where
you don't have restrictions where people
have to you know everybody's house has
to be gray or Earth Tones um but I think
this is pretty just like do you
enjoy do you enjoy like what
walking down Third Street is like on
Second Street on Fourth Street Fifth
Street and I think there should be a com
box here I think people when they hear
walkable they're going to think
sidewalks I think you can walk in the
street because there's not a whole lot
of traffic instead of
um I I don't know I just think on any of
these there could be a a comment box do
the people up in Apple Valley have a
problem with no sidewalks up there do
you
think I think some of the people people
who walk up there there's safety issue
the walk you know the safe walk streets
that went on there were a lot of issues
especially around Apple valet park is
there enough room for sidewalks would
they be willing to give up their front
yard you know people in general didn't
want sidewalks what they wanted was more
a way to identify walking corridors like
maybe with um those tubes you put up you
know when you go
Apple Valley Park and that and a lot of
the schools walked that and their
concern was safety and nobody really
wanted more babing and more maintenance
but they wanted a way to keep it safe
for the kids and that was great idea
well it probably would have been good
not to put the elementary school out at
the old high school if we really were
truly so getting back to this question
maybe just take out walkable because if
that's an issue do you like
neighborhoods
let people say what they like about
neighborhoods do you like do you like
neighborhoods or what what do you like
what do you like about typical
neighborhood what appeals what do you
like about neighborhoods or what do you
like to see what makes a neighborhood
for you or something like that but we
have to be sure that people don't get to
well I mean they can say what they want
what about what makes a neighborhood
enjoyable yeah um um I don't know maybe
we need to rephrase I just think this
one we're going to start getting into
sidewalks and the and stuff yeah it gets
too much of an issue and and we start
closing people's minds a little bit and
distracting them with maybe we could
just say what do you enjoy about the
neighborhoods you walk through yeah oh
what makes a neighborhood enjoyable what
makes an appealing
neighborhood what makes a neighborhood
appealing
what do we do side what do we want what
do you like about yeah what makes what
what appeals to you what is a turn off
to
you just say what makes a neighborhood
appealing or not I wonder if this should
have though a list of things that will
trigger people and then other because it
to me it's too open to leave it as a
text box people don't like to have to
make I don't when I'm taking a survey
want to have to answer yeah you know
individually whereas I think what makes
a neighborhood appealing Yeah question
mark and then under it would be trees
such as trees um variation in structures
safety
safety U trying to think what else um
varation and
architecture um I mean it does kind
of landscaping
land
trees
um not having an RV parked across the
sidewall landscape yeah and a variety um
privacy fences all over the place or o
porches yeah so and then they could put
in other but it seems like that would
job I like walk through a neighborhood
it has to be maybe what
um what what is in the statutes about
what the zoning code can are we it's a
comprehensive plan so it kind of deals
with chapter 16 which is our land use
code I know it's called the zoning code
but it's technically the land use code
ask
Leslie and so that's kind of the
Dominion of the comprehensive plan so
it's the size the bulk
density um what else you know the
statute when you look at the statute
saying that the comprehensive plan can
cover certain things or should cover
certain things maybe we need to be
working in the context of
that
um I think if you say a variety of
architecture that gets to difference in
Heights right difference in architecture
I um I mean it's
like but I mean that's just more kind of
like for amusement and aesthetic senses
but you had to be careful about going
down that pathway
because
um you know are we going to start
regulating what are we ask what are we
looking for I'm wondering if so Stephan
zeroed in on Third Street and he was
talking about lives there right but he
was talking about the streets that come
off of third just like the ones that
come off a second
and so really was thinking about the
older you know well mixed use what makes
those neighborhoods interesting but why
are we asking I don't think there are
any more interesting in my neighborhood
frankly no your neighborhood would be
part of it because I'm thinking the big
the two main arteries through town
second and third is what sounds like he
was thinking about the
streets that cross you know second third
and fourth a little I guess I have a
question why are we asking this question
I was kind of wondering that you know I
mean what what are we going to get from
it so maybe that's a good point maybe we
should go back to some of the policies
and just say does this do you agree with
this right because that's really what
we're trying to get at for them to look
at the housing element because I think
this is so open-ended it's like you know
I think it was just kind of to me it
felt like a starting point like a way to
SK the wheels our minds so we can start
discussing things so was kind of a
starting a jumping off
point
okay so maybe we want to look at pulling
one of the policies in
here especially like going
towards the goals housing two and
policies 8 through
okay so you're looking at the goal
enhance and maintain the character of
P's existing residential neighborhoods
is that the one you were looking at
that's one need to accommodate infield
development um so what are the goals
with that
[Music]
goals so with there questions such as if
you look at housing policy two promote
the use of alternative zoning techniques
and mechanisms for a mix of housing
types within residential neighborhoods
you know I don't know I mean could you s
would it be an easier survey to say do
you agree with the statement oh that
might be better yeah because I me this
is to people are going to go out it's
like so sophisticated I don't think the
normal person would know what that means
I don't I don't even quite understand
what that would look like you know the
mix of um The W no the mix of housing
types for instance I mean did we just do
that mean I'm so visual I almost have to
see an example of what that means so
it's hard to answer that and know what
you're answering this mix of housing
opportunities for firsttime families of
forign G
so so wait let's just go back a minute
did we decide n no we haven't finished
that one about it this typical one I
thought we we decided it's either to NX
it or put in one of the policies that
kind of get gets that
question because the point of this is to
have people look at the yeah housing
element I don't know if people will read
it but we'll make it available to look
at the element but maybe there are
certain things we would like them to
actually think about an answer I mean it
might
be policies know this make you feel like
is it red yellow or
green like yes like on a scale of one to
10 what is this policy what do you feel
about this that would be very
interesting where do you stand from a
scale of one to 10 and then agreement
yeah that would be actually that would
be a great way to do it
it's like we do that with the whole
polic all the policies that we've done
well I think
we this one's most but some of them are
they kind of go at the same question and
so we could just consolidate that you
know like all these policies actually we
could see which ones are the most
popular and the least popular we can
kind of get a feeling from people where
they kind of the direction they'd like
things to be going right well
I to some extent but we kind of need
these you know we we need to have work
with Del un reading one policy housing
one that the staff need to be aware of
working with Delta County private water
companies and developers to develop
housing units designed in price
for County see I don't feel like the
survey should
be is maybe throwing them out you know
throwing it out it's more trying to get
a feel how do do people feel like
some of these policies the goals and
policies are getting at their needs
their
20year uh window for how they like to
see housing be developed and maintained
what is the Ping census tract is down
here a small relatively permanent
geographic area within a county that is
used to present data from the Census so
if you work in hodus are you working
close enough to ponia I mean to
I mean I don't
understand work with water companies to
develop housing units
designed and working what what does that
have to do with the water companies in
Delta County with a focus on those
living and working in
Pia in Delta County so what what do we
actually want
to that's we're back to these question
why don't we go back to these questions
and see if we can find a policy that
kind of would mimic
gets at what these questions were're
trying to get at oh work with Delta
County Comm right okay developers she
develop housing units designed and
placed for employees living and working
in Delta
County specifically in Pia I
know are I don't think there are very
many um so where are we well we need to
be looking at the policies
under the housing and the goals and
policies and see if we can fit one of
these into this instead of do you what
do you want to see for your neighborhood
um and there's enough of them that
really speak to that that we could
pull and we'd get an idea or and then
you can always have no change you know
what if people don't want to see any
change at all that would be kind of
interesting
to keep it the way is or
whatever oh and that's indifferent
that's what he has that's his
indiffer
indiffer so the fourth one you know just
for example do you like a mix of housing
opportunities for first time home buers
families of four and the elderly select
all that apply it seems like the average
person would check them
all right and so I think there's a
policy that addresses
that and um or how none of the
above I'm not sure I'd check any of
these
frankly well I would check them all
simply because the mixed housing that is
so needed to have very a variety of
houses as maybe to lab one two or three
what's most important to you that would
be better to me that would that would be
more instructive rate so I don't know
what that means I mean does it means you
could have a huge house next door to you
that's out of scale with a little house
that you live in because we need mixed
opportunities for people with big
families but then that's what we have
now in this you really Town we've got
such a mix We they're generally small
houses in this town and
so you know people kind of live all in
the kind of in in very um similar sizes
I think I we're not getting the huge
things like the 2,000 something square
foot the housing study showed that most
of the houses are three bedroom and that
that a young family can't afford to buy
these houses like we have they're not
whereas a firsttime home buyer would
probably like to have a one bath two-
bedroom small hat like Shirley okay you
know more of a
Shirley so how do you a house that has
an Adu on lot too because that's going
to drive up the price of housing um I to
me that all will you got to have a mix
you know that's the whole that's why I
like this promote the use of alternative
zoning techniques and mechanisms provide
a mix of housing types within
residential neighborhoods which polic
that's I'm still I'm still zoned in on
policy housing too and that's was a big
part of the housing needs assessment but
so my question though is I are we still
going to have R1 are we this isn't
changing any of that it kind of is
because if you have adus everywhere it's
no longer R1 that R2 it may be R1 based
on how the ordinance is written yeah so
I mean so so they're different things
there's the size of units um and then
there's also the zoning which talks that
the density that you can put on the
property so there's a size of things and
there's a density right all that and so
two people understand but you don't mix
zoning classifications together it has
to be orderly right right so but do
people understand that I mean in this
question does it what do they what do
they think when they say mix of housing
opportunities is the average person
going to understand that that means you
can't have an apartment building next to
a single family residential house no I I
think that other one what was the what
was the other policy you were you read
Lynn that had the
condos what number was that remember I
think we put it in there it is it's
housing 11 so let me just support the
development of a range of housing
options as may be appro appropriate in
different parts of the community
including but not limited to small homes
accessory dwelling units town homes live
work units and limited small scale
apartments or condominiums that to me is
gets it that's a better policy to put
out there to ask people you do you agree
with this statement yes no so how about
you say in in differently zoned parts of
the community so they know that it's not
random like this mish mash it's like
planned
well to me
that's it's probably the underlying
thing with a town any development
without with anything being built you
have to meet the zoning
requirements yeah but I mean I so do
people
that you can have it are they going to
think that it's all just I mean I don't
know how sophisticated the the
the survey responses are going to be I
mean do they really understand well to
me it's it's kind of an open question
are you and how are we going to
interpret their responses that way and
okay wait I have an
idea um so we are on question number
three do you like the mix of what if we
um
said with that do you support that one
um up there and then in said how would
you rate the following one equals most
important for least important first time
home buyers families of four more the
Elder did you go one to
four want to add more are you thinking
more we could add more I'm just trying
to
um so it would be support the
development of a range of housing
options as may be appropriate in
different parts of the community
including but not limited to small homes
accessory dwelling units town homes live
work units and limited small scale
apartments or
Condominiums um and then we could also
okay let's just leave that how would you
rate the following one equal most
important and four and we can have more
ratings least for first time home buyers
families with four or more the
elderly no that doesn't work there we
have to rate
the what what do you support oh it
within yeah accessory dwelling units
more Town Homes more live work
spaces small apartments yeah yeah and
let them right rate them yeah because
these three topics that are here first
time homeone buyers families at bore and
the ERS there are like three different
classifications so there's firsttime
home
buyers second homeowners F small
families large families so we there's
like this is yeah what do you call it
like so just take out
those yeah take those out and then if we
say how would you rate the following and
then it would
be small homes what's mostos to
important to you yeah how what's most
important r one to four one
to many we have small homes adus we have
Town
Homes I wonder if people know what a li
work unit is well you know if the more
people I mean I support people being
able to work from home but you can only
turn 25% of your house that's why I
wonder if people would understand what
that means and the more people working
from home means the more the less
bedrooms there are for people to live
right so maybe a single person can
afford to have a five-bedroom house
because they can pay for it because it
becomes their Works Space too and that's
kind of contradictory to what it's like
the
whole Str Str thing we've just taken
what 30 houses out of circulation now
for permanent residents so and yet we're
saying how how many how many houses did
the housing study say that we should be
adding in the next I think it said 100
the next five years so that would be a
good question is if we were to if we had
to add a hundred units in the next five
years where do you want to see him go
this town see density increasing the
boundaries of the Town seeing some
development I'd like to know how people
feel about that if you increased density
where you because it seems like we're
kind of creating plan for density here
but I want to know how the community
feels about it you know where do you
want to see housing units go how do you
want to see it happen tiny home a zoning
for a tiny home
development um you know um where you
have more houses but you limit the size
um you know do you want to see a
subdivision going would you like to see
another apartment building mobile home
park would you like to see it all happen
as or you know more density in town it
would be really interesting to see what
people would like to you know how this
community would physically
grow well this question gets to some of
that thinking that we have to like put
in there in the beginning housing policy
too where does this come from and plan
that you know this question housing
policy
to um
not indicates but what's another word
sounds but not sounds oh you're looking
for a I'm looking for a word housing
policy two and we can say which page um
indicates give me a word proposing
proposes oh is that what you're looking
for yeah yeah I'm just like saying
housing policy 2 page blah blah blah
proposes supporting the development of
blah blah blah blah and then how would
you rate the following one being the
most important four being the least
small homes Adu Town Home Live works
Town Homes live work units so maybe we
need one to five um limited small scale
apartments and Condominiums because that
way then it comes right from our policy
and is policy 11 policy
11 was that that one supporting the
development yeah of a range of housing
options May what p is it's on 12 of the
back there's like we'll have to get it
for the it's on page well why don't we
just say housing policy
11 format of so maybe these questions
all relate to the policies not just
Loosey Goosey questions um not uh I'm
just thinking out loud so I might not I
be um what about
should it be based off the goals or the
policies so housing we have
seven goals for housing
here um and we have a ton of policies
let me see encourage building and
construction methods provote energy
preserve protect stabilize the character
and visibility residential neighborhoods
andares I'm trying to just read them see
if that would be possible
preserve identify recognize protect
unique replaceable historic and cultural
heritage yeah I guess that's um I guess
that's
too um some of them are a little it's
too nebulous it's hard to even
understand so that's why but there's
some I mean this is like important to
think about do people like the idea more
of small homes adus like a rating scale
might be you know how do you rate things
and then there can be us no answers you
know do you agree with this policy but
my feeling is that we're helping them
understand the goals and policies we put
forth right and that we're getting
specific answers for
those so um I think a lot of times what
people do is I mean I don't know how it
is now with all the new people moving in
but
you know it's expensive to live here and
the rates the utility rates keep going
up and up and up and so sharing housing
is important to people because they can
split the trash bill they split the
water bill so the more and more people
you get living in your house the cheaper
it becomes to live here
um that's California yeah so but at the
same time it doesn't really put more
money into the water system because it's
just more people living off the same
base rates
basically so I'm just trying to I'm just
trying to sorry I'm thinking about but
you can't tell people they can't live
with nonf family members it's that's not
well that's a law yeah you're I think
you're drilling down I'm trying to yeah
get my mind around whereas this is help
me again what your question was ly I'm
trying to figure out why my mind went in
that direction um mean what I was prop
proposing so I was proposing that in
these questions we say housing policy 11
proposes supporting the development of a
range of housing options blah blah blah
blah blah how would you rate the
following one being most important five
being least important and then we have
small homes Adu Town Homes lior units
limited small scale apartments or
condomini okay so you know know what you
could say maybe maybe give it a context
like if the town uh wish to see a 100
units added to its housing stock in the
next five years how would you like to
see that the P split basically you know
so that's kind of what so people have an
understanding about what we're talking
about you
know um but I think what's the context
why are you asking this the element here
is to get it all of that the housing
element because you can't be
prescriptive about how you're going to
do those hund tools this housing element
is getting into all the different things
staff need to think about when people
come in asking to build a a property or
convert a property well it has to do
with where codes are going to be use but
that's but that the housing element is a
much bigger 30,000 ft view which then
will look at whether zoning needs to be
fixed but if you start asking people how
do you want to get 100 homes in here
that is getting way too uh Regulatory
and not the 30,000 foot how how do you
want things to be thought about over
time that's what i' like that's and I
think people need to know what we're
actually talking about are they talking
about we're GNA there's going to be Arco
subdivision going up with all those Taps
because Shay said that we don't even
need to add all these housings into town
to for that housing study but the
housing study just said looking at when
they interviewed the different
businesses and whatever that you know in
order to support workers and the growth
that it looks like we would need 100
housing un it doesn't mean we're g to be
doing that and we don't want to I don't
think give people that idea because
that's just like this could be a Target
but it may be you know the economy
crashes we we just say we don't need
more housing but if we did need more
housing what would you like to see it be
an Adu small houses town houses
condominium se's questions here I think
if 100 people say small houses and five
people say
adus well then the town can look at that
or you know and the planing commission
can look at that and say what are the
most important things for the town to
support it looks out of 600 people
answered this question and 100 said this
that gives us a scale it doesn't mean so
you're talking about the types of what
types of hous the type of Housing and
that then determines but people have to
understand that the town's not going to
be building this housing it's just what
happens with developers what happens to
come here well and I mean when anytime
there's a change in you know some has to
there's a variance know that they have
to come before the planing commission or
they have to go for a permit to the
building
department so um if there was going to
be a townhouse or condominium that I
would think that that's something
unusual that we're not you know I don't
know where that would be and the land
would be I think that would be a bigger
deal that somebody will bought a lot and
built a small house it wouldn't be a
variant that would be zoned for that use
but this housing element is not
prescribing how things are going to be
zoned it's what the town need the
overarching view of how do we want our
town to look right we're we're going to
have housing come and we're going to
have housing go we we need to
accommodate very people which is why the
goals are the way they are so I don't
think you want to get prescriptive in
questions so this
is do you think the way we have it
stated is too prescriptive read it again
um no I think that again it's it's the
general um let me look at that
one okay I'll read it again and this is
what you've written right that well
you're you're using support the
development of arrangement right no
let's have do you like a mix of housing
I'm doing that okay and
walkable the walkable neighborhood I
thought we decided to just leave that
what do you want to see for housing and
neighborhoods in the next 20 years and
just let people go dos oh yeah with
number two with number two well you want
to see what say that again what do you
what do you want to see for housing and
neighborhoods in the next years and
that's just an openend question for the
text
box the came up with your question then
number three do you like the typical
loable neighborhood that many of the
neighborhoods of Third Street
enjoy we decided oh yeah that's where we
decid to get rid of that and do do you
want to see housing for neighborhoods in
the next 20 years what do you want to
see what do you want to see so now so
you're you're substituting two for three
is that what you're
saying um what do you want to see number
two leave it in and number three take up
and okay got you and then number four is
this one we've been discussing so I'll
read it again housing policy 11 proposes
supporting the development of a range of
housing op options as may be appropriate
in different parts of the community
including but not limited to small homes
accessor dwelling units town homes live
work units and limited smallscale
apartments or condominums how would you
rate the following one most important
five equals least important small homes
adus accessory dwelling town homes live
work units limited small scale
apartments or well condos and town homes
are by they are kind of small anyway
right but some people don't yeah they
don't want to see them in their
neighbors well there if it's not zone
for they won't have them in their
neighbor but it's just kind of an
open-ended question of what do people
what do they want to see so for instance
mobile home parks and manufactured
homes you want you want to add Momo
homes well statute doesn't let you
discriminate against M homes
and manufactured homes there's
specifically language in there saying
that it helps keep the cost of housing
down but you're going to get people
saying oh I don't want to see that in my
neighborhood so I
mean and I understand that
but but that's why we have zoning that's
why there's a zone that that's
appropriate but you know that's why
there's some mobile homes scattered
throughout town before they had the
zoning that's how people had it a
relatively inexpensive way to live in in
a mobile
home um and now it now it requires Ying
but I well you could put it in there as
a choice do we want to put do maybe we
ask for percentage how many big homes do
you want to see how many small homes how
many adus would you like to see how many
apartments how many like 50% 20% people
are gonna their minds are gonna I have I
don't think that's I don't think that's
appropriate for something where we're
just going for a general yeah but I just
think this is a little
too
prescriptive in that way um I mean I
think you can take out adus because that
is covered by small homes condos are
covered by small homes apartments are
small homes I don't I think they're very
different small large homes are things
that could go up in the new um like the
estate District where people have a
hobby Farm in town and they can build a
big old home maybe we should say small
family
homes instead of just small homes
because small homes have a place adus
have another place they're the
completely
different yeah small homes they use tiny
homes small homes are different than
tiny homes what if we just say small
family homes so that because we're
talking a lot of people said we don't
want to see big MCM small single family
homes no they could be multiple I mean
then you're limiting you
know many people live you I don't but
we're not I don't think
that we're even thinking about zoning
here because people who do this are not
they don't have a clue okay I guess I'm
just not understanding what you're
thinking I W explain to your mind on
this one I'm I'm not understanding it
would it be better to just have more
broader questions that say you know do
you agree with uh the use of annexations
as an opportunity to expand pay onious
supply of affordable Workforce housing
continue to require pre-annexation
agreements for new construction within
the three mile growth management area as
a condition of getting domestic how
about annexation how about um limiting
lot um infill development how about
making lots smaller in town this is
that's together that's zoning isn't
annexation kind of the same thing but
annexation is a process it may or not
even happen but if you're going to have
annexation you got to consider these
things is this in place of this question
no I was just throwing it out as another
question it's more of a do you agree
with this yes no because
um and just look at them more that way
and so don't rate them I think yours to
rate that one that seems reasonable to
me but I wouldn't want to try to have
everyone be a rating no I don't but I
think bance worthy well that has so many
units in it it's like you know you're
like well I like small homes but I don't
like town homes so how am I going to
answer this well no because and so now
if you rate it you can answer that that
was my thought yeah I think that's
reasonable to do to have a bulleted list
and read them one to four but I think
many could be yes yeah I just think
because we really want people to think
about the content of the housing element
right and do you think this is a good
goal so do you want to add that one in
to I was just throwing that out I mean
think that's good the annexation we
don't have that next we're going
to where are we going to Annex though I
mean that I'm looking at that
future that's that's still the future
and we have these huge processes to go
through to do it I know but what are
what are we I I just think it's so
open-ended I said are people thinking
that we're going to do PE people don't
even know the rules around annexation
that you can't do flag annexations you
have to be contiguous next to the town
you know you have to have a certain
amount of Frontage a bing Town property
before you can anex they can say no I
mean but I don't think they understand
what annexation
means
um
well you could describe it you could say
about if the town
Annex property outside of the existing
Town
limits as an or adjacent as an
opportunity to expand ponia supply of
affordable and Workforce housing and
continue blah blah blah do you agree yes
or no but they have to have permission
from all the property owners they can't
just go and say we're going to anex this
is just an open-ended question of do
they agree that that's how annexation
would mostly be targeted for supp
affortable and Workforce housing um you
know that and that and we could leave
the rest of that there's not a whole lot
of places to go with annexation because
we've been we've had lots turned into
conservation ements here we have out of
town property here
that's that will all come to time we're
not we're not so you're just wondering
find in the sky even if it's not
possible what do you think about it's
not possible I mean I think Delta County
is pushing the town to look at
annexation and what would that look like
and so this would give us an idea of
what you know
otherwise this would give people an idea
that there's a possibility this could
happen do you agree with it or not
because otherwise all of a sudden if we
say oh we just Annex all this property
and people are like what we didn't know
anything about that at least you know
there's a an awareness created that this
is the possibility and if it was if it
did happen what would it would you agree
it could look like this so the out of
town people would want to respond to
that question along and they could and
there could be room for comment too okay
so um and I'm just WR I'm not saying all
because we have how many than sorry well
toal
policies you know I'd like to like not
do too many on the disabilities and
Senior I think there's a lot of emphasis
on that that so we could just compile
those one and there's 25 goal uh
policies and I'm not saying we need to
do all of them no I don't think we do
and I kind of like the connected
neighborhoods to multiple types of
Transportation I
mean like kind of a no-brainer but so
about this annexation
I guess on that question what I see it
doing is helping inform the future land
use map to see what people's desires are
when we look at that component of the
comprehensive
plan let's just see where people I have
to look at the map I mean because to me
it there's a lot of agricultural there
around town so how does a town I mean if
they want to grow and create more
housing I mean that would kind of affect
what we've constrained things by through
the future land use map you know so we
kind of do this listen to the people
this way if you do it in a
survey well to me annexation is going to
be piece instance by instance we have
inh Holdings in town yeah a lot of them
and they have a lot of Acres so who
knows well there's one by the library
what is two acres so it's not one on
Second Street that's it's not surrounded
by property though you can't just engulf
no the Colorado Avenue there behind it
is in the county no not Colorado I'm
thinking Mar son yeah it's not
surrounded by Town property so you can't
just surrounded by sa and by you know it
is that Colorado Boulevard that's not
paid that's County that's not town
anyway anyway about things and we don't
even understand but the thing is this
plan isn't prescriptive it's just saying
there's going to be times when there's
going to have to be annexation regard
for whatever reason and uh do you agree
that you have to get domestic Water
Service in order as a condition get
domestic Water Service yeah so it's not
yeah and maybe annexation isn't even a
good one but let's look at seven for a
second take advantage of all
opportunities that add needed affordable
Force housing the p in the surrounding
area while being mindful of the Town's
desire to avoid over concentration and
overly dense Construction in any one
neighborhood and we could add the water
element and what do you mean by
that I'm just not I'm not overuse of
water
supp oh I'm I guess yeah never I'm not
about that at this
point but I like that one
um while being my I like while being
while being mindful of the towns desire
to avoid over concentration overly
Construction in
anyone because by by pulling some of
these out and putting them in we're get
having people actually read content and
if we pull out maybe four goals or
policies they get to four different
issues yeah you know maybe that's enough
to give people some thought um and it'll
it might you know if they it might get
them to come to the meeting and bring up
say Hey you know I had a real issue with
this and here's why um you know because
this this questionnaire is just kind of
to grease the wheel okay so um sorry um
go okay goal one housing maintain Pion
as a community that is accessible to a
range of income levels and households by
ensuring adequate and affordable housing
options are available
and then so you take a few policies
there to see which is maybe the most
appealing to people is that is that what
you're talking about I'm thinking just
find one because we have seven
goals some have only have two policies
um maybe I think ones that are more
General that give an idea I mean a lot
of these kind of like say take advantage
of all opportunity ities to add needed
affordable and Workforce housing well
that also applies to policy number four
and that also applies
to um policy number six so that's kind
of a good
one
overview it even applies to number three
with handicap and R resent so just
general God I hate to say this
especially since I'm being recorded
forever and ever onto YouTube here
um hi is not a great place to live if
you have medical needs uh you know I
broke my back in 2008 and I just
realized how far away the doctors were
and how far away the doctor's visits
were um you know there's not a lot of
jobs here for low-income res to take
advantage of you're 30 miles away from
Walmart and the less expensive places to
shop I mean so it's kind of funny when
we start seeing Fast Track processes and
incentives to
bring people that need more help you
know to to support I mean I can see
supporting people who are here but why
would you want to grow this town for
people who need cars to travel 30 m i
mean I just some of this stuff is weird
that we even have this in here but these
are people that live here this is an
overarching you need to have a community
that can that people that are
handicapped can find a place to live
exactly but I mean it's like what what
do we really need provide fast tracking
processing and other incentives for
proposed housing developments intended
for persons with so it's not saying this
is restricted to like I mean that's why
like down in Delta like n the hospital
you have some um great housing
opportunities I know people have moved
down there and they're closer to their
doctors they're closer to the shopping
they're closer to the jobs you know and
so I just don't understand how we're
playing on growing here and I understand
I understand but I feel like there's
this like popular thing that everybody
supposed to be doing because it's what's
I mean some of it's required by law it
doesn't doesn't say we have to be doing
things it's like you can't you can't
discriminate against people you can't
say no you can't do it but I just I
don't know what the meaning of this is
one of the things it just doesn't seem
very logical yeah but you know one of
the things I know happens because I know
somebody who looked at buying housing
here and buying housing in hodus and
Crawford and Delta and they looked at
the master plan of all those places and
they decided wow these people are really
looking forward into you know whatever
and so they made their decision on what
area they wanted to buy based upon the
master plans they read because they're
from out of town and they have no idea
they don't live here so I think it's
like to inform here's how we're thinking
it doesn't mean that this is what we're
going to do it's just this is
you know the way we're thinking forward
and you know and and the person that I
know
decided because of it we had a
very bad master plan they decided to buy
in who had a good
master
master so I mean but that's my point my
point is it's to inform like you know
it's great if we say you know like
short-term rentals that we're giving
preference to people who live here
because you get all these investors who
look at oh there's a house for sale we
can turn it into a shortterm bed but now
we have a policy that they're like oops
well that's probably not going to happen
so you know it's it's just to inform how
the community is thinking and the
direction they want to goward and I
think accommodating all types of people
yeah yeah I know we can say we
accommodate all kinds of people but I
just wondering about some of this
language
here all right well let's pick another
you're you're talking about but we but
wait we were
talking asking for
here well we're asking people to just
we're kind of like I said greasing the
wheel for if they want to know more
about you know what this draft is and
more in depth they after doing this they
might say well and and it could be at
the end of this if you need more
information you know go to here on
to.gov or whatever for the draft master
plan yeah that should actually go in the
top I hope yeah because it's at the
bottom are there any policies you
believe should be included any policies
should be removed and why I mean my
point is is it's kind of a way to to
just get them respond thinking about
what we're doing respond to it and
hopefully making them more inquisitive
about what's what else is there so when
it says use annexations an opportunity
to expand pay on supply of affordable
and work for housing and continue to
require pre-annexation
agreements or construction within the
growth management area as a condition of
getting domestic water service so my
question is like we're talking about we
don't want to
sprawl but so why are
why are we talking about an acing so
we're kind of saying that we don't want
to sprawl but we're going to sprawl I
mean we but we're not going to sprawl
because this town is too small but then
we have our two housing pled up there
and the town just turned that into so a
subdivision with four houses and they've
just totally they've totally negated the
fact that the town voted to have higher
densities out there at so this is a tool
that can be used
us every prescriptive thing that happens
doesn't mean that that doesn't make that
a useful tool so in a way it doesn't
even matter what it says and a way it
feels like a massive waste of time
because I'm not quite sure what we're
trying to accomplish us I think what
we're trying to accomplish is to get
people interested and get them to come
and have input because that's what we
keep asking for I see what you're saying
you're just trying to get people aware
that there's like these deep question
curiosity you know say like town is
doing something and if you're curious
answer these question and come to this
some things in there that would really
rile people
up and get them to come with some Pitch
boards and then we'll really
hear we can have a both
ways thought provoking kind of but I
think we should stick with the policies
we put in here because that's what
really pertains to what these meetings
are about so let's choose the most
controversial
ones I don't agree with that well we
want to hear from people but that
doesn't it doesn't if they take a survey
it doesn't have to be controversial well
we just want
to thinking about the extent of what
could happen well yeah or or not happen
that's to me I don't see that either
it's not the extent to what could happen
because this this has multi folks there
is no one thing here it's here are all
the tools to be considered yeah why
don't why don't we just take a a minute
and breathe and look through these uh
the goals housing one and then goals
housing two and
see what we would like because four well
we could do four three okay goal um how
how goal one and goal two
yeah just like look what one which of
the policies appeals to you that you
think would really get people like
interested oh really they're doing that
I need to know more I like
seven seven to I
think
yeah so we could take one from each of
these if if we feel that's not too much
or we could take and then we can we can
policy from each goal yeah and then if
we think that's too much we can
go
um okay you like that one I think that
one kind of takes into the
multi-generational the disabled so seven
is encourage building and construction
strategies methods and practices is that
s oh no policy we're looking at policies
policy
under go
one okay take aour all opportun okay so
you're not goal s your policy set yes
under goal one take advantage of all
opportunities to add needed affordable
and Workforce housing to ponia and the
surrounding area while being mindful of
Pon of the town's desire to avoid over
concentration and overly dense
Construction in any one neighborhood
sure
so could we
say policy housing seven states and then
take advantage BL du agree or disagree
do you might go in that direction seems
like that's a reasonable way
to as people that so
agree they could add a text box under
everyone if they wanted to
explain comment you do text box yeah
text I think text box I mean it's such a
bland statement because there's nothing
controversial about it it's like how can
you disagree with something like this
that's okay you know to me it's this is
what the comprehensive plan is is
looking at so we just try to find
everything that people agree with don't
have to but somebody I mean if I looked
at that and I was a developer I'd say no
I disagree I I think think we should
have dense Construction in this
neighborhood or this neighborhood so
you're you know there there there could
be dis so what does opportunities mean
take advantage of all opportunities what
do you think that means that's wide open
because you don't know what you're going
to have in front of you when the topic
comes
out you want to be open to take
advantage of all opportunities such as I
mean what are you don't want to ask I
mean what are you what are you signing
your life way here for I mean this isn't
you're not this again it's 30,000 foot
things to be considered when housing
there's a proposal for housing somewhere
the staff needs to look at all of these
goals and oh while being mindful of
the's desire to avoid over concentration
so we're talking about perhaps something
in an infill like next door to you and
they'll say well you said in the
comprehensive plan so that's why we're
going to do it and and then that the way
ponia works is it takes forever to for
people to realize what's going on it
takes a long time but if you if you look
at like our property and you know fast
forward and that somebody bought that
four acres and said and initially it was
Zone R5 and they said I'm G to build
five units here so that's taking an
opportunity of the overly large lot in
order for infill or
density um and there are those
opportunities
in as long as they're zoned right well
of course that's the whole thing this is
not we're not dictating zoning we're
just putting out these are the things to
consider and it says mindful the town's
desire to avoid over concentration and
overdense Construction in any one
neighborhood and that should be taken
into consideration yeah impact a
neighborhood okay whatever I guess I'm
just having massive trust issues here
okay um so whatever with that one if you
are happy with
that where you want to put in and then
the next um polic goal and policy are
there is there anything that resonates
for any of us to add in
here I think it's pretty redundant to
the last one so I I don't know let me
read
through well this the is talking about
helping people you know houses that
aging residential
neighborhoods so what about policy
14 that's cont oh under commit to
inclusivity to Ure I'm looking at the
goal oh no diversity of housing I'm just
reading the gold just okay needs the
residents including those for seniors
and
yeah yeah that's a shall discourage
Redevelopment and demolition practices
that significant reduce existing housing
stock in older neighborhoods and that
result in the displacement of very low
but then read policy
15 um it shall ensure that comparable
relocation housing is available in
accordance with Federal
Regulations so you're saying that you
don't want Demolition and then you're
saying well we will demolition things
but we'll we'll make sure we move you
somewhere else no that's not what it's
saying just there are times when you
will have to take something down but you
want to make sure that somebody doesn't
take down everything on my property and
build a 5,000 foot house that's how I
read that made it that way you want to
ensure comparable relocation housing
available in accordance with Federal
Regulations I see people who say we want
you to move I don't see that at all I
see I see it very protecton give you a
house like when you're deciding to build
the dam and and people get relocated and
the government buys their house I don't
see that in this I see it as being
protective proposed regulations maintain
and encourage diversity in housing types
that will support adequate relocation
housing is
required yeah that's what I see I mean I
see houses like particularly there's at
least one on Third Street that I think
it would be very hard if somebody bought
it and had and rebuilt it it would
really be probably more appropriate to
demo it but then to keep it within the
right you know the look and the confine
and maybe not the look you can't
regulate that but within the confines of
that lot size and what was there instead
of like well we're going to put you know
14 town houses here or whatever so what
do what do you mean when you say
comparable relocation housing are you
are you talking about demolishing like
rentals is that why you have to say
relocation housing because when you say
relocation housing it implies that
someone is having to move so something
can be demol I don't think I don't know
that it's necessarily telling somebody
they have to move as much as you want to
make sure you have the housing being put
back in place is comparable and meets
the goals of this housing plan well I
guess there's to me it feels like
there's different ways that this can be
interpreted and I don't like that I
think that that's kind of um that's
going to make different people feel
differently about this because everybody
might see a different meaning to that
statement there's your controversial
statement yeah right there if you want
to put that into like you know yeah if
you think you know that that's going to
bring up because in the future land use
map they were also talking about
Redevelopment and demolition as
well
uh so do you want to do that on policy
15 Town show monitor do you agree or
disagree with the town
because I know you wanted to put some in
there that really kind of brought up
some feisty
feelings I don't know I'd like to put
all of them together the ones anything
that mentions and I don't have my marked
up copy with me uh
tonight um like this thing about um I
know Stephan said I had to do
we just had a big flood last spring and
no houses were washed
away um preserve and that's goal
six
um and it talks about okay okay policy
housing policy 25 the town will create
programs or incorporate tools with Vis L
development code reduce substandard
housing that will also help identify
specific structures and or general areas
for rehabilitation Redevelopment and
then if appropriate demolition I like
that one better frankly that's something
that you want to put in there because
that to me that's kind clear that's fine
let's put it in yeah okay and you want
to just do the same lead in Lynn that
you did with seven let's do the same
lead in
agree or
disagree comment that policy housing
policy
25 we should have
um just
like three or four U yeah emojis is like
does this a smiley
face like straight face is the neutral
frowny face
or the one with a crinkly mouth and
people can just circle the face how
about the green man throwing up yeah a
good okay so we got that do we do we
have enough from these the housing
policy do we have two or three we have
did we end up choosing one of was it six
we have
did you say 11 11 okay 7 and
25 and 11 did you want to do and you're
going to do the
rating yeah order I think that one is a
good one for rating
okay did we get a range of things
here so we got housing policy 11 is a
range of housing how would you rate them
small family homes ad town houses
housing policy s take advantage of all
opportunities to add needed affordable
and Workforce housing to Pon in the
surrounding areas while being mindful of
the town's desire to avoid over
concentration and overly dense
Construction in anyone
neighborhood okay and then we have 25
the town will create programs and or
incorporate
tools within it Land Development code to
reduce substandard housing that will
also help to identify specific
structures and or general areas for
rehabilitation Redevelopment and if
appropriate
demolition so you know we got one that
that's
under and oh we need a text box with
that one too yeah what what are we
asking people agree disagree
text
box okay um and and they can agree or
disagree and put something in the
comment box too okay
so want it and that gets it three
different goals it which I think is good
three different goals
and
[Music]
so okay I kind of like policy number 29
that we
have that's the one ensure that all
energy efficient designs and
construction contemplate both noise
trespass and light
Tres I'd love to see what people think
about
that so and that's a short
one maybe could we add that
one you feel about that you can put it
in sometimes you can maybe find out how
to work things better for people too you
know as the responses you get right
exactly that's policy housing
um you disagree text box
right so I guess what Stephan was saying
is the policies are kind of in context
within the context of the
goal um so but that's fine because we
have the policy and if it kind of inites
a um a response it's still discussion
starter um conversation starter for
people's Christmas
parties
um and is the thought to um remove step
fourth do you like a mix of housing
opportunities since that other
policy
seven
is yeah seems like it gets it that in a
better way okay so that one's gone so
now we're on to do you want to see
connected neighborhoods to multiple
types Transportation such as walking
cycling as well as the automobile we
should do a text box there just some
people are really don't want
the you know the thing though we have to
realize and I realize this living on
Second Street and even Third Street
we're kind of thorough fairs to people
who live outside of town and so you kind
of at the mercy of the way that things
are laid out
um you
know where this people need cars
especially when they live outside of
town they're not in Walking R so they
drive through town yeah it but I think
it C that as well as not like get
rid there's a recognition there that we
are definitely people can designed for
the automobile yeah people can make
their own choices how often do you walk
how often do Town employees walk to town
I mean how walkable is this I mean it's
like it's not just it's because it's not
walkable but people just have habits
that they easier to jump in the car yeah
and you can't change it unfortunately
and you have a lot of stuff to carry and
you just can't and you don't have the
time but you still want people able to
walk I
think people have always been able to
walk in this town well well it's the
question is do you want to see connected
neighborhoods it's just do you like to
see that continue in my mind
yeah and then if we have a text box they
can make a comment you know if you want
to have a parking area where people
carpue and I noticed one happens up on
the highway just spontaneous all right
but this next one I'm not sure Marvel
doesn't
it they all go to the go to the this
next one does do seem appropriate for
housing do you want which one do you
want to see trails neighboring
municipalities points of interest that
seems off topic that is off topic we
have that
in I think neighboring municipalities
Recreation that's not really us that's
the county saying that we don't have
money to Wi yeah I don't think
that right and then I mean even they
tried to do one to the
Park and there's nightmare with all
these land owners that don't want CH
Crossing so that's not not realistic
well and I don't think it's appropriate
what's it I don't see what it has
housing El no let's check that
out so we have one
two think of the views that we have
should these views be protected and
that's coming from one of
the height VI sheds shed shed VI shed
protection I can't remember which
housing policy it is what about just rid
line development adding
that I mean we're we're kind of in a
hole here and we're surrounded
by Bas here I don't know that we can
control that yeah you can because that's
in town it's all anex up onto lambor
there on with the Christmas decorations
that's in
town I mean and so I know Barb heck at
one point had expressed concern about
rine development in the context of I
think was USS but was also
fires um
but so we have on number 10 housing four
preserve views to the Mountain Natural
amenities and Scenic vist Vistas from
the public real and then and does not
mean from the streets like what is a
public realm like if you can see it from
town park it needs to be protected or
what do public realm me I'm just reading
it I know that's why I was wondering I
didn't understand what the then we have
another one here housing B number four
preserv vied to the mountains natural
amenities and Scenic Miss is from the
public realm and then policy number 19
ensure views designated on the map
entitled viewshed gateways and story
contexts are integrated into planning
for new development this may include
dedication of land setbacks height
restrictions modified building
orientation or modified placement on the
lot that might be a good one they they
had Landscaping in the last
comprehensive plan so anything on
133 they were in that that but this is
View yeah they were they required they
didn't want you to take away from the
like the bur character so you had to do
some sort of a landcaping to like screen
screen proposals I think when you get a
permit you have to designate a
certain percentage of your property to
Landscaping we ENT
to so I think that it's in the building
code I think it's covered in and not out
of town the out of town I don't know I
just remember reading the Highway 133
plans and that's a Scenic byway and so
they wanted to have screening
proposals so you know if you had like
a you had to have some sort of design to
help
mask like the not
exactly F 133 railroad t no it was I
think on that side
but I wonder about farmsworth you know
how they have that attractive like the
Evergreen with the boulders kind of in
front of their I'm wonder if that was
done with this in mind the old
comprehensive plan where they wanted to
do some screening to make things a
little bit better what do you think
about this policy number 19 and adding
it instead of saying do you think the
views we have it's more it just speaks
more
I think the views are self-evident
that's why people move here yeah but
this is saying that it's integrated into
planning for new development and may
include dedication of land setbacks
height restrictions modified building
orientations or modified placement on
the LA so that's
pretty to it so why don't we put that in
did you include the reference to the map
that first phrase that's
on the map should we I don't I
was we don't have the map we don't have
the map
so the intro yeah so how would
[Music]
we encroach on you views
are sure that how about just just take
out designated on the map views are
integrated into planning views okay for
new development I guess views of you
want to above is the S Vistas where they
have the
list of the policy 18 maybe include
jumbo M Lambo L and Peak blah blah blah
en R development I mean you know for
people who live in in the whole
like on
the on on the North Slope you don't have
you don't have all the views but what's
important to you is maybe just the ridg
line view is like we live in the country
so it's just like what if we combine 18
and
19 cor downtown P Europe so would say if
we did which says maintain Scenic Vistas
from rights of away public facilities V
and public lands to Open Spaces J jumo
mountain m m lambor l and Peak and the
core commercial District of downtown
ponia and then housing policy 19 which
would be included in it ensure views are
integrated into planning for gateways
and historic
context uh that integrated into planning
for
new
development this may include dedication
of land setbacks height restrictions
modified building orientations and or
modified placement on the lot so we
would combine those two how about um
Lynn just taking the housing for goal
preserve views to the mountains natural
amenities and Scenic misses from the
public Realm and this may include so or
you know so you aren't quite as specific
with this map thing you should get you
know yeah I would get not do the map we
took the map out yeah okay so when you
out the specific jumo Mountain Matt
lambor just preserve so that's housing
so let's say we're combining goal
housing 4 and policy housing 19 yeah
and then you have room for comment there
maybe it would open up the discussion
about you know other things people are
concerned about so we without being so
specific so that will take the place
of this third to the last entry what do
you think of the views that we have on
Mount laborn that's opening question
so I hate it I know me too jez get rid
of that I could do without that that's
so dry yeah and then it should should
those views be protected but no this is
better and then you know simple I don't
like the light on top of L like we can't
do anything about the light on top of L
so you have to watch I don't
likei there you
go and it got worse this year bigger
really I came down the street and I'm
like it's
bigger property it is yeah cuz people
think it's a town it's like no but it's
kind of sweet though yeah
I think there is a real tradition to
that and that's kind of important that's
the cultural identity of the Town yeah
but just so people know it's not the
town by the way you know my friend
Marvin Beni who's not around anymore he
said back in the day his memory was
there was such a mix of um in the mind
of workers and and um cultural um and
you you can see it actually when you
look at the list of the Mind deaths you
know people were from Greece and from
there are so many
so many countries represented in that
mind and he said that the neighborhoods
would get together and there'd be like a
they'd have a Greek barbecue or
something in the street and then over
here the Polish people and he said it
was really interesting because there was
such it was such a Melting Pot of ethnic
and there were so many like ethnic foods
that you could find actually I I don't
know that's just what he had said at one
time and it was really interesting to
hear and you know that was a time pass
now but
yeah yeah well we can always try again
so do we agree we do we combine go
housing foreign policy housing 19 in one
paragraph which reads preserve views to
the mountains natural amenities and
Scenic Vistas from the public realm
ensure views are integrated into
planning for new development this may
include dedication of land setback
height restrictions modifi building
Orient orations or modified placement on
the
lot just one if you need to put in
within Town limits or something I was
thinking lambor Lamborn jumbo lands and
Peak we do but we decide to not be
specific do you
want preserve views to the surrounding
mountains to the surrounding R to the
yeah we could say but then we're
changing same mountains to the West
well we're the word no no no I think
that's okay because we're not we're not
integrating the content of
18 I'm not I don't think I don't feel
like we're changing the goal here
because the the P the policy list jumbo
Mountain Mount lambor lands and Peak so
I just wonder if PR well no how about
just surrounding mountains yeah do we
want to say both within town and and
within the growth area can you can you
restrict things in the growth area I
mean there was possibly that yeah so I
mean do people need to know where we're
talking about well I think the intro to
this to the whole plan talks about the
three mile growth area that this applies
in the intro to the not to the U um
comprehensive plan yeah but the survey I
mean it's just like do people know what
it's like I guess you'll see when you
get results and it's like whoa that was
interpreted a little differently than we
thought but we're saying preserve the
views to the surrounding mountains
natural amenities and Scenic Vistas from
the public realm so it's big preserve
the views from the public realm what
does that mean from the public
realm that are contained within the
public real deserve the views from us
sitting here as a public person looking
out or is it on Town streets when you're
on Town property public actually when
you look at 819 it gets very specific to
the lot where they put a house on the
lot if it's going to the view of your
neighbor got yeah because I think that's
important too have some say on whether
you just lost Al so everybody who like
has eyeballs they're the
public It also
says was in the that was in the State
statue um that's good so so I have a
question do we like the
indifferent or should we take that out
um or should we add it to all of them oh
you know maybe add it to all of
them you change
up go or light I mean just just because
you don't have a great view doesn't mean
a big house
shouldn't you may not want to look you
know just like I'm street that way yeah
beh behem
yeah um
ma yeah okay so do we want to add in
different different probably a good
addition
yeah okayi so that's
Indi um agree disagree indifferent well
indifferent means you don't care um
okay or that neither one of them you're
not I'd say other agree disagree
indifferent or other well the text
box so they can put in their other inste
of text box well no it's a text box
where they can
com each one will have a place where
they can type in their own thoughts okay
right so yeah I think every each one
should have a common like when you go
and they
say like when they try to rate pain and
you're like I don't know if this is a
one or a four you
should yeah that's what I don't give a
anyway some of these like pigeon
holding things but as long as people
feel like they have they can break out a
little bit okay now is there anything
else I mean we got the view thing there
was something in here it was was the
historic culture is the next Bowl that's
housing five identify recognize and
protect Pon as unique and you replace
both historic and cultural it should be
cultural here shouldn't it yeah I think
that was that was one I got the other
first one fixed I didn't get that one
fixed we'll get it fixed okay um so is
that something we want to add in here to
see if people care about that
um I'm sorry go
ahead oh no sorry got or something El
have anything I was just wondering if we
want to pop one more in before the
viewshed
thing
just well we could put it after the view
shed because that's cultural the
Heritage I'm just making a note to fix
that culture to cultural protect
historic and cultural
resources so maybe policy number 21
speaks to that
F
maybe so you could combine the goal by
identify recognize and protect P's
unique and irreplaceable historic and
cultural heritage by acknowledging and
supporting P ponus Artisan artistic and
Multicultural heritage
Community diversity in planning Town
facilities programs events and resources
I don't think you're really recognizing
diversity and cultural heritage there
because Artis an
artistic multicult this is kind of very
specific and it's like a direction that
we're going in but it's really not
recognizing for inst of the old- here or
the you know it's like kind of a
Community
diversity that would be covered with a
variety of people political points of
view different okay you
know is a big word right but it's all
encompassing so because you don't want
to be prescriptive so the question is
how would we identify and recognize and
protect P's unique
Heritage I'd like to know what people
think that means and then and
um so how what what what does that mean
it comes with when you're looking at a
proposal to do something in to okay so
you know what the library you know the
design of the library building you know
what inspired the
architect The Cow Shed a Cow Shed in
Gunnison County does that library look
like a Cow Shed I think it would be had
been nicer to like recognize like the
fruit package you know something a lot
more but you're bringing up a perfect
point exactly but you see one man's but
the thing is he thought he was and then
the library board was like that that's
great Cow Shed and then when it got
built it's like you know that's a lot
bigger than you know what I mean so you
can't really how do you do that because
they would have to get permission to
build it well he got permission well
with this but this plan this wasn't
there I don't know what's in the night
they didn't have to get permission to
build that building I mean it's just
it's int
yeah but they had to get a permit and so
the town you know a permit isn't for
Aesthetics the permit is for the
physical construction but but all of
this can be considered when somebody
comes in for something like that that's
why this is here so staff will say wait
a minute you know that that thing in the
shape of an egg the apartment building
you want to build it's in the shape of
an egg we don't think that meets this
this this and this what if it's free
speech I mean it's like it's just such a
s
remember that no remember that thing
that Nick gave us with the slides in the
house that was like that it's like
there's this would have protected that I
don't know I he I think he was saying
that it's kind of like a a weird place
and what if it's like Free Speech but he
wasn't talking about the comprehensive
plan he was talking about that specific
situation yeah he's talking about zoning
P the comp plan will be looked at it
informs them decisions yeah to say we
don't want an egg we don't want a
building in the shape of an egg because
it doesn't recognize in prot chech Pay
unique and irreplaceable historic and
cultural heritage because you don't see
any eggs or anyway that's my example
that's why that's
there well ly do you
wanna to who decides to who's greasing
who's Palm
just I don't think this protects things
all that well you don't have a plan
there's nothing there's nothing for
anybody to fall back on the plan you
know you got to have this in place and I
see these as considerations look at the
subdivision there that's go with
anything in our plan I'm sorry but you
know now we have this and it's going to
be fresh and it's going to
be um on everyone's plate and you know
you can't Wordsmith it thing is I guess
you can say what you want and it really
you can't really um reach from the grave
and control what happens in the future
but you can do your best and say what
you want at this point and hopefully
it's listened to right because there
this is a pretty Broad View but some
decides they're just going to go ahead
and do it there's just no way a neighbor
could even Sue because it cost so much
to hire a water hopefully this prevents
these 30,000 foot
considerations this is people read these
things they go oh this town is looking
in this direction so we like it wouldn't
be a good idea for us to look in that
direction in terms so if we combine
housing
five thank you being the typus um yes
housing five goal goal and policy house
policy
21 and so it would read identify
recognize and protect Pon is unique and
we are replac for historic
and I missed something historic and or
cultural heritage that's why I that
didn't read sorry and cultural heritage
um acknowledge and support ponia Artisan
artistic and Multicultural Heritage and
Community diversity in planning Town
facilities programs events and
resources I don't think so I don't agree
with any you
I'm an artist too but it's like
um in planning and in planning Town
facilities Town programs events and
resources this is like telling the town
what to do this isn't developers no this
is the have the town because the town
has to go with this too and use this
because if we had to build a town hall I
don't think it's necessary but it's also
like a lot of people no I'm tired of
seeing I mean I'm getting a little tired
I think this there's like an
overemphasis on the funk Factor here I'm
getting a little tired of looking at it
I just like to see I mean so it's just
like I mean how do you give that option
to people to say enough let's just like
go with some meat and potatoes for a
while all right let's skip this let's
skip this it's a little bit to down the
um just dump it let's look at it's non
that's kind of like necessity so do you
want we have one two three one two three
four
five
six
78 okay questions I'm keep I'm looking
at the last two which is asking people
if there's policies if they read the
housing element are there policies
missing or there ones you want to remove
well so I yeah but I think that's for us
we went home no no that's for the really
yeah he wanted to put that in the
because he wants people to read the read
the housing Poli be included should be
removed okay because that's asking
people to read it and if they see
something they don't like you have to
make sure people know how to find it
Well they I think it's all going to be
under the
same uh what what am I trying to say
it'll be linked it'll be there with the
survey monkey I mean it the housing
element should be first and foremost
before they even take the survey in my
opinion okay so so Sam let
me
Samantha would there be a Sam why do I
want to call you saman I'm
sorry so there where would where would
you see putting in the link um you know
where people could access this and look
at the policies they might want to have
removed or not with it seems like
Stephan linked in one of the first
questions he had a link to the
um uh what was the last one on I don't
know I never saw it it was any it's
still on the website I'm just blanking
out I I would think at the beginning
somewhere would be the best hang on um
he had a link in it oh it was the
short-term rental that's was the last
question here he had a link to the
ordinance in the questionnaire okay so
we could put that in yeah the link
should there be there right up front and
and they could be up front and it could
be again down yeah he can link at the
bottom too because we're asking him to
look
at I mean could have two links um yeah
and it'll be on the mass head here
[Music]
so that's eight questions right I think
that's good I have one more question so
you know I had a strong reaction to the
divers housing options including sen
residents of special needs but did we
did we choose one of these policies for
goal
three three I'm not because I'm
wondering if 16 policy 16 would be maybe
a little bit more open that it might
elicit more of a a response and 11 is in
there now that go let's compare yeah
which one did you just say
16 or is that it doesn't tell you about
housing sizes but it talks about housing
op expan housing options for aging
population to facilate Aging in place
such as
adus that's I guess that's a different
direction energ generational households
and housing products for downsizing
households so would that be tiny
homes support the of range of housing
options see the they're kind of all
saying the same but they're slightly
different worded and so remember when we
had to cut out all that stuff about
trees because it was redundant I'm kind
of getting the same feeling from this
it's like excessively wordy but saying
the same thing but slightly different
when every policy so there's tons of
policy I guess I
don't I see this as really an important
one so do you
think no I think they both need to be
there how would you combine it because
that become very very long well you
would have to change it you you probably
couldn't have a one through four rating
or five or whatever it turns out to be
okay have it is a separate have it is
another question I think it's a worthy
why didn't why don't in uh four why
don't we add
um extend housing for aging population
so you can expand housing options as an
option but you can support development
so you expand it but you also support
the development
um so it's it's just hard how can you
say that a little bit more
concisely um what if we just added it to
the 11 as um housing for aging
population but a small home could be
aging Town Homes could be aging so I
don't see that to me it doesn't
seem I I think it should be a separate
okay I think it's important enough
because that a big part of the housing
study to make own question okay I think
after 11 what did you say what is what
did we finally settle on with the
wording there just leave
it or do you agree with or what what's
been your intro pardon what have you had
an intro phrase that you've been putting
in front of the goals in different no no
no when you have the do you just have
the goal sitting there do you just have
been um reiterating go oh I just put
policy housing
16 yeah do you agree disagree do you
agree
disagree I think that's kind of a good
one for it's because that's been that's
a problem in the town you know people
could also underline or Circle the one
that seems the most important to them or
comment you know because they might say
well I like this but I don't like this
and this and there a comment but then
they can do agree and disagree and I
don't want the pickles or the onions
either but I don't want the pickles or
the onions and make sure it's a non-at
skinny latte
with so we might say with each of these
things P we did this in housing policy
seven states do we want to say States
states yes yeah yeah I think that's more
more readable yep because and then we do
agree
disagree and then text box I mean
somebody might go why didn't you put
them all in It's like because there's
too many yeah I don't think people would
want to do it we just pick what we and
so that we might want to like reiterate
again more the policies can view it's
important to that's where the link to
the housing yeah it so you need to paper
copies yeah there could be paper copies
and it's not let's
see I think the town could print out
paper copies of the housing element to
go with the a paper survey of the monkey
survey right yeah that's all doable and
get get rid of all the red and
everything it'll just
be oh yeah L text right but that's sure
doable for those folks that are going to
fill it out on
paper and when do you want to do this
you know what's the
deadline did we Sam did we have a
deadline for putting this survey out did
we come up with one
or I don't I don't
know see if I made some
notes but refer to number three and I
can't find the tree up in
here we in the oh right there it isil
visability is that
word expand the supply
hous things are so redundant in a way
but slightly different so it makes it
hard to know what you're reading I'm
having a hard time with well this one
you know puts in through the use of
Universal Design which isn't really and
that means you know that it's Ada client
or yeah but I thought with the trees we
put a lot of things in that but we
struck out a lot because it was deemed
redundant so I but it was you know being
redundant in a way it was repeated
pretty much verting you know these are
these each combine a different a
slightly different aspect of the same
concept yeah that's how I read it anyway
okay do you want
to when get this
out I guess the thing about the light to
have we shall discourage Redevelopment
and demolition practices that
significant reduce existing housing
stock in older neighborhoods and the
result of displacement of very low low
and moderate income pris well a lot of
the really crummy houses around here
that are kind of talked about
this future one the reason people live
there is they can't afford anything else
and and so that's kind of like but see I
think controversial they contradict each
other yeah I do too but I just think
there's like contradictory stuff I just
don't understand what we're trying to
say here when it seems like there points
that are contrad but maybe we'll let
people look at it and yeah I mean that's
why we're put
and hopefully people all those four
people and substandard housing that have
to like drive to W Walmart to work have
time to actually do surveys like this
you know or you know what I mean because
a lot of times working folks just don't
have the
time it's really short so we do have to
give it enough time for people to
really be able to so could I make a
motion that we accept these changes that
we came up um yeah just yeah need a the
draft for you know for the questions and
answers for the Survey
Monkey okay I make motion that we accept
the changes that we made for the um
draft of this for the questions for the
public survey
monkey just say the survey okay public
survey okay I make a motion that we
accept the draft that we just worked on
tonight for the public survey to be sent
out yeah for the housing
portioning of
the do you have that s thank
you second
that those in favor I hi hi and Lynn I
was going to ask if you could share your
typing with Stefan okay I'm G you know
I'm going to clean it up yeah but I
think you have taken the best notes and
I don't know that Sam has taken his as
sync notes because you don't really have
every send them
to yeah yeah and you may have to like
it's not really clear to me like on some
of these where we say policy 25 and then
there are other policies 20 25 so you no
there's only one policy 25 in the
housing element right but then we have
okay I'm just going to make sure that
people know which one we're talking
about and so Sam if it doesn't seem
clear could you clear clean that part up
absolutely okay thanks and do you want
to come up with a time for the Survey
Monkey to go out and then a deadline for
the comment
come
in should do that and what are other
de we don't have anything really until
after the first of the year right
because we left it open-ended for the
the work that um P riz's going to
do and the the uh work work session for
the draft that is why way open-ended
because it was it's not clear when there
be a final draft to put out for people
to comment so you know we shouldn't if
we put it out we shouldn't give people
too much time or they forget about yeah
I don't know how
much I don't know what Stephan did long
this Survey Monkey was open I'm not sure
on that one I know that when you guys
did talk
about I don't know if it helps but I
think you guys were aiming for your um
public meeting with Phoenix Ry resources
somewhere around the January 6th period
was oh I I we could never make it by
January 6 I don't think well I'm just I
thought it was TBD in January because we
knew we wouldn't have a draft for them
to do all the spread the Earth right
till I would say just because of
Christmas because we're not going to
meet again
rightone yeah so I was thinking TBD
January and this could be in December
the Survey Monkey could you
know he was saying a month but then
willed from the public meeting say it
again then would it feel to the public a
little bit you know Lost in Space for
you know the timeline for the the
meeting on the draft element well I'm
wondering do you think there should be a
meeting seems to me there needs to be a
meeting on the housing element before
the draft
oh did you say C plan or element sorry
suggestion yeah
says survey up through the
holidays through the holidays till the
end survey up through the holidays in
January 6 have the survey go till
January
6 okay takes a
while do you feel like you want to have
a meeting to go over the survey results
on the housing element then I think
we would inform us as to opinion because
the first meeting is that that's the
regular first meeting of the Planning
Commission so if Stephan it it shouldn't
the the survey should stop before the
six so we have something to talk about
on the sixth right it should be stopped
to give him time to um maybe by to look
at to analyze it you know to go through
and get all the statistics
usually survey do that he it does but
you would want that
you there's no it's not like there's
going to be that much deing maybe well
but it should I'm thinking it should be
in the agenda packet the results of the
survey and that has to be done the week
before right the meeting so what how
about like December 31st would would the
survey would surve that does that are
you is this a text from Stefan or you
yeah I was ritten off a text from Stefan
seems like yeah survey up through the
holidays ending in January I
think this is just my my opinion here is
that you're
GNA trying to stop anything right there
within that holiday period I think is
gonna really take away from you because
I mean I know you got Christmas but you
also have New Years New Years and then
the town hall is closed and people are
yeah people are
sometimes it's the best time that people
have to get off with holiday I don't
think we would have something ready to
put an agenda packet on the six if it
closed on the six and wouldn't we be
missing a meeting opportunity to talk
about El could we move that meeting
would we be in agreement to move that
meeting Suzanne that's to you so that we
did have it in I mean I think it's
important and I'm
contractor gr what what was the next
step with her she just was going to
advertise a comprehensive plan in
general but that would be but she wanted
to focus remember she said she wanted to
focus on um some of the sections that
were new so are we kind are we kind of
yeah so I mean the Housing section was
new but so how can we like dovetail it
so benefits what she's trying to do I
don't think you can duil it and the
reason I say that is
because if we we now have a draft of the
comprehensive plan but the draft hasn't
been approved by the Planning Commission
and it seems like you can't you don't
want to put out something that we
haven't all said yay to and we haven't
talked about the future land use map but
there's some written stuff on that is a
f future land use section yeah yeah you
did that that came from cose okay but so
I'm seeing because we only have five
hours of calories I know and she was she
was going to be dedicated to kind of um
doing the the meeting the the meeting
sounded like no she was going to do the
advertis not not come to the meeting
just that her five hours was to get the
word out can't remember what she said
and it seems to me if we only have five
you want to wait until we have a draft
for a work session which I feel like the
housing element needs another meeting
where the public can come after the
survey mon need to be a work session for
the public and if you feel like you want
to change it later in January that would
give time for the Survey Monkey to be
over on the 6th but we have to have time
for the Survey Monkey to be a put in an
agenda packet so we need to move the
planning
meeting if we
I'm have the regular planning meeting to
talk about your future land use map or
whatever else you talked about then
maybe you set a workshop for this one
after that so keep the six and Leap Frog
go have a sixth meeting to talk about
land use and then have another meeting
to talk about housing element later yeah
that may be
[Music]
better we haven't put the survey out
there so it's kind premature to talk
about do we have any hearings on
this okay I was just asking if there was
a hearing
does sound like it so we would put the
survey monthy out in December have it
end by the six then we would have our
planning meeting on housing element is
that right no later in the month the
sixth would be to talk about land use
map oh the
maps there's several map and the other
maps that we haven't seen and then and
then the later in the month we would
talk about those results of this and
then look at the housing
how
we it's
okay anyone choose a meeting in January
on
the no no no I mean do you want to
choose the later meeting in January on
the 6th yeah okay know what you want to
have on that agenda because that's also
going to come up through the holidays I
mean let's not make it too big well if I
was going if you can
either we were talking about future
Landing SP up do you maybe all the maps
yeah just seeing it the because that's
what we've been waiting on
those then you don't have toy all us
down to get
your okay
Su just the future land use map future
land use map and the future land use
content yeah let's do the future land
use map and I I can't remember what it's
called I'll give it to you later and I
think there's goals and policies right
um no not in that I saw something okay
um go back it's it talks about the
different um zones on the land use map
and then by then we could get the other
four maps from Stefan that are
outstanding so land use map and section
right yeah and the other remaining Maps
Okay I don't know if we have probably
set your session you know we're GNA talk
about the future land use map and you
can present the other Maps but I don't
think we necessarily have to discuss the
other Maps right now because that I
don't know how expensive I don't like
these late meetings as it's a little too
much slot to digest so let's focus on
the future land use map and then make
sure that we have those other Maps
available too to see just to start start
that yeah and then we can decide if we
want to
like something more based on what we get
probably
[Music]
okay great okay let's the meeting