e
e e
uh let's see I don't have an agenda in
front of me but there's not much on it
other than I was just asked if we could
do a roll call that we're all here
my trusty Hunter trusty schwarts mayor
Smith trusty check trusty
stelter you
me administrator
treasur
Rec and we're working but you don't need
a don't need AUM we're just here with
just just you look good for a quum
later yes okay take it away
administrator win oh okay um so this is
uh this is an updated budget based on
what we talked about the last time it
was uh presented I did add some things I
didn't want to include the SWAT
analysises
analyses for each department so those
were included in this packet um to show
what guided the budgeting process and
and where we're at um this is admin um I
don't want to go over this in great
detail unless you want to because I've
already done it a a staff report or a
Town Administrator report um streets
parks and
recks police
department water
Wastewater trash
oops okay and now this is where it
starts becoming
new um this page in your packet your
agenda packet as uh page 10 is capital
Improvement requests um you'll see that
a number of these don't have don't have
values in the administration department
how the reason for that is they're dues
and subscriptions they're not Capital
costs but Sam wanted to make sure that I
had them included in the budget so
um that's why they're there like your
cmca does your IC
dues so those things are
included should ask for a chair it's
under
$1,000 Reuben okay law enforcement um so
MD mdts those are mobile data terminals
those are actual laptops for police cars
each one of the new the new squads that
we have um that we purchased from AA has
a a stand to take a laptop um we use
spilman as our records management system
it's all very digital but we don't have
laptops for officers um so we'd like to
buy some um in the upcoming uh fisal
year
25 how many you're gonna get mat you
know how many this was six six you get
six for $10,000 I think so we probably
will not be purchasing the traditional
like Panasonic Toughbook yeah um that's
probably we'll go a little different
because we did find some yeah like Asus
essis um they do like a tough book but
instead of it being $4,400 it's like
$900 same heavy duty hinges you know
good good speeds and things like that
that we that we're looking at
so um and then also security cameras so
this is the police department sherff
security cameras this is back parking
lot
hallway I think one in here was it one
in here Matt this room one out front and
then also in the um I need to add that
to this but I did put it the budget um
also inside the cashier room one that's
up top looking down over the cash
register um as well as outside so uh we
need a bad so I'm just this is not like
in the movies where there' be a TV
screen with each camera could be
there so yeah that's I guess what I'm
asking so where where do the cameras
where do the images go well so now it's
cloud-based so we log into the software
system and we're able to pull it up so
it's all housed uh the one that we're
looking at is verata and it's all housed
on site in their server Farm whatever
you want to call it that houses have you
remember how many days uh depends on
which plan we get minimum or at least 30
days um but that's where part of the
cost comes from is housing it storing
everything in the cloud verse the older
systems that store everything on site
which we would have to
have resp and then this is also not just
for this building but it ALS the the
cost that we got from verata is also for
the water plant the Wastewater Plant and
the parks uh was it three in the Park
yeah
um one at the there's one in the
Pavilion there's one looking towards the
state park and then U one kind of
generally around the Smith Memorial
center there no one
downo so I was looking at the previous
work session and and is all of are all
the cameras what is presented at the
very end of that agenda packet so we
can't we don't have in front of us
tonight so I don't really we can talk
about it but could you reinstate it for
the next agenda pack so it can be back
in front of us do you do you all know
what I'm talking about we didn't get to
so at the last meeting we didn't get to
um CBT really we didn't get to the
salaries and we didn't get to cersa and
we didn't get to these cameras which
were which are being budgeted and I I
kind of would like us to be able to go
back and discuss those pieces of the
previous agenda packet that didn't get
in just from my perspective but I know
we'll have to put it in another agenda I
can talk about it tonight it's work yeah
budg all right well then
okay let me go I just downloaded
it it's October
22nd Work
session am I the only one who's
interested in this no okay
and I say maybe we come to that however
you want to do it
Stephan let's go to it
now so the the cameras start on page 72
of
77 wasn't on the 22nd that was it it was
um yeah it was uh budget session October
22nd this pack doesn't have an
Argent what page should you say I the
one I'm seeing is Page 72 it was a tail
end of that agenda
factor and it's the work session agenda
packet not sorry it's the work session
packet not the agenda packet
sorry did we go through the sersa like
Insurance stuff because I think that
would be helpful yeah I don't think we
did because I went back and listen to
the tail end of the video had gotten
through the budget tables
yeah sorry okay
72 is that too far I think I'm more in
the are you in the budget work section
from October 22nd yeah page 72 go all
the way to the end it's rroll
up
oh you're looking at the cameras
yes that's in the work session pack so
this this is this is the camera you know
that we're talking about um what it's
it's showing uh that we that we be
putting
in uh one camera at the water the main
building at the
lamber um water treatment
plant uh then there's an influent
building um that is
where is the
influent this is for Wastewater it's on
the far end of the P okay okay so that's
the that's the place that we so this
isn't lamber this is our Wastewater
Plant um the main building is where they
have their their their lab and then the
influent building is where the bathroom
is where that screen that screen is that
bar screen um water treatment that
that's the lamber plant there are uh
looks like
two two c cameras um one indoor outdoor
fisheye and then um an indoor Mini Dome
inside the plant
itself town park
has uh one indoor outdoor fisheye an
outlet bullet
camera and then an outdoor multisensor
camera and so I want to say that one was
going to be right
here um one at the one at the teen
center
facing um that orange is actually
supposed to be on the other side one at
the Pavilion and then one at the
Gazebo Tower Hall this is the one where
uh that I explained earlier this is
where we have two um one out front
facing the front one out back facing the
parking
lot exterior and then two indoor um one
over by the PD and then one in front of
um
facing down at the cashier
desk I think that was it for the
cameras um we're budgeting about $50,000
amongst all the different funds for
them um and then there will be an annual
cost with them for
um to be able to log in remotely and and
check all of our uh check
what's been
recorded how come only the um the
capital expense for law enforcement
shows up here I put it in for the oh so
this is that's coming from cleargov um
but when we get down into the
actual into each budget line item in in
the workshop packet for today you'll see
under Capital outlay each one of them
pass this budget for
ask a question before you move off the
first table or t I'm now in tonight's
packet yep page 10 so what is listed
here in this table are those the capital
costs the things that the department
heads want to buy are we going to see
more this is what they put in for this
year so that's it um no knowing knowing
what hasn't been included is the fifth
and Grand alignment project uh but that
is in the actual
spreadsheets um the water tank reigning
project not in this but in the actual
spreadsheets and then also
um Western Ro realignment as
well and I've got a question the bid bid
date on this was uh August 20th and it
said good for 30 days we're going to
have to go out to so this is we needed
something for budgeting purposes when we
do this we're going to have to go out to
bid get through
yeah in accordance with this policy
manual so and at a work session can
everybody just speak
up yeah yeah everybody just speak don't
wait for
me thank you oh we have a question in
the M I'll point out as well that you'll
see that law enforcement Public Safety
both on there the public safety items
were budgeted for this year the vest as
you know we've already purchased five
those we're only waiting to purchase one
V and then the Red Dot systems that'll
be a this year item as well so those
won't be for 25 but the reason they're
in there is because they were uh used
for Capital budgetting last year and
they're not completed
yet uh did you want to go over the
insurance from sersa from the last one
well in terms for a matter of timing
what do folks do you do you feel like we
should look at what's in tonight's
packet um as a priority and then see if
we have time to go to the others I I
just because I don't have a preference
okay I'm happy to answer any questions
you have an insurance um that's that's
why that's why I want because it it all
is reflected within the actual budget
documents so um I might ask one question
if you could just say what is the
average pay raise that has been that is
in the it's 5.7
% and then I had one inflence I'm over
ring myself here I'm taking it so in the
cersa list that is in that previous
meetings
packet I was kind of curious this had
come up before I was curious about can I
just ask one question is just were there
can you give me the range like uh if 5.7
is average what's the highest and what's
the lowest um I uh yes on I sorry no no
no good it's all
good I don't know if I have a percentage
but I definitely have an
amount okay
okay so this
is uh you won't see this one this is an
internal document as is
is this
doc see
it is this that amazing spreadsheet you
did like yes so this is this is the this
is the spreadsheet that I use to look at
um salary increases overall um let's I
do this one okay so for example um Matt
if if you look in that I don't know if
you can really see it or
not we do have your other table the
columnar table you were just showing you
aren't going to get it from here okay so
if you look at whoa okay if you look at
this top line up so where it says F ofx
that says equals so that 1.08 that's an
example of Max it's an 8% increase um I
think one of the largest ones comes from
our sergeant gett
when I didn't do his let's see this one
sorry we're doing math on the Fly
Guys so this one looks so Matt or
Garrett is it's actually 19% but that's
not where he's at right now so we split
that he got a merit increase this year
and then the balance of that is for uh
going to 25 uh what did we do was it a
seven or eight% this year and then we're
doing the balance of it going into
2025 and this these to get him at that
number brings him to about the average
of Cur we our average when we looked at
different uh communities which was KY
was it KY or
ke was Kingsburg
and me
see have to stop sharing
here we go
so you can see their sergeants um they
start them at
92,000 in
Kingsburg uh this is is this yeah this
is
Kingsburg and are they an an anomaly for
City set size they're a lot um so what
we're finding is that for Sergeants and
for Chiefs Matt um on average a chief
for communities our size is about
114,000 so we're just we're trying to
get everybody incrementally there and
while we did give an increase Queen in
24 it was um it didn't even get us into
the average it got us got us pretty
close but it wasn't quite there that's
why we're proposing a 5.7% increase
going going forward um but Garretts was
probably the highest the highest
increase um we did increase like our
starting salary for water that water
oper that's still sitting open um a
minimum of 52,000 and that's untrained
right that's somebody that that's ready
to that meets all of our skills you know
required competencies so they can get so
that we can get them trained to take the
exams um it's just the reality that
we're in that position has been
published all over the place at
government jobs.com we've done
newspapers it's on our website and we
can't even get qualified people to to
apply it's pretty rough
um so that's that's kind of where we're
at if I may I'll point out in his
defense as well and his support
more even if that
raise more than likely makes you the
lowest paid Sergeant adta
County with his time in
grade say that again with his time in
grade and his time here that's something
we have to look at too
right right we don't while we don't
necessarily directly to our surrounding
communities given that we have two
Sheriff's Department V County and Delta
County
um those are the organizations that
we're we are surrounded
by that goes across the board that's
with ad Public Works water that's
everything um and it's not 52 we we
bumped it up from 52 to 55 starting so
just we're trying to fill that position
we need somebody
um it's it's part of the requirements of
lifting our water monitoring says that
we're staffed um we are reply or
responding to leaks from the time that
we're we're notified of them to the
repairs about 24 hours on average which
is incredible um going back from like
eight weeks before or 24 hours that's
good turnaround but we still we still
need that one more
person to cover that
um one of the things that we we
identified uh right now with some of the
training that we're sending people to
we're doing the positive employee
training offered through one Delta
County um it's been phenomenal the
things that we're hearing come back
about how um our employees can you know
communicate with each other but they're
learning about themselves and they've
identified somebody who's ready to
become a supervisor um in the public
works department so that's what this
budget also proposes that proposes Matt
Taylor um to move from a labor General
Public Works to a a public works
supervisor running streets trash that
kind of
stuff is that in this table that we had
in the last package it is yeah so let's
see I don't know if I changed the name
yet um but it was he was in general
public works there it is so on pay I
don't know what pack it is but page it's
um this one right here let me see if I
can highlight it water operators on page
47 water operators yeah and it's got the
Public Works director Deputy water
operator go to the next page okay it's
that one that's labor General Public
Works PW that's Matt Taylor and it's 56
and that that is the um salary to put
him in that new position supervisor
position correct
yep oh I'm sorry he's the one just above
that so it's on the flas page at 56,000
this one below is actually Rodney he's
he's just 10 years that's why his salary
is so so high it was a 56 56 on the
bottom of page correct
[Music]
yep so we just missing one employee
we're missing two um so the other one is
so that we're missing the water employee
but if you also go down to laborer
General Public Works it's on that second
page at 52,000 that's just a laborer we
do have a position open um it was filled
with um uh was that Coxwell what was his
name who was it um oh yeah Coxwell yeah
he was here for two weeks and then went
back to se do so he came from seop went
back to se not um what we have to make
sure is that this whoever applies for
this realizes they will be throwing
trash right it's it's INR to this
position that was actually rice it was
uh rice rice okay Caleb rice so that we
have two positions open and um yeah this
one also contemplates moving Morgan to
full-time for part-time um and then
she's really going to dive into being a
utility Utility Billing and permit Clerk
or coordinator um you going to hit that
hard so uh we do have training next week
on the new Community Development module
for Cassel so all of our building
permits all of our permitting system
everything we'll be going through that
module and she's the front line so um
instead of having boxes of paper records
and really crummy
applications um C Cassel will actually
uh has an application that's ready to go
um and then also offering actual permits
and it will all be digitized so we will
have a digital record that at the end of
the year when the county assessor's
office asks for it I can print a report
and say Here's all the properties I've
got a billing permit in town um and
here's here's the estimated cost of
their Renovations which also helps our
property taxes
so um it's coming but that's that's so
this budget does contemplate those
things um I want to say
uh you know mine go my salary goes from
118 to
125 um clerk gets her to closer to where
other clerks are at
70,000 um this also does contemplate
Kaja Bowman going from staff accountant
to Deputy Treasurer and then paying her
for you know that those responsibilities
she's already doing those
responsibilities um she actually has
exceeded my expectations for what that
position could ever have been
um so it just it just makes sense to get
her towards that department head so
that's not actually shown here it is no
that the the future it is the salary is
not the title change so which one is
hers staff accountant it's on that first
I'm on page 48 I need to go 47 yes okay
thank you and then this also adds uh an
allocation for hers to be paid 25% out
of
general fund water sewer trash the
majority of her time is spent on water
sewer trash it's just the way it
is I heard her today having to explain
to someone you didn't you weren't the
only one that got this letter we we need
to verify that you are the owner of this
property so she deals a lot of with
policy that comes out she's that front
line that has to explain no this is our
policy um Public Works director um gets
Corey closer to 82,000 sub 815
2260 um and that is more in line with
with what other Public Works directors
are making he's still on the lower end
to kind of like that is um but it's
still an incremental Step Up um this
also does uh does change fixed
allocations so that the Enterprise
utilities are getting hit more than um
parks and streets um he spends a lot of
time in water and
trash uh Nikki this also contemplates a
change for Nikki as well as Deputy
Public Works director with fixed
allocations um again I'm seeing more of
her time being spent in water and
wastewater but then um probably an equal
amount with between streets parks and
trash the way they've divied up
responsibilities is this is pretty good
they get things done they need another
supervisor though actually in the
field so the one water operator that
also has trash at 10% that's that's
Jordan um he's the he's the one who's
well on his way to becoming our orc and
that's why you see him getting paid um a
little bit more than the deputy Public
Works director he's paid for the LI
Insurance certifications that he has but
he also runs trash truck he's got a CDL
so not only does he have the water
license the Wastewater license but he
also has a CDL so he's he's paid
appropriately for
that um the water operators uh that
second that first one is Derek so um
that's why he's at 56 612 he's he's got
a going on three years with us um and
has earned his licensure while he's been
with us that's why he's higher than
while we're trying to start somebody
new the labor waterer oh the labor water
um I can't remember who that's tied to
um it may be
Dennis I think it is Dennis Dennis is
our longest tenured employee that's why
you would see that at 56
explode and he's not an operator but he
does a lot of work out there so and
streets see labor Parks um this is Cole
so Cole is our Parks guy um that's why
he paid Park Street and sanitation he
also throws trash he does not have a CDL
he's throwing trash on back
truck labor Solid Waste I don't remember
who that one is um but it it that was at
5.7%
Inc oh no I'm sorry that's Matt it's
Matt Taylor he's that one's going to
change to
supervisor labor or General Public Works
um so that is Rodney um and he spends a
lot of his time in sanitation or trash
he has he's the CDL driver he's
typically the one that you see driving
around town driving the trash truck but
he also gets out throws trash he'll also
hook up to uh um dumpsters and and throw
those as
well labor mechanic that's Clint um he
does all of our oil changes I think he's
been doing it for your Fleet too Matt so
um been working on ior as well so as
things get done it's being recorded in
our in our software um so that we can be
doing uh TR um tracking you know
materials that we're using things like
that when it's time for new tires all
that Clint's pretty good at that there's
a few things he can't do um that we have
to take out most of it is related to
Hydraulics so like if we're doing um
like a trash truck has a has a dumper um
that might go out we got to take that
somebody else to look at hydraulic stuff
so when um the mayor and I review the
finances every other week I'm always
just impressed to see like okay we just
bought struts or shocks or whatever I'm
like sweet we're doing that in house
yeah that is just awesome and even just
to reduce the amount of downtime for
having these vehicles not be operatable
so it's great and we're tracking it too
so um that's what that whole ey workor
program was was for I think it I I don't
know if it helped inform what needed to
go on the disposal list um but it's
certainly it's certainly on there um so
we had a lot that just had to go that's
that's what you'll see in your next
meeting uh again I talked about Matt as
you know police chief um I'm telling you
when we were looking the average the
average was
$114,000 so we're getting a hell of a
bargain it's like going to all's
Discount St
um the clerk so that that's Joanne um
she really needed to be bumped up for
what she does um she's also the police
mom but really what she what she does is
everything that comes to that front desk
she takes care of she's a notor she also
helps Prov my backup when I got uh when
when we need uh everyone up front she'll
she'll come up and run that front desk
as well so she's well versed in
everything that's why she's looking at
um finally being closer to that that
average um I think that average is
closer to 60 but she's at 52
so police sergeant again that scar it we
got to bring him up or we're gonna lose
him I I just I I not that he's looking
but I'm really worried that we're going
to lose the the staff that we've built
this team that we've built trying to get
them closer to where you know that
90,000 Mar is trying to get them up
there um that police officer that first
one um that's at
60,000 that I believe is it's either
Thomas or Brad Thomas so Thomas is bring
being brought up to 60,000 we're still
at below average so we're we're we're
trying to get closer to that average
cost of police officers we for the guys
that we
have I think we're paying them low but
for the guys that we have we're doing
you know we're doing pretty good we've
got really good guys that really should
be they could be doing a lot more
somewhere else that investigator that's
Pat um so he's our longest tenured
officer I think second longest with the
town second longest with the town so
Dennis and then Pat um that's why he's
at 67
93550 this other one at 60,000 is uh is
Brad
bisano um and again I'm worried about
losing these guys um but 60,000 seems to
be um I think that's where they're like
starting off officers to go send them to
training post training so these are
people that don't even have the
certification that other departments are
starting with at this in Delta County in
Delta County
yeah um and then if you remember the
municipal quarterly we were asked um to
stop raising police salaries and if we
could have a pack we're like no you guys
are way higher than us we got to catch
up so sorry um the SRO that's Kaden um
he's at 65,000 I don't know what Matt's
planning to do with ranks or anything
but because he's a SRO that's why he's
looking at that higher amount he's he is
integral to PKA and he's trying to get
his way into nius a little bit more but
they're they're pretty hesitant it's
just the
Nature
School okay and that was it for PD
office assistant part-time I've budgeted
higher than normal for this one but this
would be like candy or hiring so cand is
only here on front Fridays um but this
will also be hiring like a part-time
person um throughout the week that can
help with filing and things like that um
I need candy here on Fridays I
personally need her she's the one that
does things like this for me um but then
she's also going she doesn't know it yet
she's going to be integral into making
this Community Development module active
she's going to take all of our historic
permits going back to the 50s and
digitizing them attaching to the
properties she's good at that so she can
do that um
I'm just going to have to be really
prescriptive with my instructions so but
I think that that's going to be a really
good project that if I were to hire
somebody else to do that you know to do
some of the stuff with um what do they
call it integration implementing an
integration for software I mean this is
50 60,000 bucks just just to do this
kind of stuff that she'll do when she's
here and and attach it to property
recers which would be really good
because when I when I went to buy my
home and I looked for property records
it was pretty rough um I don't think
they even got um the the extensive
remodeling that they did they certainly
didn't get a building permit for um
found that out the last building permit
I think was from 1980 and it was from
Windows that have also been
replaced it's all important for
maintaining our property tax space right
so as people do Renovations you're
supposed to give back to the assessor's
office annually so that they can adjust
what they've got
so Delta city of Delta doesn't have to
worry about that because they have a
Walmart they have a McDonald's and they
have a Little Caesars they got all of
this big sales tax base that they don't
have to have property tax because of all
their sales tax they're all their sales
tax we learn that that there too I
didn't know if that was because they
were a home rule it's just because they
have enough Revenue they have enough
Revenue that they decided they don't
need property taxes so that would be
something yeah H um let's
see well I guess they don't do local tax
to the city of Delta no they do a local
tax Oh you mean a property tax no they
yeah they do sales tax but they don't do
property I thought the
county the county does right so if
you're in the city of Delta there's no
city of Delta property tax military you
you've still got your taxing districts
at the school and the fire district and
all that stuff but you won't have
that cedar is different
though um let's see Utility Billing
permit clerk so this is this is Morgan
um bumping up to a full-time position
and so this budget also recognizes and I
showed you that big long spreadsheet I
have it down to cost for
employee by fund and so I can tell you
that um in the admin Department I might
cost uh
$40,000 with my salary uh benefits
insurances uh taxes paid on my behalf
and um what's the final
one retirement retirement benefits yeah
so all of I can tell you the cost per
person for by fund um and what that
breakdown looks
like I wish cell did that for me but
instead I had to build a workshop for so
um let's see and then if you guys
would consider giving yourselves raises
whatever that takes I think what you do
is you give it but then it's for the
next
board to get in um it's been a while so
that might be something we contemplate
if not this year maybe next year um
looking at looking at raising them
because uh what is it 100 bucks month is
is really a pit so I wrote that
or
96 $100 since no or you just wrote that
the existing you kept it and then you
couldn't vote on your yeah
pay it had to go to the next council
person that seemed to be fair yeah
that's actually standard across
municipalities so none of you would ever
see this
it's standard maybe in Colorado like
other places like that some of them even
do it by uh U referendum so to go on the
bot um and then municipal judge we're
still keeping her at 6600 we recover a
lot of that cost from the finds that she
imposes so um it's pretty good but
that's that's it for like salaries
things um we did uh and then in that in
that
workbook or the old packet um does it do
I have in
there there it is the that one is what
I'm looking at cost sharing so this will
be this is the first year that that I'm
proposing or the town is proposing since
I don't it must have been different in
the past um that every employee that
takes health insurance pays some portion
of it in the past it was always 100%
employee paid we we just received such a
large increase in health insurance that
I said even an employee only um you're
going to have to pay at least 10% which
is still really generous um I think this
the industry standard is
65% um paid by paid by the by the
employer and then that that balance is
made up by um by the
employee but at the same time we still
have to have enough employees buying
into the insurance program to stay in CB
CBT and receive the the incredible rates
that we get so even though it was like a
third was a 13 half% increase something
like that on average 13% increase we're
still trying to recover some of that
cost and then I did some of that math um
the total annual Town cost is
229,000 the total employee annual cost
is
42 so we're
still getting you know getting there
my understanding was the reason for this
increase is we finally out of that Co
people are actually using health
insurance again and that's that's that's
kind of why the r it's an experien
quotient it it goes up it's EQ um the
good news is for like um for like my
family where we do have this family plan
um my son is on is on a Medicaid waiver
so this insurance is secondary for
whatever Medicaid doesn't pay so far we
haven't had to use it so that should
keep that experience quotient down at
least of my end um and I don't go to the
doctor ever even though I'm told I need
to go so um that's no reason not to use
it so but we we're still trying to
recover some of that cost right so know
I think it's worth mentioning that I
know that pay is a big thing that keeps
people at jobs but we also can't forget
about benefits culture feeling valued
having
responsibility having towns people yell
at you like there's all of these things
that I think go into keeping so I I
appreciate what what St what the
leadership is doing to help encourage
that staff moral because that's a big
deal nobody wants to work at a place
that getting yelled at we don't have
responsibilities so that's a big part of
it as well and that's I know that you
can't reflect those things in the budget
but it definitely is there yeah and I've
heard that same feedback is it's our
benefits that keep people here because
we do offer pretty good
benefits I wish I could get more people
to invest in their retirement though so
that they don't have to work to 78 um
but that's that's a longer discussion
you know down the road with
employees ask question yeah of course
can just go ahead is there a way of
setting up like a medical savings plan
that sort of a hybrid
retirement you know what I'm talking
about right um hey John's trying to
get um I so are you talking like a
health savings account well that's that
there's different versions of oh you're
an MSA so i' have I'd have to look at um
what CBT offers but because we're we're
cons even though by the IRS standards we
are considered a high deductible health
plan we are not a high deductible Health
Plan we're a PO and there are different
things that we can and can't offer like
I can't offer an HSA because we are a
PTO now I can have my own personal HSA
and contribute myself because that
deductible is is considered high
deductible by the IRS standards um but
it isn't it is actually po um so I'd
have to look into that but what I'd
really like to encourage and maybe
consider putting in front of you soon is
our match right now we just give 5% to
every employee for their retirement plan
so whether they whether they invest or
not we give them 5% I it's really good
right if they don't invest it it just
stays in the kitty no so we give it to
them we have established the 401K for
them um or not a um 457 457b we have
established that for them we're putting
money into it and it's normally going
into like um based on their birth year
whatever that it is for 67 years and so
that's the fund that they they
automatically get placed into I do it
differently and then I found out I was
the guy that was was the reason why they
sent an email and a letter it was saying
um we're getting ready to get rid of the
JP Morgan small Equity cap because it's
performing poorly and I was I had most
of my money invested in it um don't care
I still got an 18% return so but it
wasn't performing as well as they'd like
so um I was really happy log I check it
religiously um I like to see how my
investments are doing and I'll make
changes but I have that L like that's
this is my baile wig right some of our
guys in public works it's not their
baileywick even some of our police
officers it's not their baileywick but
our guy at Empower Shane squib is is
doing one-on ones with guys but what we
need to do or consider is maybe doing a
matching program where we give 3% and
then we'll go you know if you if you go
if you go 5% we'll match up to 5% so you
know now they're at 10% instead of just
a 5% you see where I'm going with that
that's that's what I'm trying to maybe
consider and Shane um squib from U he's
what is he actually
Empower modern Financial can give us
something that we can look at and then
consider for um implementing
but that would that would help like some
of our 25 year employees who have maybe
$18,000 you know in the retirement it's
like yikes how um so that's something to
consider yeah but does that require like
a 1040 or 1069 or an 89 or something
like that we have to file a form with
the
IRS the contributions for retirement
then we do it every year so so you do
have to file yeah so um because we go
through um our we have a plan
administrator and that's
empower empowers the platform but it's
modern financials are administrator they
actually send they I get one so they
mail it out um you actually had a
retirement plan here's what you put into
it um I also get one for my HSA company
because I I have my own HSA and it's I I
get something as well we don't actually
send it out we send out uh what is it w
is it W2s that we send out at the end of
the year we send those out and then we
show on their retirement contributions
but then modern Financial will also send
something in uh a form to you as well so
there's no tax liability to the employee
on
it depends Ira right well we so I also
elect to do an out Roth IRA which I can
now do what is it uh 20,000 it used to
be 10 but they bumped it up so I can put
that in taxfree I just take a penalty
when I take it out early but if they
don't and it's not a tax there's a
tax if they take it
out one of the things that a lot of our
um our employees are a lot more in
charge of their retirement now than they
have been in the past and um Shane has
been really good about starting to get
some education out there we have
multiple workshops hopefully with him
planned over this next year so people
can start getting a little bit more with
it but they all they do have the option
of so the town always puts into a 457b
for them which is which is uh preex yeah
yes it's pre-tax but quite a few of our
employees they also have the option some
of them put into a Roth instead which is
a an after tax thing so it really
depends on what they want to do they
some people put into both you know that
actually have a lot of flexibility with
what they can do with their retirement
and then we're doing our best right now
to get them the knowledge that they need
so they can start doing more with it
well what I'm worried about is getting
our employees thrown in jail
I
concern vacation show me
[Music]
so so so my I like I the after look at
my retirement program and my rate of
return right now is
21.7% okay we just have
39 sorry we have so much to talk
about we got to stay on
track a little bit the rest thank you so
I just want to keep us on
track okay the only only thing I was
wondering is if we sell all those
Vehicles do we get will our insurance
premium with cersa go
down uh the German word for that is y
yes or no I say that because while we we
are getting rid of them I still have to
ensure our side by sides um yeah so
we're going to take some things off and
then um we most likely we'll buy
something next year that will add to it
I got a back truck on this agenda for
the upcoming I'm gonna have to ensure
that as well so mind yeah sorry and then
I if they buy this roller you know this
asphalt roller I'll have to cheer that
there's a whole lot
of we will probably see a decrease or a
dip but it won't be
much okay are we on property schedule
now can every time on insurance is if
you want to yes yeah I just want to just
ask about as I was going through um our
property what's that I cannot remember
the
one former Water Treatment Plant like
why is that still on here if it burns to
the ground we can collect on
it and are you referring to the old 500
million gallon 500,000 gallons yeah so I
that's what I wanted yeah that's what I
want to ask about is it the old water
plant tank 500,000 that's
1.1 million and that is just a cement
trench in the ground that's all that it
is no roof the roof is gone it's gone
there is no
roof with a chain link fence around it
so yeah why why is it worth what because
it's also doesn't that contribute to our
to our assets like it does feel like it
artificially inflates things and do we
need to go through here and actually say
okay what are are we being
too like too liberal with what our
building value is um okay so if you're
looking at the lower Water Treatment
Plant we we colloquially call that the
clock plant um the to rebuild that plant
you're looking at like three million
bucks and so that's why it's it's it's
assessed at that the tank is separate
that's that next line item that million
gallon tank um and I guess what are we
looking at for the
contributions yeah we're looking at like
$7,000 between the two the one million
oh between the lower plant yeah $7,000 a
year to ensure it
um it is within our it's within our cap
water Capital Improvement plan to do
something with that with that plant um
just not to make it an actual uh
finished water treatment plan would be
more like a pumping station and a raw
water
holding
tank so could we talk about the 500,000
gallon
cement SE old water old water tank I
don't even know where that one is is
that is that the one over by uh Kirby
clocks it's the Crest Haven the people
are getting Prett trashed because they
keep an eye on it and and they have
removed the roof it has gone to other
people's
property yeah a open
cement um
trench it's a trough cement and it just
has a chain Lan fence around it I mean
what
we building yeah there's like a shed out
it's not it's like a metal Hill
sh yeah I mean I think that that we do
need to look at that because if that
shows up on our on our balance sheet
like that doesn't feel right to me like
I mean the insurance is one thing like
yeah we need to have insurance there but
is it really
1.1 well you can't you so you can't use
what cers has given us for a property
value and think that that is what's on
our fixed or our uh our assets right for
our audit okay because they've been
depreciated sersa doesn't depreciate it
right they say this is what it's going
to cost to reild it okay so um our
balance sheets are showing that it's I
think it's almost pretty if it's not
fully depreciated it's pretty Dar close
okay
um but that being said if it's not
functional we have no intention of ever
making it functional um we should talk
about demolishing it and then removing
this from our L and it's a piece of town
property it is and it has the one of the
prvs is next to it too there is a prv
and that's that's for that that whole
area up top on the Basin I think it is
worth I I appreciate you saying like
demolishing it because it is at a
massive safety hazard it's like okay no
it's not going to be anybody climbs that
CH like what could that look like so we
can yeah just be safe about it that's we
that might be a good idea for an agenda
in the next few months so that we can
actually you can give us direction to
demo it you can hear from Corey um you
know about if he ever uses it for
anything yeah ay field trip if you
haven't seen it
um it's funny that I didn't realize we
had a park P house until I saw it on
this list last year and I went out to
look at this park bump house and asked
who has a key to
it we gotta work on that too so is this
something that we can task stack with is
just going through and being like even
if it's just a gut check like is there
anything else that just seems completely
unreasonable that's like why are you
paying so much Insurance when the
building value is there yes so so I've
been through this list
um you can direct me to to do but if
we're going to demo it then that would
have to be a specific direction that
comes from you so then so we can remove
it
right is there any other questions on
that property schedule I'm glad you
brought it up because something we need
to look
at see yeah and did everything get paid
for with cersa I know that the premiums
were due before this meeting before the
last meeting
um I believe
so really cck seems
like oh the renewal has been submitted
to
CBT and that had been done earlier
like
cersa oh and cersa paperwork's been
submitted because there was a
deadline oh that's for yeah I don't
believe so what I've elected is
quarterly billing so we'll get a
quarterly bill as we move forward but
we're we're we're in under all the um
deadlines those iners yeah the only one
that isn't is my bond I tried to get out
of it and now they want me to pay the
first one
[Music]
okay um then this is the vehicle
schedule um like I said I have to add a
couple more and then once we dispose of
these these things like the easygo and I
think was it the that the freight liner
um the
old is it an international
it's it's one of the vehicles that that
we were using as a water truck all fire
truck once we dispose of that I can
remove it off here yeah
so so this will be updated um as we as
we dispose of vehicles right now I've
got them insured because we still have
them
um that gem car I can't believe we have
it insured
but if the Wastewater Plant caught fire
we could collect a whole bunch of stuff
say with because it's sitting outside is
that the one I call the
bootmobile
white did you have any more questions on
vehicles anyone okay but we will update
this um one of the things that is on
here is our street sweeper um it
is it's been we've gone through it many
times but thing that always goes out is
the the belts and pulley um it's pretty
old it's 2007 um we need to really think
about
get a new one in the future year I just
don't see how we can do it this year in
this upcoming year but we it's something
that everybody loves to see the street
sweeper go out and ours leaves a big
butt Trail so that's how we're supposed
to
do
105,000 that's what they cost oh no
that's a that's maybe a six-year-old
with 10,000 hours on it it was about 250
keep going now they're pushing 325 oh my
go but they have fun to
dry
Weare high schedu they are and it's
because of all the belts and the pulley
and U and brushes yes now I did um I did
elect for the no fault waterline rupture
sewer backup again um so this is if
somebody um I don't I don't think we had
it this year but going into 25 if there
is um a sewer backup or a waterline
break in a basement any Resident can ask
to to to collect on this we'd have to
submit a claim regardless of whose fault
it is it's just something that I've
elected because it was so cheap it was
1,23 bucks so I think it was option one
that we chose how do we notify like the
citizens about that um the reason the
dedu or the reason that it's so low is
because we haven't
but if somebody were to call in and ask
about it um we could direct them that
way as of right now we don't have it so
it'll start in
25 and I think that's really
it so that was it for in larine the one
big the big big changes where Police
Department liability insurance of course
keeps going up um that's just the nature
of the the service we
offer um I did not submit the withdrawal
notice because this is by far the
cheapest inland marine and liability
insurance we will ever see no matter
where we go
so to the um and it's it's getting so to
the that cersa Underwriters are actually
in London not Kentucky London the United
Kingdom that's where cersa has to fly to
get under Riders to um back up there
with their their
costs um do you want to go back to the
packet the changes that were made for
this
meeting um okay so I hope we get to I
want to see where the reserves will end
up after Capital expenses yes so if you
can leave a little time for that I can
um okay so in the general fund um no
changes were made to property taxes
because those amendments did pass um so
I'm thinking like we're going to see a
significant reduction in property tax um
at least a $27,000
reduction um Jess is going to be here
for the next meeting she got an
application and then let's
see one of the new things is sidewalk
fee so sidewalk fee got to stay in
because it did pass and now we can use
it for new sidewalks as well I can use
it towards Smith and Grand that
realignment project it's huge pass over
60% was pretty good um so I was happy to
see that and we're going to start seeing
new sidewalks coming I'm excited for
that um short-term rental licenses
that's a new line item
103208 um I anticipate about 14,000 so
the the the license the short-term
rental ordinance that you have on the
next agenda agenda has 40 available
licences that's doesn't matter if it's a
single bedroom or Full House there are
40 regardless of what type of short-term
rental you have I'll question sorry so
i' I've come up with this number based
on um 22 bedrooms at $150 a pop and so
if I have two bedrooms that I want to
run out in my primary residence that's
$300 plus a special use review fee
because I'm in an R1 zoning so I've
contemplated those revenues in here for
both special reviews and short-term
rental licenses which means 18 of those
licenses are expected to be for that
full
$500 for a whole house that might be not
your primary residence you live in
Steamboat or you live in uh a gison and
you've got a home here second home that
you're running out as shortterm 500
bucks so that's that's where those fees
come um Highway user tax I haven't heard
anything else from the state to say that
we're going to see more
um that big reduction that I'm
anticipating going from 61,000 to 46,000
or
[Music]
47,000
um think of other big
things um transfer Revenue so 2,
22258 that's uh from Surplus that's what
everyone called reserves it's our
Surplus P you want uh this is page
12 so right now by what I have to go off
of is our fiscal year 23 audit so trusty
shorts to answer your question I to to
go with reserves I have to go by what
was audited we currently have $
4,455
1952 in unrestricted funds across all of
our funds um pulling pulling out 2,22
from um both the sales sales uh Capital
ta sales tax Capital Improvement um
sidewalk fee and our general fund uh
reserves or general fund Surplus um we
would be left
with
2,433
694 say that again 2,4
33694 now we are going to go into 2025
starting our fiscal year 24 audit in
January or February so it'll be we might
have our audit done by April be the
first time in ponus history that we're
not like deadline June 30th here you go
um which would allow me to say hey we
have this much available going in and I
anticipate this being significantly
higher um because it already is we see
that in our budget actuals every month
right um so is all of that the reserve
of the two wait what was oh you can't
see the calculator
it's the transfer basically two million
is that all for Capital Improvements or
is there any of that that's funding
General like just operations we are not
doing operations with this this is 100%
if we don't in the next meeting you're
going to see us asking to go for a bunch
of Grants um one of them being a raise
Grant to to get the balance of the money
needed for Fifth and Grand of $1.9
million um then you'll see that go way
way down so what this is buying is like
cameras computers um those kinds of
things it's really going towards Capital
outlet but the big Capital outlay right
now is 50 Grand yes and does this in
this 2 million this doesn't include
water no that's GNA so I'll get to that
one and and garbage in a second garbage
I'm kind of not relying on the 23 audit
I'm relying on where we're at right now
because we're going to have a big
Surplus I'll talk about that one I'll
get there here in a second um let's see
admin not much changed nothing changed
in Personnel Services nothing changed in
operating things did change in capital
out way um and that is uh let's see I uh
Treasures Fe was already there that's
what the county takes from us every time
they give us sales tax they take a fee
um and we recently learned that they may
be taking more than what they should be
um commissioner C seems to think like
they for back the badge bill is supposed
to take 1% We Believe they've been
taking 2% and that's been countywide so
that's something um a band of
municipalities are looking into with the
county um but we're still budgeting for
about $7,000 to be taken out um from all
of our sales Tex Machinery equipment is
where the cameras and are coming out of
um next that 1041 74 and then also
budgeting for roof replacement uh
because as we've talked about the roof
over my office uh is really bad um then
Matt has a sink over his
office um that's part that's not a joke
it's really there uh building
improvements um is also uh I think
that's that's part of the um that roof
repair as
well okay law enforcement nothing
changed in Personnel Services nothing
changed operating um what did change is
capital outlay that's that machinery and
equipment that's his mobile data
terminals those laptops for his uh for
squads and then also his his share of U
the
cameras Oh I cut off the sorry um
building only thing in here is legal
engineering Professional Services we
have two contracts um one with the city
of Delta for inspection services and one
with shakota for building uh to be our
building uh building official so we
don't pay insurance we don't pay all
this other stuff out of building it's
strictly just these
contracts nothing changed there streets
this one changed and so streets is
operating so um you'll see a number of
things listed under operating expenses
um that weren't filled into the last
time I said oops that was an oopsy
um let's
see repairs and maintenance so this is
this would be like for getting cold
patch things like that
15,000 um we've significantly reduced
the amount of Engineering Services we'll
need because we are 100% designed in
fifth in Grand um so we the only thing
that we'll have is like construction
inspection engineering but that's going
to come out of capital outlay for the
actual Fifth and Grand realignment
project um then when we go down Capital
outlay you'll see Fifth Street
realignment the reason it's not that
full $2.9 million is um is because part
a portion of that is water it's funded
out of water because it's a water line
as well um machinery and equipment I
added 25,000 in there um actually that
was that's a
carryover and that was
for um like a like a if they wanted to
get a new vehicle they needed something
um
to help with uh Street Paving that's
what that's
for machine uh the grants project at
325,000 so Fifth Street realignment has
its own code but the grant project is
10475 that's that Safe Streets for all
Grant um it is a it is Grant funded it's
listed in general fund Revenue as Grant
funded um but our portion of it is
75,000 that's why that outlay is more
than the $250,000 Grand
okay and we've been following grants on
that budget to actual sheet um I do have
two three to add um I just couldn't
figure out how to add them for this go
around um they're 10,000 two of them are
$10,000 a piece it's for um
reimbursement for the project needs
assessment for water and the project
needs assessment that we're working on
for waste water and then
200,000 200 to 300,000 for um
reimbursing us for all of the design
work that's been down at phase one so
they we will receive that for
reimbursement this year before December
31st for audit so we're going to see
about
$320,000 that's awesome it's coming I
haven't added it in to our our budget
actual sheet I'll do it for next month
but that would go in this in this budget
that streets or go up in Revenue no so
that'll end up going into Surplus okay
so we'll have higher Surplus okay good
I I I'm glad to have done it I should
have done it earlier but I'm glad to go
surprise more than what we thought um
Parks um not nothing changed in Parks
except for the machinery and equipment
that's for their cameras um so that's in
Parks now listed under
10467 um and then whatever's left over
they have a serious need for a lawnmower
um I'm trying to that's what that um
that's why there's something in
Machinery equipment and capital outlay
um it's so whatever's left over they can
buy a new new lawn mower instead of the
oh no it'll be a zero turn like the big
yeah yeah it'll be a right on if they
had a walk behind push mower it would
take him six weeks to do it
one a reel no canot use a reel so but
we've budgeted for those things so that
they can get them Cory had been out
that's why his capital
um thing for in in uh cleargov wasn't
completed so both Corey and Nikki were
out um so that's why it it'll go in
there eventually for the final budget
you'll see
it
water
um after so we had a preim
pre-application meeting today with DOA
um where we're talking about submitting
before December 2nd another 900
our million dollar grant for um EF tier
2 that is to go towards our Western
water loop realignment project and rep
Dana asked us to change our project from
the name of realignment to replacement
because we are re replacing even though
we are speci
realigning um because it gets it's
better when you go before the board for
that grant funding so we are changing
the name of that project to the Western
room replacement project but we're
asking for a million do to go towards
the $7.2 million cost um it is it is
stackable in addition to the $965,000
we've already received for our water
tank realignment project so this we can
stack them and we're going to go and ask
for that money
um but what we what we learned is that
we will have to raise ours um so uh Dana
Dana ask that rather than wait until May
that um I present again a
fiveyear thing for this year to go in
December to raise our rates for usage
our base our base rates are fine it's
our usage rates that we go up especially
for things over 20,000 gallons a month
so that's coming just yeah he was happy
to see that we had already done one but
when I said something like you know we
based it on a lot more water usage or
water consumption that we actually use
after we did a meter audit project he
said you're going to want to update
those
so in order to be able to for them to
say yes to the Grant and then also in
order for them to be able to say yes to
the load that we're applying for in
January which is the bigy that's the
bigy yeah so that's coming um darn
it um got the little your little number
one where it says budget revenues differ
from the 20-year cash flow analysis
budget is in whole number of cash flows
in the penny what do you mean by that
again so um have you you may not have
seen the 20-year cash flow analysis I
did oh you did yeah so um I did that
based on consumption and it went by
rates and so it is that is to the penny
so if we were if you get if you get
charged um a usage rate of 1678 for
th000 after 15,000 gallons that's to the
penny this one is whole numbers because
it's budget I typically put on your on a
revenue I tend to be low
in Revenue so I round down and then
expenses I round up um yeah so I have
some sort of a cushion um we're gonna
have to have to make that
change
sorry you sure will and then I'll also I
also have to clean up trash um because H
I should just say it now um y'all passed
a
resolution increase trash rates but it's
set by ordinance you can't change an
ordinance rate set with a resolution so
um we're going to have to go back and
redo that ordinance and then do a
resolution so an ordinance will say or B
collection rates uh collect you know as
as changed from time by time to time by
resolution and then right after that
will be a resolution it's got to happen
going into
25 it's the only one we have to clean up
yeah um and then Wastewater rates we're
not proposing anything yet but um once
we get this PNA done we're going to know
that we're going to have rates
that or you'll start looking at a sewer
district so combining sewers with hotus
or other outline counties and then you
lose control over it and it becomes a
taxing district and then we get an extra
tax so there's there's other ways to do
it I just don't like that
route I do have a question about
sanitation yeah you know I know you've
mentioned this idea of having like
standard trash
bins is that in there I
think because I feel like this is I'm
like a I hate this idea but it sounds
like it's just going to this is a work
session yes you can say it I was
wondering if there's going to be any
discussion about that or is it just a
done deal nothing is a done deal however
um I should let you know
the number of customer complaints that
we get um or the interactions that we
have the negative interactions that we
have also around are because of trash
and it's uh because some people may be
paying for that lesser amount and then
they have six trash BS and I don't I
don't need to dis debate what it is now
I just think it's worth having a
discussion at a future meeting and to
yeah I know you've talked about this
many times but yeah um yeah and so the
idea going to get a lot of people
confing this route too well so the idea
is it's no longer that you have your
personal trash can now it's a town trash
can that if we beat up we're going to
fix it right and so instead of my you
know my trash Li you know they threw my
trash FL away or you know on a windy day
it's that trash FL is attached and it's
it's not going anywhere and so there's
there'll be two sizes 35 gallons that's
for that lower lesser amount and then a
0 gallon trash can for anyone that's
paying higher and so if they want um if
some people have five or six trash cans
they'll get two 90 gallon bins so it's I
can then then I can track it I know who
whose bin belongs to who that part of
our code that is archaic that says you
have to put your your address on your
trash cans um wouldn't be an issue
anymore I think that there's also a
discussion about are there ways that we
can reduce trash because what I'm
hearing is this is going to increase
trash because it's and so that's a
discussion I'm more interested in having
is what can we do to help reduce the
amount that goes into the landfill
through recycling through compost
through waste reduction and not being
like Oh let's make it easier for you to
generate more trash so I feel pretty
passionate no I understand and I think
it'll be interesting to see if it really
does increase trash or we just have a
better understanding of how much trash
we actually picking up um but what we
what we also need to do is look at um go
going into 25 and applying for a cdph
technical assistance grant to help us
understand what it would take to start a
recycling program to start what we've
talked about in the past for a um
um compost compost plan and they can
give us an idea on how to implement it
um that would go in conjunction with
this there's no way come with this
budget pass
you know I I would still have to get
quotes to find trash cans you know to
purchase and then it's not like they'd
show up immediately we're talking we're
six to seven month implementation at a
minimum so but we do certainly need to
go for City pH techn assistance it's
what came up in our um in our
comprehensive planning meetings as well
as doing some sort of question more of a
historical question one point we lived
in town and they set up a large dump at
the city park and everybody's allow was
after a storm but they just kept do for
a long time um are you you I believe you
are talking about the cleanup days that
I have not budgeted for contemplated in
the 25th budget does that
save does that make is that more
expensive or does it save on Labor uh
what we found was that it was much more
expensive because people were throwing
away electronics and then we can't take
those to the landfill and so then the
town gets stiff because it's hazardous
materials so was more expensive more
expensive just more clarifi um we have
two we need a f minute break there's two
minutes okay um almost done so uh
sanitation was was one of them
Wastewater um what did we do there was a
we we contemplated stuff for like
cameras in all of these funds and then I
wanted to show you water really quick
that
um the who what what1 uh n 19 okay I
went back up to 19 thank you so uh raw
water metering is contemplated in this
budget it's Grant funded um capital
outlay is cameras and things like that
that's that's budgeted um water tank
realigning is its
owned uh its own fund waste West Loop
Improvement project um which we now have
to call the West Loop replacement
project is its own water smart is in
there and then machinery and equipment
or cameras so it's all there uh but then
what was it it was the I
start Capital outlay that
111,000 that's for fifth in main as uh
Fifth Fifth in Grand as
well okay that was that was that was it
what are our next steps so with the
budget um we have have it done by the
15th of December so my plan unless you
want to have another another Workshop is
December 12th you'll get a packaged
budget with our Capital Improvement plan
our water Capital Improvement plan all
of the narratives that show this is the
admin Department here's how many
employees we have here's how many
employees we're proposing to increase or
decrease those cover sheets all of that
will be put together will also include
um your strategic plan that with these
SWAT analyses um on what guided
US unless you want to have another
Workshop
which we can very well
do feel pretty comfortable with what we
have in front of us I know you're gonna
add in more to that first
page I I'm kind of okay with it and by
that time I'll have a final number from
the assessor's office on what our
property tax will be I don't anticipate
it going down um because I went really
conservative on that
lo I don't everybody though I'm agre so
December 12th I'll have a packaged
budget for you in that agenda packet you
can go from
there of course all right five minute
three oh you're
good know the airport so that's what's
up on the screen right now I think you
had a question on the airport stand
airport
out but you can see that like this is
money that we had reserves it's money
that was spe specifically collected for
the airport and what we're looking at is
paying for the design for the apron next
year based on what we've received I've
been working to try to get that cell
tower to get T-Mobile on it